<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Perl</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://perl.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>There's More Than One Way To Aggregate It</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-03-30T12:53:18Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://perl.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://perl.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Installation of Perl on Mac 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/yukikimoto/installation-of-perl-on-mac-2022-31k4" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Perl is already installed on Mac. </p>

<p>Execute the "Terminal" application and input the following command to check the version of Perl.</p>

<p>This article is originally <a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20180814153419.html">Installation of Perl on Mac | Perl ABC</a></p>

<pre>
perl -v
</pre>

<p>You can see the version of Perl.</p>

<pre>
This is perl 5, version 28, subversion 2 (v5.28.2) built for darwin-thread-multi-2level
(with 2 registered patches, see perl -V for more detail)
</pre>

<h3>
  
  
  Installation of Perl on your home directory
</h3>

<p>If you want to install the specific version of Perl on your home directory, you can use <strong>perlbrew</strong> or <strong>plenv</strong> according to your taste.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20110220130464.html">perlbrew - Install Perl on your home directory</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20180816153437.html">plenv - Install Perl on your home directory</a></li>
</ul>

</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Yuki Kimoto</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/yukikimoto/installation-of-perl-on-mac-2022-31k4</id>
    <published>2022-03-30T08:18:08Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-30T08:18:08Z</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="mac"/>
    <category term="begnners"/>
    <category term="programing"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Installation of msys2 and Perl on Windows 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/yukikimoto/installation-of-msys2-and-perl-on-windows-2022-i81" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Explains how to install &lt;a href="https://www.msys2.org"&gt;msys2&lt;/a&gt; and Perl on Windows. The msys2 is a software to build a Linux-like environment on Windows. Perl can be installed on msys2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is originally &lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20180806153350.html"&gt;Installation of msys2 and Perl on Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--FlE5JWCh--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/msys2.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--FlE5JWCh--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/msys2.png" alt="" width="582" height="371"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On msys2, you can use &lt;a href="https://en.linux.perlzemi.com/blog/20200211081227.html"&gt;Linux commands&lt;/a&gt; such as &lt;a href="https://en.linux.perlzemi.com/blog/20191126082723.html"&gt;ls&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.linux.perlzemi.com/blog/20200113083613.html"&gt;cat&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.linux.perlzemi.com/blog/20190129171737.html"&gt;tar&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://en.git.perlzemi.com/"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;. The terminal charset is UTF-8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The msys2 is compatible with POSIX. The Perl web framework such as &lt;a href="https://en.mojolicious.perlzemi.com/"&gt;Mojolicious&lt;/a&gt; can work correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Download of msys2
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's download msys2 from the following page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.msys2.org/"&gt;msys2.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click "the installer: msys2-x86_64-20220319.exe" and donwload msys2 to your desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Installation of msys2
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Double-click the msys2 icon on your desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Finish. The msys2 will start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Execution of msys2
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You close msys2. Next time, you find the msys2 program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Windows Start Menu" | "List of Apps" | "MSYS2 64bit".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will see three msys2 program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;MSYS2 MinGW 64bit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;MSYS2 MINGW 32bit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MSYS2 MSYS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;MSYS2 MSYS&lt;/strong&gt;. This is needed to run Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"MSYS2 MinGW 64bit" and "MSYS2 MINGW 32bit" are used to create Windows native apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Instalation of Perl on msys2
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's install Perl. &lt;strong&gt;pacman&lt;/strong&gt; is the package manager of msys2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
pacman -S perl perl-CPAN msys2-devel make libcrypt-devel
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copy the above command and paste it on msys2 by clicking the right mouse button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be asked if you want to install them. Press "Enter".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following softwares will be installed for Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;perl (perl)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;cpan (perl-CPAN)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;gcc (msys2-devel)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;make (make)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;crypt.h (libcrypt-devel)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some Perl modules are written by C/C++ language. To compile these modules, &lt;a href="https://en.linux.perlzemi.com/blog/20201216103956.html"&gt;gcc&lt;/a&gt; and make are required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Check of Perl Installation
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checks of Perl installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
perl -v
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see the version of Perl, the Perl installation is succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
This is perl 5, version 24, subversion 4 (v5.24.4) built for x86_64-msys-thread-multi
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Installation of CPAN Modules
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make sure your Perl environment is built correctly, install some Perl modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some CPAN modules expect Unix/Linux environments. Make sure the symlink works properly on msys2 with the following command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
export MSYS = winsymlinks
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the first time to use cpan, you will be asked if you want to set cpan automatically. Press "Enter".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
cpan Mojolicious
cpan JSON::XS
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the installation of these modules are finished, your Perl environment on msys2 is built correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <author>
      <name>Yuki Kimoto</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/yukikimoto/installation-of-msys2-and-perl-on-windows-2022-i81</id>
    <published>2022-03-29T08:35:20Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-29T08:35:20Z</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="programing"/>
    <category term="beginners"/>
    <category term="webdev"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>#557 - Human languages</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/557.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Hi there!</p>
<p>First of all, let me congratulate <b>Mohammad S. Anwar</b> for editing 100 issues of <a href="https://perlweekly.com/">Perl Weekly</a>. If you visit the main page of the website you will see a list of all editors, past and present, in the order they joined and with the number of issues they edited. Let me thank all of you!</p>
<p>Learning programming languages is not easy, but if you compare that to learning human languages you'll notice that it has a lot more difficulties. Human languages have much bigger vocabulary and much bigger grammar with lots of exceptions. This already makes it much harder to learn on, but in addition it is hard to get fast and cheap feedback. Something you are given by the compiler/interpreter of your language. You can even add more by writing your own tests and setting up a CI system. That's part of the value <a href="https://www.duolingo.com/">DuoLingo</a> provides. Fast and cheap feedback. However it is proprietary.  <a href="https://librelingo.app/">LibreLingo</a> is an open source alternative to which I started to contribute. The most fun part for me is actually trying to write a course: building a dictionary and writing sample sentences.</p>
<p>Enjoy your week!</p></div>
    </content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/557.html</id>
    <published>2022-03-28T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-28T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Dancer2: Plackup reload  on Windows and Linux</title>
  <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Part of the Dancer2 video course available both to <a href="/pro">Pro</a> subscribers and attendees of the <a href="https://leanpub.com/c/dancer">Perl Dancer course</a> on Leanpub.
<p>
]]></summary>
  <updated>2022-03-28T07:30:01Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://perlmaven.com/dancer2-plackup-reload"/>  <id>https://perlmaven.com/dancer2-plackup-reload</id>
  <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Part of the Dancer2 video course available both to <a href="/pro">Pro</a> subscribers and attendees of the <a href="https://leanpub.com/c/dancer">Perl Dancer course</a> on Leanpub.
<p>
]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Gabor Szabo</name>
    </author>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Three means and big bases</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/simongreennet/three-means-and-big-bases-3o2f" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h2>
  
  
  Weekly Challenge 157
</h2>

<p>I'm back after the three week hiatus!</p>

<p><a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-157/">Challenge</a>, <a href="https://github.com/manwar/perlweeklychallenge-club/tree/master/challenge-157/sgreen">My solution</a></p>

<h2>
  
  
  TASK #1 › Pythagorean Means
</h2>

<h3>
  
  
  Task
</h3>

<p>You are given a set of integers.</p>

<p>Write a script to compute all three <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pythagorean_means">Pythagorean Means</a> i.e Arithmetic Mean, Geometric Mean and Harmonic Mean of the given set of integers.</p>

<h3>
  
  
  My solution
</h3>

<p>This is a relatively straight forward task. The Wikipedia page provides the necessary formulas and we can use the <code>sum</code> <code>reduce</code> and <code>lambda</code> functions to calculate the required figures. Finally we use the <code>round</code> function to print the results to one decimal place.</p>

<p>The Perl code is similar to the Python version, except we use the product() method in List::Utils. Python's math.product is only available for Python 3.8+</p>

<p>One thing to note is if the sum of integers is 0, a division by zero error might occur when calculating the harmonic mean. I'm not catching this and let the error pass to the user.</p>

<h3>
  
  
  Examples
</h3>



<div class="highlight js-code-highlight">
<pre class="highlight plaintext"><code>$ ./ch-1.py 1 3 5 6 9
AM = 4.8, GM = 3.8, HM = 2.8

$ ./ch-1.py 2 4 6 8 10
AM = 6.0, GM = 5.2, HM = 4.4

$ ./ch-1.py 1 2 3 4 5
AM = 3.0, GM = 2.6, HM = 2.2
</code></pre>

</div>



<h2>
  
  
  TASK #2 › Brazilian Number
</h2>

<h3>
  
  
  Task
</h3>

<p>You are given a number <code>$n</code> &gt; 3.</p>

<p>Write a script to find out if the given number is a Brazilian Number. A positive integer number <code>N</code> has at least one natural number <code>B</code> where <code>1 &lt; B &lt; N-1</code> where the representation of <code>N</code> in base <code>B</code> has [the] same digits.</p>

<h3>
  
  
  My solution
</h3>

<p>This was an interesting task. We can't convert numbers into a different base simply by using letters and numbers. For example 1282 is 22 in base 640, but how would you express 639 in the same base?</p>

<p>For this task I considered a value having the same digits even if the number itself has different digits. For example, 925 is express as (25)(25) in base 36.</p>

<p>The guts of this task is to convert the number <code>n</code> in base 10 to a specified base, which I have called <code>b</code>. The function is called <code>same_digits</code>. I take the modulus (remainder) of <code>n</code> and <code>b</code> and make this value <code>d</code>. I then do an integer division and repeat this process comparing that <code>n % b</code> is <code>d</code>. I return <code>False</code> if any digit isn't the same, or <code>True</code> if they all are.</p>

<p>Then it's just a matter of having a loop from 2 to <code>n - 2</code>, and calling the <code>same_digits</code> function for each base. If there is a match, I print <code>1</code> (and the base), or <code>0</code> otherwise.</p>

<p>The Perl code is a transliteration of the Python code.</p>

<h3>
  
  
  Examples
</h3>



<div class="highlight js-code-highlight">
<pre class="highlight plaintext"><code>$ ./ch-2.py 6
0

$ ./ch-2.py 7
1 (base 2)

$ ./ch-2.py 8
1 (base 3)
</code></pre>

</div>



</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Simon Green</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/simongreennet/three-means-and-big-bases-3o2f</id>
    <published>2022-03-27T10:50:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-27T10:50:19Z</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="python"/>
    <category term="theweeklychallenge"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Installing Perl: A Chicken-and-Egg Problem</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2022/03/installing-perl-a-chicken-and-egg-problem.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2022:/users/tom_wyant//506.10745</id>
    <published>2022-03-27T06:30:01Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-27T06:31:19Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tom Wyant</name>
        
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/">
        <![CDATA[<p>A couple days ago the SD card on a Raspberry Pi lost its beady little mind, and I ended up rebuilding the system from scratch. I generally build my own Perl (also from scratch) and then install the modules I need. So that I can have a log file to rummage through in the event of a problem, I start by configuring the CPAN client interactively, and then doing</p>

<pre>
$ cpan YAML 2&gt;&amp;1 | tee YAML.log
$ cpan Bundle::CPAN 2&gt;&amp;1 | tee YAML.log
</pre>

<p>Normally I would now install the modules specific to my use. But when I tried this time I got</p>

<pre>
HTTP::Tiny failed with an internal error: IO::Socket::SSL 1.42 must be installed for https support
Net::SSLeay 1.49 must be installed for https support
</pre>

<p>What happened here is that last fall the CPAN client was updated in response to a spoofing threat. The change consisted of adding a Boolean configuration item, <code>pushy_https</code>, which causes the client to ignore its <code>urllist</code> configuration and retrieve modules from <code>https://www.cpan.org/</code>. Now, core Perl does not support <code>https:</code>, I have to get it by installing (among other things) <code>Net::SSLeay</code>. But Perl 5.34.1, being a maintenance release, comes with the same CPAN client as 5.34.0 -- that is, it does not have <code>pushy_https</code> setting and associated machinery. But when I installed <code>Bundle::CPAN</code>, I got the latest CPAN client, but <strong>not</strong> the <code>https:</code> support it wants by default.</p>

<p>Fortunately, all was not lost. The default value of <code>urllist</code> is <code>http://www.perl.org/</code>, and <code>http:</code> is in fact supported. So I could simply set <code>pushy_https</code> to <code>0</code>, install what I needed, and then set <code>pushy_https</code> to <code>1</code> and continue my merry way.</p>

<p>But I wondered what someone unfamiliar with recent Perl history would make of this. Would this person fight through to the solution, or simply give up on Perl in disgust?</p>

<p>Obviously if core Perl supported <code>https:</code> this would not be an issue. But much as I would like to see that, I understand (or at least sympathize) with why it is not happening any time soon. And I can not advocate defaulting the CPAN client to unsafe behavior.</p>

<p>But is there no way to give the poor user any help? The unconfigured value of <code>pushy_https</code> is <code>undef</code>, which the CPAN client interprets as true. Could that value at least cause a more helpful error message?</p>

<p><cite>Truth in advertising: normally I install from a Mini-CPAN mirror, so in my case I just pointed the CPAN client to that mirror. But I thought the more typical case was to install from www.cpan.org, so after I got my Raspberry Pi going I did that with another Perl install, just to be sure I was reporting a general problem and not one I had completely caused myself.</cite></p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Perl Weekly Challenge 157: Pythagorean Means and Brazilian Number</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/laurent_r/2022/03/perl-weekly-challenge-157-pythagorean-means-and-brazilian-number.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2022:/users/laurent_r//3226.10744</id>
    <published>2022-03-26T04:06:35Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-27T03:45:29Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>laurent_r</name>
        <uri>https://laurent-rosenfeld.developpez.com/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/laurent_r/">
        <![CDATA[<p>These are some answers to the Week 157 of the <a href="https://perlweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-157/">Perl Weekly Challenge</a> organized by <a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/mohammad_s_anwar/">Mohammad S. Anwar</a>.</p>

<p><em>Spoiler Alert:</em> This weekly challenge deadline is due in a couple of days from now (on March 27, 2022 at 24:00). This blog post offers some solutions to this challenge, please don’t read on if you intend to complete the challenge on your own.</p>

<h2>Task 1: Pythagorean Numbers</h2>

<p><em>You are given a set of integers.</em></p>

<p><em>Write a script to compute all three Pythagorean Means i.e Arithmetic Mean, Geometric Mean and Harmonic Mean of the given set of integers. Please refer to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pythagorean_means">wikipedia page</a> for more informations.</em></p>

<p><em>Example 1:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: @n = (1,3,5,6,9)
Output: AM = 4.8, GM = 3.9, HM = 2.8
</code></pre>

<p><em>Example 2:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: @n = (2,4,6,8,10)
Output: AM = 6.0, GM = 5.2, HM = 4.4
</code></pre>

<p><em>Example 3:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: @n = (1,2,3,4,5)
Output: AM = 3.0, GM = 2.6, HM = 2.2
</code></pre>

<p>Since the task description doesn&#8217;t explain it, let me provide some formulas for arithmetic mean (AM), geometric mean (GM) and harmonic mean (AM):</p>

<p><img alt="Pytagorean_means.jpg" src="http://blogs.perl.org/users/laurent_r/Pytagorean_means.jpg" width="301" height="195" class="mt-image-none" style="" /></p>

<h3>Pythagorean Numbers in Raku</h3>

<p>The Raku build-in <code>[ ]</code> <a href="https://docs.raku.org/language/operators#index-entry-[]_(reduction_metaoperators">reduce metaoperator</a> makes it possible to compute each of the means with just one simple code-line:</p>

<pre><code>for (1,3,5,6,9), (2,4,6,8,10), (1,2,3,4,5) -&gt; @in {
    my $n = @in.elems;
    my $am = ([+] @in)/ $n;
    my $gm = ([*] @in)** (1/$n);
    my $hm = $n / ([+] map { 1/$_}, @in);
    printf  "%-10s -&gt; AM: %0.1f, GM: %0.1f, HM: %0.1f\n", "@in[]", $am, $gm, $hm;
}
</code></pre>

<p>This script displays the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ raku ./means.raku
1 3 5 6 9  -&gt; AM: 4.8, GM: 3.8, HM: 2.8
2 4 6 8 10 -&gt; AM: 6.0, GM: 5.2, HM: 4.4
1 2 3 4 5  -&gt; AM: 3.0, GM: 2.6, HM: 2.2
</code></pre>

<h3>Pythagorean Numbers in Perl</h3>

<p>Perl doesn&#8217;t have a built-in <code>reduce</code> operator. We could either implement a <code>reduce</code> subroutine (I&#8217;ve done that in some previous PWC challenge), or compute each mean separately. Here, I&#8217;ve chosen the second option.</p>

<pre><code>use strict;
use warnings;
use feature "say";

for my $test ([1,3,5,6,9], [2,4,6,8,10], [1,2,3,4,5]) {
    my @in = @$test;
    my $n = scalar @in;

    my $sum = 0;
    $sum += $_ for @in;
    my $am = $sum / $n;

    my $prod = 1;
    $prod *= $_ for @in;
    my $gm = $prod ** (1/$n);

    my $invsum = 0;
    $invsum += 1/$_ for @in;
    my $hm = $n / $invsum;
    printf  "%-10s -&gt; AM: %0.1f, GM: %0.1f, HM: %0.1f\n", "@in", $am, $gm, $hm;
}
</code></pre>

<p>This script displays the following output:</p>

<p>$ perl ./means.pl
1 3 5 6 9  -> AM: 4.8, GM: 3.8, HM: 2.8
2 4 6 8 10 -> AM: 6.0, GM: 5.2, HM: 4.4
1 2 3 4 5  -> AM: 3.0, GM: 2.6, HM: 2.2</p>

<h2>Task 2: Brazilian numbers</h2>

<p><em>You are given a number <code>$n</code> > 3.</em></p>

<p><em>Write a script to find out if the given number is a Brazilian Number.</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A positive integer number N has at least one natural number B where 1 &lt; B &lt; N-1 where the representation of N in base B has same digits.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Example 1:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: $n = 7
Output: 1

Since 7 in base 2 is 111.
</code></pre>

<p><em>Example 2:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: $n = 6
Output: 0

Since 6 in base 2 is 110,
      6 in base 3 is 20 and
      6 in base 4 is 12.
</code></pre>

<p><em>Example 3:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: $n = 8
Output: 1

Since 8 in base 3 is 22.
</code></pre>

<p>Well to start with, I find the above definition of a Brazilian number to be not completely clear. This is another definition:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Brazilian&#8221; numbers are numbers n such that there is a natural number b with 1 &lt; b &lt; n-1 such that the representation of n in base b has all equal digits.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>First, the condition <code>b &lt; n-1</code> is important because every number <code>n</code> has representation 11 in base <code>n-1</code>. Then, every even number <code>2P</code> >= 8 is Brazilian, because <code>2P = 2(P-1) + 2</code>, which is 22 in base <code>P-1</code> when <code>P-1 &gt; 2</code>. Finally, we will extend the task to a search of all Brazilian numbers less than or equal to 36, since working with bases larger than 36 (the <code>1..9, 'a'..'z'</code> range) would require a different data model.</p>

<h3>Brazilian Numbers in Raku</h3>

<p>We use the Raku built-in <a href="https://docs.raku.org/routine/base">base</a> to convert the input number to a string using <code>$base</code> as base.</p>

<pre><code>sub is-brazilian (Int $n) {
    return True if $n %% 2 and $n &gt;= 8;
    return False if $n &lt;= 3;
    for 2..^($n-1) -&gt; $base {
        return True if $n.base($base) ~~ /^(\d)$0+$/;
    }
    False;
}

say "Brazilian numbers less than or equal to 36 are:";
for 1..36 -&gt; $m {
    print "$m " if is-brazilian $m;
}
say "";
</code></pre>

<p>This script displays the following Brazilian numbers:</p>

<pre><code>$ raku ./brazilian_number.raku
Brazilian numbers less than or equal to 36 are:
7 8 10 12 13 14 15 16 18 20 21 22 24 26 27 28 30 31 32 33 34 35 36
</code></pre>

<h3>Brazilian Numbers in Perl</h3>

<p>The program below if basically a port to Perl of the Raku program above. The only significant change is that we had to implement the <code>to_base_b</code> subroutine to perform decimal-to-some_base conversion.</p>

<pre><code>use strict;
use warnings;
use feature qw /say/;
use constant DIGITS =&gt; ('0'..'9', 'A'..'Z');

sub to_base_b { # Converts decimal number to base b string
    my($dec, $base) = @_;
    my @digits;
    while ($dec) {
        unshift @digits, (DIGITS)[$dec % $base];
        $dec = int($dec/$base);
    }
    return join "", @digits;
}

sub is_brazilian {
    my $n = shift;
    return 1 if $n % 2 == 0 and $n &gt;= 8;
    return 0 if $n &lt;= 3;
    for my $base (2..$n-2) {
        return 1 if to_base_b($n, $base) =~ /^(\d)\1+$/;
    }
    0;
}

say "Brazilian numbers less than or equal to 36 are:";
for my $m (1..36) {
    print "$m " if is_brazilian($m);
}
say "";
</code></pre>

<p>This program displays the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ perl brazilian_number.pl
Brazilian numbers less than or equal to 36 are:
7 8 10 12 13 14 15 16 18 20 21 22 24 26 27 28 30 31 32 33 34 35 36
</code></pre>

<h2>Wrapping up</h2>

<p>The next week Perl Weekly Challenge will start soon. If you want to participate in this challenge, please check https://perlweeklychallenge.org/ and make sure you answer the challenge before 23:59 BST (British summer time) on April 3, 2022. And, please, also spread the word about the Perl Weekly Challenge if you can.</p>
]]>
        

    </content>
</entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-8512928937749428916</id>
    <published>2022-03-26T15:45:00.000+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-26T15:45:22.004+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(ccclxxxv) 10 great CPAN modules released last week</title>
    <content type="html">Updates for &lt;i&gt;great CPAN modules&lt;/i&gt; released last week. A module is considered &lt;i&gt;great&lt;/i&gt; if its favorites count is greater or equal than 12.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/NICS/Catmandu-1.2019' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Catmandu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - a data toolkit &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.2019&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-21&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 21&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.2018 was 12 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/ETJ/GraphQL-0.54' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;GraphQL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Perl implementation of GraphQL &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.54&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-24&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 18&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.53 was 2 months, 9 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/JHTHORSEN/JSON-Validator-5.08' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;JSON::Validator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Validate data against a JSON schema &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;5.08&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-25&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 29&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 5.05 was 2 months, 19 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/BINGOS/Module-CoreList-5.20220320' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Module::CoreList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - what modules shipped with versions of perl &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;5.20220320&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-20&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 37&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 5.20220313 was 5 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/DBOOK/Mojo-SQLite-3.009' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Mojo::SQLite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - A tiny Mojolicious wrapper for SQLite &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;3.009&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-23&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 24&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 3.008 was 3 months, 25 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/SRI/Mojolicious-9.23' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Mojolicious&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Real-time web framework &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;9.23&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-25&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 468&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 9.22 was 5 months, 4 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/JHTHORSEN/Mojolicious-Plugin-OpenAPI-5.05' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Mojolicious::Plugin::OpenAPI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - OpenAPI / Swagger plugin for Mojolicious &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;5.05&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-25&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 41&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 5.02 was 4 months, 4 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/BINGOS/POE-1.370' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;POE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Portable, event-loop agnostic eventy networking and multitasking. &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.370&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-23&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 51&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.368 was 2 years, 1 month, 21 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/KIMOTO/SPVM-0.9509' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;SPVM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Static Perl Virtual Machine. Fast Calculation, Fast Array Operation, and Easy C/C++ Binding. &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.9509&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-23&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 23&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.9508 was 19 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/GHENRY/ZMQ-FFI-1.18' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;ZMQ::FFI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - version agnostic Perl bindings for zeromq using ffi &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.18&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-21&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 16&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.17 was 3 years, 7 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/8512928937749428916/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/ccclxxxv-10-great-cpan-modules-released.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/8512928937749428916"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/8512928937749428916"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/ccclxxxv-10-great-cpan-modules-released.html" title="(ccclxxxv) 10 great CPAN modules released last week"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-3599518942001300163</id>
    <published>2022-03-26T15:42:00.002+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-26T15:42:39.327+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(d) metacpan weekly report - Starman</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the weekly favourites list of CPAN distributions. Votes count: 71&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Week's winner: &lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Starman" target="_blank"&gt;Starman (+2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build date: 2022/03/26 14:42:21 GMT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clicked for &lt;u&gt;first time&lt;/u&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/App::perlvars" target="_blank"&gt;App::perlvars&lt;/a&gt; - CLI tool to detect unused variables in Perl modules&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Class::Generic" target="_blank"&gt;Class::Generic&lt;/a&gt; - Class Generic&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2::Plugin::CSRF" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2::Plugin::CSRF&lt;/a&gt; - CSRF tokens generation and validation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2::Plugin::Deferred" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2::Plugin::Deferred&lt;/a&gt; - Defer messages or data across redirections&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2::Plugin::Shutdown" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2::Plugin::Shutdown&lt;/a&gt; - Graceful shutdown your Dancer2 application&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Mo::utils" target="_blank"&gt;Mo::utils&lt;/a&gt; - Mo utilities.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/XS::libcatch" target="_blank"&gt;XS::libcatch&lt;/a&gt; - Catch test library for XS &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Increasing&lt;/u&gt; its reputation:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Alien::ImageMagick" target="_blank"&gt;Alien::ImageMagick&lt;/a&gt; (+1=12)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/App::cpanminus" target="_blank"&gt;App::cpanminus&lt;/a&gt; (+1=261)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/App::Daemon" target="_blank"&gt;App::Daemon&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/App::perlimports" target="_blank"&gt;App::perlimports&lt;/a&gt; (+1=8)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/autouse" target="_blank"&gt;autouse&lt;/a&gt; (+1=6)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/AWS::Lambda" target="_blank"&gt;AWS::Lambda&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/bareword::filehandles" target="_blank"&gt;bareword::filehandles&lt;/a&gt; (+1=3)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Carton" target="_blank"&gt;Carton&lt;/a&gt; (+1=109)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/CGI::Ajax" target="_blank"&gt;CGI::Ajax&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/CGI::Tiny" target="_blank"&gt;CGI::Tiny&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Class::Autouse" target="_blank"&gt;Class::Autouse&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Daemon::Generic" target="_blank"&gt;Daemon::Generic&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2&lt;/a&gt; (+1=127)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2::Plugin::Auth::Extensible" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2::Plugin::Auth::Extensible&lt;/a&gt; (+1=6)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2::Plugin::Database" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2::Plugin::Database&lt;/a&gt; (+1=6)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2::Plugin::DBIC" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2::Plugin::DBIC&lt;/a&gt; (+1=13)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2::Session::Redis" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2::Session::Redis&lt;/a&gt; (+1=3)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer2::Template::Xslate" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer2::Template::Xslate&lt;/a&gt; (+1=4)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dancer::Plugin::Auth::Extensible" target="_blank"&gt;Dancer::Plugin::Auth::Extensible&lt;/a&gt; (+1=9)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Data::FormValidator" target="_blank"&gt;Data::FormValidator&lt;/a&gt; (+1=13)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Data::TableReader" target="_blank"&gt;Data::TableReader&lt;/a&gt; (+1=4)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Date" target="_blank"&gt;Date&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/DBD::MariaDB" target="_blank"&gt;DBD::MariaDB&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/DBIx::Class::Helpers" target="_blank"&gt;DBIx::Class::Helpers&lt;/a&gt; (+1=48)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/DBIx::Class::ResultSet::HashRef" target="_blank"&gt;DBIx::Class::ResultSet::HashRef&lt;/a&gt; (+1=4)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Devel::PPPort" target="_blank"&gt;Devel::PPPort&lt;/a&gt; (+1=11)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dist::Zilla" target="_blank"&gt;Dist::Zilla&lt;/a&gt; (+1=175)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Dist::Zilla::Plugin::Git" target="_blank"&gt;Dist::Zilla::Plugin::Git&lt;/a&gt; (+1=43)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Email::Mailer" target="_blank"&gt;Email::Mailer&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Email::Simple" target="_blank"&gt;Email::Simple&lt;/a&gt; (+1=17)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/FindBin" target="_blank"&gt;FindBin&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Getopt::Long" target="_blank"&gt;Getopt::Long&lt;/a&gt; (+1=108)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Getopt::Long::Descriptive" target="_blank"&gt;Getopt::Long::Descriptive&lt;/a&gt; (+1=48)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Import::Into" target="_blank"&gt;Import::Into&lt;/a&gt; (+1=35)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Log::Dispatch" target="_blank"&gt;Log::Dispatch&lt;/a&gt; (+1=44)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Log::ger" target="_blank"&gt;Log::ger&lt;/a&gt; (+1=6)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/MCE" target="_blank"&gt;MCE&lt;/a&gt; (+1=90)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Net::OpenSSH" target="_blank"&gt;Net::OpenSSH&lt;/a&gt; (+1=37)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Net::OpenSSH::Parallel" target="_blank"&gt;Net::OpenSSH::Parallel&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Net::Ping" target="_blank"&gt;Net::Ping&lt;/a&gt; (+1=12)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Params::Validate" target="_blank"&gt;Params::Validate&lt;/a&gt; (+1=33)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/PDL::Graphics::Gnuplot" target="_blank"&gt;PDL::Graphics::Gnuplot&lt;/a&gt; (+1=10)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Plack" target="_blank"&gt;Plack&lt;/a&gt; (+1=225)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Progress::Any" target="_blank"&gt;Progress::Any&lt;/a&gt; (+1=10)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Regex::Object" target="_blank"&gt;Regex::Object&lt;/a&gt; (+1=3)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Regexp::Common" target="_blank"&gt;Regexp::Common&lt;/a&gt; (+1=54)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Return::Type" target="_blank"&gt;Return::Type&lt;/a&gt; (+1=4)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Sodium::FFI" target="_blank"&gt;Sodium::FFI&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Sort::Key" target="_blank"&gt;Sort::Key&lt;/a&gt; (+1=26)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Sort::Naturally" target="_blank"&gt;Sort::Naturally&lt;/a&gt; (+1=18)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Spreadsheet::GenerateXLSX" target="_blank"&gt;Spreadsheet::GenerateXLSX&lt;/a&gt; (+1=3)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Starman" target="_blank"&gt;Starman&lt;/a&gt; (+2=111)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Sub::Retry" target="_blank"&gt;Sub::Retry&lt;/a&gt; (+1=12)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Task::Kensho" target="_blank"&gt;Task::Kensho&lt;/a&gt; (+1=110)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Template::Mustache" target="_blank"&gt;Template::Mustache&lt;/a&gt; (+1=4)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Template::Toolkit" target="_blank"&gt;Template::Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; (+1=136)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Test::Mojo::WithRoles" target="_blank"&gt;Test::Mojo::WithRoles&lt;/a&gt; (+1=8)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Text::ParseWords" target="_blank"&gt;Text::ParseWords&lt;/a&gt; (+1=12)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Type::Tiny::XS" target="_blank"&gt;Type::Tiny::XS&lt;/a&gt; (+1=15)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Win32::LongPath" target="_blank"&gt;Win32::LongPath&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/WWW::YouTube::Download" target="_blank"&gt;WWW::YouTube::Download&lt;/a&gt; (+1=20)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/XML::LibXML" target="_blank"&gt;XML::LibXML&lt;/a&gt; (+1=94)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/XS::Parse::Keyword" target="_blank"&gt;XS::Parse::Keyword&lt;/a&gt; (+1=6)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/3599518942001300163/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/d-metacpan-weekly-report-starman.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/3599518942001300163"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/3599518942001300163"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/d-metacpan-weekly-report-starman.html" title="(d) metacpan weekly report - Starman"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-2659807463567231029</id>
    <published>2022-03-26T15:41:00.001+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-26T15:41:43.054+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(dxxvii) stackoverflow perl report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;These are the five most rated questions at &lt;a href="http://www.stackoverflow.com"&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; last week.&lt;br/&gt;Between brackets: [&lt;b&gt;question score&lt;/b&gt; / answers count]&lt;br/&gt;Build date: 2022-03-26 14:41:23 GMT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr/&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71604861" target="_blank"&gt;Where is the uninitialized value in the compare function?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;4&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71552241" target="_blank"&gt;Getting individual key values from Perl JSON one at a time&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71587494" target="_blank"&gt;How can I shorten a [ qw( ... ) ] construct in Perl?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71607439" target="_blank"&gt;Perl 5.34.0 regular expression for word matching language Hebrew&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71556049" target="_blank"&gt;Regex does not match in Perl, while it does in other programs&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/2659807463567231029/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/dxxvii-stackoverflow-perl-report.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/2659807463567231029"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/2659807463567231029"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/dxxvii-stackoverflow-perl-report.html" title="(dxxvii) stackoverflow perl report"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Download and Installation of ActivePerl 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/yukikimoto/download-and-installation-of-activeperl-2022-31kk" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ActivePerl&lt;/strong&gt;  is one of the Windows Perl distributions provided by &lt;a href="https://www.activestate.com/"&gt;ActiveState&lt;/a&gt; for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.activestate.com/activeperl/downloads"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--B9ZBl4OK--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/installation/active_perl.png" alt="ActivePerl" width="450" height="199"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's download and install ActivePerl on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is originally &lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20080602121231.html"&gt;Download and Installation of ActivePerl | Perl ABC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  
  
  Installation of ActivePerl
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download and Install ActivePerl from the next page. The 2022 latest version is Perl 5.34.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.activestate.com/activeperl/downloads"&gt;Download and Install ActivePerl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.activestate.com/activeperl/downloads"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--Vwwx5jrp--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/installation/active_perl_click.png" alt="" width="880" height="528"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ActivePerl download requires ActiveState membership registration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the registration, you see the following page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--w4f8wV90--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/installation/active_perl_create_project.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--w4f8wV90--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/installation/active_perl_create_project.png" alt="" width="667" height="522"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scroll to the bottom of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--De1Rs_NK--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/installation/active_perl_create_rantime.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--De1Rs_NK--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/installation/active_perl_create_rantime.png" alt="" width="880" height="563"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click "Create Runtime". A runtime is created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click "Install" button, you see the following content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s---E0n5LhQ--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/installation/active_perl_install_runtime.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s---E0n5LhQ--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/installation/active_perl_install_runtime.png" alt="" width="880" height="387"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copy the command and paste it to Command Prompt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  
  
  Check the Installation of ActivePerl
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's check if ActivePerl is installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Command Prompt
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, you execute &lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20080603121251.html"&gt;Command Prompt&lt;/a&gt;. Command Prompt is a Windows CUI tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command prompt can be executed from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Start Menu" | "List of Apps" | "Windows System Tools" | "Command Prompt".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A black screen will appear. This is Command Prompt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--e4hywWKX--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/commandprompt/commandprompt.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--e4hywWKX--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/commandprompt/commandprompt.png" alt="" width="521" height="302"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Input the following command to display the version of Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
perl -v
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And press "Enter".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The version information of Perl is displayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
This is perl 5, version 34, subversion 0 (v5.34.0) built for MSWin32-x64-multi-thread
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can see this, the installation of ActivePerl is succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  
  
  Other ways to install Perl on Windows
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other ways to install Perl on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20180808153368.html"&gt;Installation of Strawberry Perl on Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20180806153350.html"&gt;Installation of msys2 and Perl on Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
    <author>
      <name>Yuki Kimoto</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/yukikimoto/download-and-installation-of-activeperl-2022-31kk</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T08:45:17Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T08:45:17Z</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="beginners"/>
    <category term="programming"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Please test DBD::Oracle v1.90_1</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/dean/2022/03/please-test-dbdoracle-v190-1.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2022:/users/dean//558.10743</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T05:56:38Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T05:58:34Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Dean</name>
        <uri>http://perl.sydney</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/dean/">
        <![CDATA[<p>Anyone using DBD::Oracle is invited to test out out this dev release v1.90_1</p>

<p>Download from metacpan <a href="https://metacpan.org/release/ZARQUON/DBD-Oracle-1.90_1">here</a></p>

<p>GH Tag <a href="https://github.com/perl5-dbi/DBD-Oracle/tree/v1.90_1">here</a></p>

<p>v1.90 candidate <a href="https://github.com/perl5-dbi/DBD-Oracle/tree/cand-v1.90">branch</a> </p>

<p>This <a href="https://github.com/perl5-dbi/DBD-Oracle/commit/4dd996e84725ec122e5f2fa2365ca7109bbf1d98">commit</a> is a big big change which should hopefully fix a lot of problems <br />
<blockquote><br />
Rewrite of login6<br />
This changes the way things are done during login6 (connect). In<br />
particular:</p>

<p>1. OCIEnv is cached based on character sets and mode. One copy<br />
is used in all threads (so OCI_THREADED is important!)</p>

<p>2. There are no more global variables for character sets. So each<br />
connection uses exactly what is specified at connection time. Thus<br />
option ora_envhp is removed.</p>

<p>3. Improved support for DRCP. Now the pools are independent from<br />
threads. The pool is defined by DSN and UID. No more leaking of<br />
connections or pools. When last imp_drh goes away the pools<br />
are released. It is now also possible to tag sessions in addition<br />
to using connection_class (the latter works only with DRCP).</p>

<p>4. Reauthenticate now keeps old session as long as possible, so<br />
if new identity is wrong, then old session stays intact.</p>

<p>5. Support for using shared variables is also improved. There is<br />
now additional function ora_shared_release that cleans up shared<br />
connection, when it is not needed anymore. Though it is still<br />
cleaner to used DRCP. No more handles are leaking.</p>

<p>6. Support for imp_take is improved. No handles are leaking.<br />
But it is cleaner to use DRCP.</p>

<p>7. Small fixes for compilation and handling of attributes.</blockquote></p>

<p><br />
Your feedback is most welcome via the <a href="https://github.com/perl5-dbi/DBD-Oracle/pull/150">pull request</a> <br />
</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Installation of Strawberry Perl on Windows 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/yukikimoto/installation-of-strawberry-perl-on-windows-2022-4k53" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strawberry Perl&lt;/strong&gt; is one of the Windows Perl distributions. Strawberry Perl is easy to install and has the C language compiler &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MinGW"&gt;MinGW&lt;/a&gt;, a CPAN module installer &lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20101027127859.html"&gt;cpanm&lt;/a&gt; and often used C libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is originally &lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20180808153368.html"&gt;Installation of Strawberry Perl on Windows | Perl ABC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://strawberryperl.com"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--j-UI-AP6--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/strawberry_perl/strawberry_perl_logo.png" alt="" width="450" height="295"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://strawberryperl.com"&gt;Strawberry Perl for Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  What is Strawbery Perl?
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strawbery Perl can be downloaded without registration. Older versions of Perl are available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/MinGW"&gt;MinGW&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href="https://en.c.perlzemi.com/"&gt;C&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%2B%2B"&gt;C++&lt;/a&gt; compiler that can be used on Windows. MinGW is compatible with &lt;a href="https://en.linux.perlzemi.comhttps://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20201216103956.html"&gt;gcc&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://en.linux.perlzemi.com/"&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix"&gt;UNIX&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gmake&lt;/strong&gt; is also available. gmake is a port of GNU make to Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the reason that Strawbery Perl has gcc and gmake, many &lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20101008127859.html"&gt;CPAN&lt;/a&gt; modules written in C/C++ can be installed on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20101027127859.html"&gt;cpanm&lt;/a&gt; command allows you to install CPAN modules quickly and easily. If you create a &lt;strong&gt;cpanfile&lt;/strong&gt; required modules are defined , you can install all modules you need at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Download Strawberry Perl
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming Windows 10, I explain how to download and install Strawberry Perl. The way to download and install is almost the same for older versions of Windows(Windows 8, Windows 7).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's download and install Strawberry Perl. The latest version of Perl 2022 is Perl 5.32.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click  &lt;strong&gt;Strawberry Perl 5.32 64bit MSI installer&lt;/strong&gt;  of the following link to download Strawberry Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="http://strawberryperl.com/releases.html"&gt;Strawberry Perl Releases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://strawberryperl.com/releases.html"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--uSNPJ2Ot--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/strawberry_perl/strawberry_perl_msi.png" alt="" width="465" height="196"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MSI installer is the default installer for Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The version number at the end(5.32.x.y) may be a little different, but don't worry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, the 64-bit version of Windows will work, but if you need the 32-bit version, download the 32-bit version of Strawberry Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Installation of Strawberry Perl
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Double-click the downloaded installer file of Strawberry Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installer will start. It may take some time to calculate the free space. Please wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press "Next" to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A check box that hears "I accept the terms in the License Agreement" will appear. Check it and press "Next".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press "Next" to proceed, and finally click "Install" to start Strawberry Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You'll see a dialog here, "Do you want to allow apps from this unknown publisher to make changes to your device?". Click "Yes".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take about 5 minutes. Please wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the progress bar is full, the Strawberry Perl installation is complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press "Finish" to close the dialog. A Readme will be displayed. Close it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Check the Installation of Strawberry Perl
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's check if Strawberry Perl is installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
  
  
  Command Prompt
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, you execute &lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20080603121251.html"&gt;Command Prompt&lt;/a&gt;. Command Prompt is a Windows CUI tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command prompt can be executed from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Start Menu" | "List of Apps" | "Windows System Tools" | "Command Prompt".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A black screen will appear. This is Command Prompt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--e4hywWKX--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/commandprompt/commandprompt.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--e4hywWKX--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://en.perlzemi.com/images/commandprompt/commandprompt.png" alt="" width="521" height="302"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Input the following command to display the version of Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
perl -v
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And press "Enter".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The version information of Perl is displayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
This is perl 5, version 32, subversion 0 (v5.32.1) built for MSWin32-x64-multi-thread
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can see this, the installation of Strawberry Perl is succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Trouble Shooting
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Strawberry Perl doesn't work, see the following trouble shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
  
  
  The Priority of PATH Environment Variable
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If another Perl such as ActivePerl or Strawberry Perl 32bit is already installed, the Strawberry Perl installed in this article may not work due to the priority problem of the PATH environment variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move the path of Perl you want to use to the front of other Perls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  The ways of Installation other than MSI
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ways to install Strawberry Perl other than MSI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
  
  
  ZIP Version of Strawberry Perl
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ZIP Version of Strawberry Perl is also prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
  
  
  Portable Version of Strawberry Perl
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portable Version of Strawberry Perl is also prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  
  
  Other Ways to Install Perl on Windows
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the following links to known other ways to install Perl on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
  
  
  ActivePerl
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ActivePerl is another Windows Perl distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20080602121231.html"&gt;Installation of Active Perl on Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
  
  
  msys2
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want a Linux pseudo environment on Windows, you can use msys2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20180806153350.html"&gt;Install msys2 on Windows to use Perl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
    <author>
      <name>Yuki Kimoto</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/yukikimoto/installation-of-strawberry-perl-on-windows-2022-4k53</id>
    <published>2022-03-24T08:42:10Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-24T08:42:10Z</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="programming"/>
    <category term="beginners"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>#556 - Cucumber &amp; Perl</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/556.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you test a &lt;strong&gt;Web API&lt;/strong&gt; using Perl?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure you have most likely used TDD to test your Web API. How about trying something new for a change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something like BDD, Behaviour Driven Development. I came across BDD many years ago when my manager introduced the term to the team and gave us a short tutorial using Java. I was completely blown away by the idea itself. I never actually got the opportunity to use BDD in any of the Perl projects I worked in afterwards, unfortunately. Then few years later in 2018, I got the opportunity to attend the talk &lt;a href="https://act.yapc.eu/lpw2018/talk/7547"&gt;Behaviour Driven Development and Cucumber&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Martin Berends&lt;/strong&gt; at the London Perl Workshop. After a quick search, I found a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B6IsKr50wAE"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; of the same talk. If you missed the talk then it is your chance now to watch the talk. If the video is not enough and you are looking for more. I would highly recommend the book &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B084Z6GTKK"&gt;Cucumber &amp; Perl&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;John Davies&lt;/strong&gt;. It was published by &lt;a href="https://perlschool.com"&gt;Perl School&lt;/a&gt; publishing house run by &lt;strong&gt;Dave Cross&lt;/strong&gt;. If you are interested in complete tutorial then you should check out this &lt;a href="https://www.cognizantsoftvision.com/blog/how-to-test-web-apis-with-perl-and-cucumber"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of BDD, I came across the term "&lt;strong&gt;Extreme Programming (XP)&lt;/strong&gt;". TDD has been part of my day job most of the time without realising it being part of XP. I found this &lt;a href="https://www.extremeperl.org/bk/home"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; showing &lt;strong&gt;Extreme Programming using Perl&lt;/strong&gt;. You can download the entire book in &lt;a href="https://www.extremeperl.org/f/extremeperl.pdf"&gt;pdf format&lt;/a&gt; for FREE. If you are new to &lt;strong&gt;Extreme Programming&lt;/strong&gt; then take a look at the &lt;a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org"&gt;gentle introduction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THe last couple of years have been very tough for most of us in the IT sector. Although we all have been adjusted to the new normal of work-from-home culture, it has still left some scars behind. Mental health is one such issue being discussed more frequently during this period. I have found a way to keep my mind busy when needed; reading books (mostly non-technical). Recently I found the quote &lt;strong&gt;"Lately my peace has been more important than proving my point."&lt;/strong&gt; on web that express my current mental state. How do you deal with your WFH blues?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, I have finally reached the 3 digits figure i.e. my &lt;strong&gt;100th edition&lt;/strong&gt; of the weekly newsletter. It took me nearly &lt;strong&gt;3 years&lt;/strong&gt; to get this far. I would like to take this opportunity to thank each and every readers of the weekly newsletter for the kind words and appreciations. I would also like to thank, &lt;strong&gt;Gabor Szabo&lt;/strong&gt; for being my guide and mentor, all these years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy the rest of the newsletter, stay safe and pray for world peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/556.html</id>
    <published>2022-03-21T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-21T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Perl Weekly Challenge 156: Pernicious and Weird Numbers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/laurent_r/2022/03/perl-weekly-challenge-156-pernicious-and-weird-numbers.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2022:/users/laurent_r//3226.10738</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T03:30:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-21T01:30:38Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>laurent_r</name>
        <uri>https://laurent-rosenfeld.developpez.com/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/laurent_r/">
        <![CDATA[<p>These are some answers to the Week 156 of the <a href="https://perlweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-156/">Perl Weekly Challenge</a> organized by <a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/mohammad_s_anwar/">Mohammad S. Anwar</a>.</p>

<p><em>Spoiler Alert:</em> This weekly challenge deadline is due in a few days from now (on March 20, 2022 at 24:00). This blog post offers some solutions to this challenge, please don’t read on if you intend to complete the challenge on your own.</p>

<h2>Task 1: Pernicious Numbers</h2>

<p><em>Write a script to permute first 10 Pernicious Numbers.</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>A pernicious number is a positive integer which has prime number of ones in its binary representation.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>The first pernicious number is 3 since binary representation of 3 = (11) and 1 + 1 = 2, which is a prime.</em></p>

<p><em>Expected Output:</em></p>

<pre><code>3, 5, 6, 7, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14
</code></pre>

<p>I&#8217;m not sure why the task description speaks about <em>permuting</em> the first 10 pernicious numbers. It seems we&#8217;re simply requested to display them.</p>

<h3>Pernicious Numbers in Raku</h3>

<p>In Raku, we can use the <a href="https://docs.raku.org/routine/base">base</a> method to convert a real number into a string representation with a chosen base. To find the number of <code>1</code> in the resulting binary string, we can just sum the digits. Then, Raku has the built in <a href="https://docs.raku.org/routine/is-prime">is-prime</a> to find out whether the <code>1</code> count is a prime numbers. We end up with a method invocation pipeline (<code>$n.base(2).comb.sum.is-prime</code>) that does all the real work.</p>

<pre><code>my $count = 0;
for 2..* -&gt; $n {
    if $n.base(2).comb.sum.is-prime {
        $count++;
        print "$n, " and next if $count &lt; 10;
        say $n and last;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This program displays the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ raku ./pernicious.raku
3, 5, 6, 7, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14
</code></pre>

<h3>Pernicious Numbers in Perl</h3>

<p>In Perl, we will simply use the <code>sprintf</code> built-in function with a <code>%b</code> formatting string to convert the input integer into a binary representation. The program is otherwise similar to the Raku implementation, except for finding if the <code>1</code> count is prime. We could write a subroutine for that (or, rather, re-use one of the numerous such subroutines that I have implemented for previous Perl Weekly Challenge task implementations, including last week for <a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/laurent_r/2022/03/perl-weekly-challenge-155-fortunate-numbers-and-pisano-periods.html">PWC 155</a>). But since we don&#8217;t need any large prime, I&#8217;ll simply hard-code the first eight prime numbers (those less than 20) known to all people having even only a slight inclination for maths , and store them in a hash for fast lookup</p>

<pre><code>use strict;
use warnings;
use feature "say";

my $count = 0;
my %primes = map { $_ =&gt; 1 } (2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13, 17, 19);

for my $n (2..100) {
    my $bin = sprintf "%b", $n;
    my $num_1 = 0;
    $num_1 += $_ for split "", $bin;
    if (exists $primes{$num_1}) {
        $count++;
        print "$n, " and next if $count &lt; 10;
        say $n and last;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This script displays the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ perl pernicious.pl
3, 5, 6, 7, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14
</code></pre>

<h3>Pernicious Numbers in Julia</h3>

<pre><code>primes = Dict(2 =&gt; 1, 3 =&gt; 1, 5 =&gt; 1, 7 =&gt; 1, 11 =&gt; 1, 13 =&gt; 1, 17 =&gt; 1, 19 =&gt; 1)
count = 0
for n in 2:20
    n_bin = string(n, base=2)
    num_1 = 0
    for digit in n_bin
        num_1 += parse(Int64, digit)
    end
    if num_1 ∈ keys(primes)
        global count
        count += 1
        print(n, " ")
        count &gt;= 10 &amp;&amp; break
    end
end
println("")
</code></pre>

<p>Output:</p>

<pre><code>3 5 6 7 9 10 11 12 13 14
</code></pre>

<h3>Pernicious Numbers in Python</h3>

<pre><code>primeset = {2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13, 17, 19}
count= 0
for n in range(2, 20):
    bin_n = format(n, 'b')
    num_1 = 0
    for x in bin_n:
        if x == '1':
            num_1 += 1

    if num_1 in primeset:
        count += 1
        print(n, end =" ")
        if count &gt;= 10:
            break
print("")
</code></pre>

<p>Output:</p>

<pre><code>$ python3 pernicious.py
3 5 6 7 9 10 11 12 13 14
</code></pre>

<h2>Task 2: Weird Numbers</h2>

<p><em>You are given number, $n > 0.</em></p>

<p><em>Write a script to find out if the given number is a Weird Number.</em></p>

<p><em>According to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weird_number">Wikipedia</a>, it is defined as:</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>The sum of the proper divisors (divisors including 1 but not itself) of the number is greater than the number, but no subset of those divisors sums to the number itself.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Example 1:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: $n = 12
Output: 0

Since the proper divisors of 12 are 1, 2, 3, 4, and 6, which sum to 16; but 2 + 4 + 6 = 12.
</code></pre>

<p><em>Example 2:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: $n = 70
Output: 1

As the proper divisors of 70 are 1, 2, 5, 7, 10, 14, and 35; these sum to 74, but no subset of these sums to 70.
</code></pre>

<p>If a number is equal to the sum of its proper divisors, it is said to be a <em>perfect</em> number (such as 6, 28, 496, etc.). If it it less than the sum of its divisors, it is said to be <em>abundant</em> and it it is more than the sum of its divisors, it is <em>deficient</em>. If a number is equal to the sum of a subset of its proper divisors (such as 12), it it said to be <em>semi-perfect</em>). With these definitions in mind, a <em>weird</em> number is an abundant number that is not semi-perfect.</p>

<h3>Weird Numbers in Raku</h3>

<p>The <code>is-weird</code> subroutine first finds the proper divisors of the input integer (testing divisibility for all integers less than or equal to the input integer). Then it returns False if the sum of the divisors is less than or equal to the input integer (i.e. if the input  number is deficient or perfect). For the remaining integers (the so-called abundant numbers), it uses the <a href="https://docs.raku.org/routine/combinations">combinations</a> method on the <code>@divisors</code> list to test all subsets of at least 2 items and returns False if the sum of the items of any such subset is equal to the input numbers. If no such subset has been found, then the number is not semi-perfect and the subroutine returns True.</p>

<pre><code>sub is-weird (Int $n where * &gt; 0) {
    my @divisors = grep {$n %% $_}, 1..$n/2;
    return False if @divisors.sum &lt;= $n;
    for @divisors.combinations: 2..@divisors.elems -&gt; $subset {
        return False if $subset.sum == $n;
    }
    True;
}

for 2..1000 -&gt; $m {
    say "Found $m" if is-weird($m);
}
</code></pre>

<p>This script finds only two integers less than 1000 that are weird:</p>

<pre><code>raku ./wierd_nrs.raku
Found 70
Found 836
</code></pre>

<h3>Weird Numbers in Perl</h3>

<p>This is essentially a port to Perl of the Raku implementation above, except that we had to implement two helper subroutines, <code>sum</code> and <code>combine</code>. The first one simply computes the sum of the items of an input list or array, and the second is a recursive subroutine that computes all subsets of the input divisors list and returns a false value (0) if the sum of any subset is equal to the input integer, and a true value (1) otherwise.</p>

<pre><code>use strict;
use warnings;
use feature "say";

sub sum {
    my $sum = 0;
    $sum += $_ for @_;
    return $sum;
}

sub combine {
    my ($test, $comb, $div) = @_;
    my @comb_so_far = @$comb;
    my @divisors = @$div;
    # say "(@comb_so_far) (@divisors)";
    return 0 if sum(@comb_so_far) == $test;
    return 1 if scalar @divisors == 0;
    for my $i (0..$#divisors) {
        my $result = combine($test, [@comb_so_far, $divisors[$i]],
                             [@divisors[($i+1)..$#divisors]]);
        return 0 if $result == 0;
    }
    return 1;
}

sub is_weird {
    my $n = shift;
    my @divisors = grep {$n % $_ == 0} 1..($n/2);
    return 0 if sum(@divisors) &lt;= $n;
    return combine($n, [], [@divisors]);
}

for my $m (2..6000) {
    say "Found $m" if is_weird($m);
}
</code></pre>

<p>With the wider range used in this program, it displays the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ perl weird_nrs.pl
Found 70
Found 836
Found 4030
Found 5830
</code></pre>

<p>This program is becoming very slow for the larger values of the input integer. It took more than 25 minutes on my computer to find the four weird numbers below 6,000 above.</p>

<p>Note that all four weird numbers found above are even. In fact, although there are infinitely many weird numbers, all known weird numbers are even, and it is not known whether there exists any odd weird number (this is an unsolved problem in mathematics). So if you can find an odd weird number, or else if you can prove that no such number exists, you might become famous.</p>

<h2>Wrapping up</h2>

<p>The next week Perl Weekly Challenge will start soon. If you want to participate in this challenge, please check https://perlweeklychallenge.org/ and make sure you answer the challenge before 23:59 BST (British summer time) on March 27, 2022. And, please, also spread the word about the Perl Weekly Challenge if you can.</p>
]]>
        

    </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Persnickety Pernicious and Weird</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/2022/03/20#pwc156" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The examples used here are from The Weekly Challenge problem statement and demonstrate 
the working solution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write a script to generate the first 10 Pernicious Numbers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;

use Math::Primality qw/is_prime/;

sub count_bits{
    my($n) = @_;
    my $total_count_set_bit = 0;
    while($n){
        my $b = $n &amp; 1;
        $total_count_set_bit++ if $b;
        $n = $n &gt;&gt; 1;
    }
    return $total_count_set_bit;
}

sub first_n_pernicious{
    my($n) = @_;
    my @pernicious;
    my $x = 1;
    do{
        my $set_bits = count_bits($x);
        push @pernicious, $x if is_prime($set_bits);
        $x++;
    }while(@pernicious &lt; $n);
    return @pernicious;
}

MAIN:{
    print join(", ", first_n_pernicious(10)) . "\n";
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-1.pl
3, 5, 6, 7, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number Theory was one of my favorite classes as an undergraduate. This sort of challenge
is fun, especially if you dive into the background of these sequences and try to learn
more about them. Computing them is fairly straightforward, especially here where the two
functions are largely drawn from past TWCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are given number, $n &gt; 0. Write a script to find out if the given number is a Weird 
Number.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;

use boolean;
use Data::PowerSet q/powerset/;

sub factor{
    my($n) = @_;
    my @factors = (1);
    foreach  my $j (2 .. sqrt($n)){
        push @factors, $j if $n % $j == 0;
        push @factors, ($n / $j) if $n % $j == 0 &amp;&amp; $j ** 2 != $n;
    }
    return @factors;  
}

sub is_weird{
    my($x) = @_;
    my @factors = factor($x); 
    my $sum = unpack("%32I*", pack("I*",  @factors));
    for my $subset (@{powerset(@factors)}){
        return false if unpack("%32I*", pack("I*",  @{$subset})) == $x;
    }  
    return boolean($sum &gt; $x);
}

MAIN:{
    print is_weird(12) . "\n";
    print is_weird(70) . "\n";
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-2.pl
0
1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This task kind of bothered me, not because of the complexity of the task itself; the code
was overall not extremely demanding. Rather anytime when I want to make use of 
&lt;em&gt;Data::PowerSet&lt;/em&gt; I get a bit anxious that there may be a far more elegant way of 
proceeding! After coming up blank on alternatives I just went with this, but I'll probably
still have this in the back of my mind for a few more days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-156/"&gt;Challenge 156&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pernicious_number"&gt;Pernicious Number&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/WeirdNumber.html"&gt;Weird Number&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/perl/pwc156</id>
    <published>2022-03-20T18:29:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-20T18:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <category term="/perl"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Access the Tesla API with Perl!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/steve_bertrand/2022/03/access-the-tesla-api-with-perl.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2022:/users/steve_bertrand//2771.10739</id>
    <published>2022-03-19T03:30:07Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-20T20:16:31Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Steve Bertrand</name>
        
    </author>
    <category term="perlperl5teslaapi" label="perl perl5 tesla api" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#tag"/>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/steve_bertrand/">
        <![CDATA[<p>For several years, I spent much time writing code for the Raspberry Pi, including hardware level register C code so that we can use various Integrated Circuit chips and sensors with Perl.</p>

<p>A couple of years ago, I acquired much larger and much more expensive toy, an all-wheel drive, full auto-pilot Tesla Model-X SUV, so of course, I want to write Perl code to access and manipulate it.</p>

<p>In the ensuing two years, I developed several microcontroller-based devices for the car, including one that knows where the car is, and its battery charge and state, and dispslays this information via an LED light strip and an OLED screen inside of my garage, along with an audible alarm that sounds for 1/8th of a second every three seconds if the battery is below a certain threshold so I don't forget to plug the charger in.</p>

<p>The microcontroller speaks to a Raspberry Pi who's job it is to fetch data from the Tesla API for my car, and to present that data to the microconroller, over Wifi. The software on the Pi is of course written in Perl, but because I couldn't figure out how to write the Tesla API authentication mechanism in Perl, I used Tim Dorssers TeslaPy Python library, and wrapped it for those calls.</p>

<p>Not anymore! We can now talk to the Tesla API via Perl!</p>

<p>I've officially released <a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Tesla::Vehicle">Tesla::Vehicle</a>, which inherits from my other new related distribution, <a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Tesla::API">Tesla::API</a>.</p>

<p>Upon first attempt to fetch data from Tesla, we will generate a URL that you must browse through to in a browser, authenticate into your Tesla account, and then paste back the ensuing URL you are redirected to into the console. After that, all access tokens are automatically used and updated when needed. My software never has any access or knowledge of your Tesla account credentials, which is the way I wanted this designed.</p>

<p>Thereafter, it's clear sailing!</p>

<p>The documentation is pretty elaborate about what the software can do so please check it out. For <a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Tesla::Vehicle">Tesla::Vehicle</a>, there are methods to access aggregate data, sections of the aggregate data, and for several specific attributes that I use myself, I've added methods for them directly. More will be added as time goes on.</p>

<p>Features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Built-in initial access token generation code with prompts of instructions</li>
<li>Automatic access token renewal</li>
<li>Single method (<code>api()</code>) to access data from endpoints that don't yet have a direct method</li>
<li>Built in modifiable data cache (set to 2 second timeout by default) to reduce calls to Tesla for data already retrieved (cache can be disabled)</li>
<li>Consistent data return values... for data aggregate methods, all data is returned as a hash reference</li></li>
<li>Near feature complete; most data has at least an aggregate fetch method, many individual attributes have accessor methods</li>
<li>Ability to wake the car from sleep (<code>wake()</code>). For calls that require the car to be awake, you can set <code>auto_wake</code> and we'll wake the car ourselves (disabled by default)</li>
<li>Many Tesla API calls require a vehicle ID sent in. We do our best to get this ourselves, otherwise it can be sent into <code>new()</code> or <code>id()</code></li>
</ul>

<p>Todo: The main one is adding methods that allow control of the functionality of the car. The only one implemented thus far is <code>wake()</code>. I'll also be adding more direct attribute retrieval methods. For now, use the aggregate methods and pull the data out of the return values yourself. There are also a few minor issues, primarily related to the handling of Tesla API timeouts.</p>

<p>How 'bout some code and output:</p>

<pre><code>use warnings;
use strict;

use Tesla::Vehicle;

my $car = Tesla::Vehicle-&gt;new(auto_wake =&gt; 1);

printf(
    "My Tesla account has my car registered with the name '%s'.\n",
    $car-&gt;name
);

printf(
    "My car is in gear %s and is currently going %d MPH and my odometer is %d\n",
    $car-&gt;gear,
    $car-&gt;speed,
    $car-&gt;odometer
);

printf(
    "My latitude is %f, longitide is %f, my heading is %d degrees and its using %.2f kWh/mile\n",
    $car-&gt;latitude,
    $car-&gt;longitude,
    $car-&gt;heading,
    $car-&gt;power
);

printf(
    "My dashcam is %s, sentry mode is %s and I %s currently near my vehicle\n",
    $car-&gt;dashcam,
    $car-&gt;sentry_mode ? 'enabled' : 'disabled',
    $car-&gt;user_present ? 'am' : 'am not'
);

printf(
    "My battery is at %d%%, and is %s charging at %.2f volts pulling %.2f Amps\n",
    $car-&gt;battery_level,
    $car-&gt;charging_state ? 'currently' : 'not',
    $car-&gt;charger_voltage,
    $car-&gt;charge_actual_current
);

if ($car-&gt;battery_level &gt;= $car-&gt;charge_limit_soc) {
    print "The charger is connected but disabled due to set maximum charge level reached\n";
}

printf(
    "My steering wheel warmer is %s, passenger seat warmer is %s, and Bio Weapon mode is %s\n",
    $car-&gt;heater_steering_wheel ? 'on' : 'off',
    $car-&gt;heater_seat_passenger ? 'on' : 'off',
    $car-&gt;bioweapon_mode ? 'on' : 'off'
);

printf(
    "The temperature inside the car is %dC and outside it's %dC, and climate control is %s\n",
    $car-&gt;temperature_inside,
    $car-&gt;temperature_outside,
    $car-&gt;is_climate_on ? 'on' : 'off'
);
</code></pre>

<p>Output:</p>

<pre><code>My Tesla account has my car registered with the name 'Dream machine'.

My car is in gear P and is currently going 0 MPH and my odometer is 49066

My latitude is XX.XXXXXX, longitide is -XXX.XXXXXX, my heading is 229 degrees and its using 0.00 kWh/mile

My dashcam is Unavailable, sentry mode is disabled and I am not currently near my vehicle

My battery is at 94%, and is currently charging at 0.00 volts pulling 0.00 Amps

The charger is connected but disabled due to set maximum charge level reached

My steering wheel warmer is off, passenger seat warmer is off, and Bio Weapon mode is off

The temperature inside the car is 17C and outside it's 13C, and climate control is off
</code></pre>
]]>
        

    </content>
</entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-1656490883575635454</id>
    <published>2022-03-19T22:15:00.000+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-19T22:15:29.407+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(ccclxxxiv) 12 great CPAN modules released last week</title>
    <content type="html">Updates for &lt;i&gt;great CPAN modules&lt;/i&gt; released last week. A module is considered &lt;i&gt;great&lt;/i&gt; if its favorites count is greater or equal than 12.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/PLICEASE/Alien-Build-2.48' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Alien::Build&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Build external dependencies for use in CPAN &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;2.48&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-13&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 21&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 2.47 was 6 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/CROMEDOME/Dancer2-0.400000' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Dancer2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Lightweight yet powerful web application framework &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.400000&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-14&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 127&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.301004 was 9 months, 8 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/DROLSKY/DateTime-TimeZone-2.52' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;DateTime::TimeZone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Time zone object base class and factory &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;2.52&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-17&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 17&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 2.51 was 4 months, 26 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/PEVANS/Future-AsyncAwait-0.57' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Future::AsyncAwait&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - deferred subroutine syntax for futures &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.57&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-16&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 42&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.56 was 1 month, 21 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/OALDERS/HTML-Parser-3.77' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;HTML::Parser&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - HTML parser class &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;3.77&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-14&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 43&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 3.76 was 1 year, 10 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/SKAJI/Minilla-v3.1.16' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Minilla&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - CPAN module authoring tool &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;v3.1.16&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-13&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 54&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: v3.1.15 was 1 month, 13 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/BINGOS/Module-CoreList-5.20220313' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Module::CoreList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - what modules shipped with versions of perl &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;5.20220313&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-15&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 37&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 5.20220220 was 23 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/SRI/Mojo-Pg-4.27' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Mojo::Pg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Mojolicious ♥ PostgreSQL &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;4.27&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-15&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 68&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 4.26 was 6 months, 7 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/ETJ/PDL-2.077' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;PDL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Perl Data Language &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;2.077&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-16&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 43&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 2.076 was 19 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/SHAY/perl-5.34.1' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;utf8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - The Perl 5 language interpreter &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;5.034001&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-13&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 388&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 5.34.0 was 9 months, 24 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/TOBYINK/PerlX-Maybe-1.202' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;PerlX::Maybe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - return a pair only if they are both defined &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.202&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-14&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 34&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.201 was 3 years, 3 months, 19 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/PEVANS/Scalar-List-Utils-1.62' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Sub::Util&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Common Scalar and List utility subroutines &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.62&lt;/strong&gt; on 2022-03-17&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 158&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.61 was 1 month, 1 day before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/1656490883575635454/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/ccclxxxiv-12-great-cpan-modules.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/1656490883575635454"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/1656490883575635454"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/ccclxxxiv-12-great-cpan-modules.html" title="(ccclxxxiv) 12 great CPAN modules released last week"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-1512352191470237630</id>
    <published>2022-03-19T22:11:00.000+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-19T22:11:13.555+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(dxxvi) stackoverflow perl report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;These are the five most rated questions at &lt;a href="http://www.stackoverflow.com"&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; last week.&lt;br/&gt;Between brackets: [&lt;b&gt;question score&lt;/b&gt; / answers count]&lt;br/&gt;Build date: 2022-03-19 21:10:57 GMT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr/&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71518438" target="_blank"&gt;How To Set ChromeOptions (or goog:ChromeOptions) for Selenium::Chrome in Perl&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71531385" target="_blank"&gt;Why does grep not work when searching array for value if the value has a special character?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71492318" target="_blank"&gt;Template in Mojolicious controller not found&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71496243" target="_blank"&gt;How to create a circular linked list in Perl without using arrays?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/71504096" target="_blank"&gt;Perl backticks subprocess is causing EOF on STDIN&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/1512352191470237630/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/dxxvi-stackoverflow-perl-report.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/1512352191470237630"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/1512352191470237630"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2022/03/dxxvi-stackoverflow-perl-report.html" title="(dxxvi) stackoverflow perl report"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>#555 - Holidays</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/555.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Hi there!</p>
<p>I am in Hungary now where where there is a 4-days Holiday around the 15th March - the Hungarian version of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revolutions_of_1848">Springtime of Nations revolutions</a>.</p>
<p>Then I'll have another 2 days off as my client in Israel celebrates <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Purim">Purim</a>.</p>
<p>I use these free days to work on an open source platform for word-games. It is not ready yet to show the world, but it is already in a condition where people can contribute to it. The first game needs lots of words in various languages. I already started to do versions in English, Hungarian, Hebrew, and Ladino and I already had a contributor with French and German, but I am looking for more people who might be interested in contributing in other languages. Let me know and I can show you the game. I hope that two weeks from now, when I am editing the next issue of the Perl Weekly I'll be able to link to the game. (the game is only front-end code now so there is no Perl in it. Sorry.)</p>
<p>Enjoy your week!</p></div>
    </content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/555.html</id>
    <published>2022-03-14T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-14T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Fortunate Pisano</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/2022/03/13#pwc155" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The examples used here are from The Weekly Challenge problem statement and demonstrate 
the working solution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write a script to produce the first eight Fortunate Numbers (unique and sorted).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;

use boolean;
use Math::Primality qw/is_prime/;

use constant N =&gt; 10_000; 

sub sieve_atkin{
    my($n) = @_;
    my @primes = (2, 3, 5);
    my $upper_bound = int($n * log($n) + $n * log(log($n)));
    my @atkin = (false) x $upper_bound;    
    my @sieve = (1, 7, 11, 13, 17, 19, 23, 29, 31, 37, 41, 43, 47, 49, 53, 59);
    for my $x (1 .. sqrt($upper_bound)){
        for(my $y = 1; $y &lt;= sqrt($upper_bound); $y+=2){
            my $m = (4 * $x ** 2) + ($y ** 2);
            my @remainders;  
            @remainders = grep {$m % 60 == $_} (1, 13, 17, 29, 37, 41, 49, 53) if $m &lt;= $upper_bound; 
            $atkin[$m] = !$atkin[$m] if @remainders; 
        }          
    } 
    for(my $x = 1; $x &lt;= sqrt($upper_bound); $x += 2){
        for(my $y = 2; $y &lt;= sqrt($upper_bound); $y += 2){
            my $m = (3 * $x ** 2) + ($y ** 2);
            my @remainders;  
            @remainders = grep {$m % 60 == $_} (7, 19, 31, 43) if $m &lt;= $upper_bound; 
            $atkin[$m] = !$atkin[$m] if @remainders; 
        }          
    }   
    for(my $x = 2; $x &lt;= sqrt($upper_bound); $x++){
        for(my $y = $x - 1; $y &gt;= 1; $y -= 2){
            my $m = (3 * $x ** 2) - ($y ** 2);
            my @remainders;  
            @remainders = grep {$m % 60 == $_} (11, 23, 47, 59) if $m &lt;= $upper_bound;
            $atkin[$m] = !$atkin[$m] if @remainders; 
        }          
    } 
    my @m;
    for my $w (0 .. ($upper_bound / 60)){
        for my $s (@sieve){
            push @m, 60 * $w + $s;  
        }
    }
    for my $m (@m){
        last if $upper_bound &lt; ($m ** 2);
        my $mm = $m ** 2;
        if($atkin[$m]){
            for my $m2 (@m){
                my $c = $mm * $m2;
                last if $c &gt; $upper_bound;
                $atkin[$c] = false;
            }
        }
    }
    map{ push @primes, $_ if $atkin[$_] } 0 .. @atkin - 1;
    return @primes; 
}

sub first_n_fortunate{
    my($n) = @_;
    my @primes = sieve_atkin(N);
    my @fortunates;
    my $x = 1;
    do{
        my @first_n_primes = @primes[0 .. $x - 1];
        my $product_first_n_primes = 1;
        map {$product_first_n_primes *= $_} @first_n_primes;
        my $m = 1;
        do{
            $m++;
        }while(!is_prime($product_first_n_primes + $m));
        if(!grep {$m == $_} @fortunates){
             unshift @fortunates, $m;
        }
        $x++;
    }while(@fortunates != $n);
    return sort {$a &lt;=&gt; $b} @fortunates;
}

MAIN:{
    print join(", ", first_n_fortunate(8)) . "\n";
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-1.pl
3, 5, 7, 13, 17, 19, 23, 37
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another re-use of my Sieve of Adkin code! Here the sieve is used to generate primes
for us to compute &lt;em&gt;primorials&lt;/em&gt;, the product of the first &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; prime numbers. A Fortunate
Number is a sequence in which each &lt;code&gt;kth&lt;/code&gt; term is the number &lt;code&gt;m&lt;/code&gt; such that for the
primorial of the first &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt; primes summed with the smallest &lt;code&gt;m&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;m &amp;gt; 1&lt;/code&gt; such that the sum 
is prime. It is an unproven conjecture in Number Theory that all terms of the Fortunate
Numbers sequence are prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the code follows pretty directly from the definition with the added restrictions
that we must eliminate duplicates and sort the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write a script to find the period of the third Pisano Period.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;

use constant N =&gt; 1_000_000_000; 

sub fibonacci_below_n{
    my($n, $fibonaccis) = @_;
    $fibonaccis = [1, 1] if !$fibonaccis;
    my $f = $fibonaccis-&gt;[@{$fibonaccis} - 2] + $fibonaccis-&gt;[@{$fibonaccis} - 1];
    if($f &lt; $n){
        push @{$fibonaccis}, $f;
        fibonacci_below_n($n, $fibonaccis);
    }
    else{
        return $fibonaccis;
    }
}

sub multiplicative_order{
    my($a, $n) = @_;
    my $k = 1;
    my $result = 1;
    while($k &lt; $n){
        $result = ($result * $a) % $n;
        return $k if $result == 1;
        $k++;
    }
    return -1 ;
}

sub fibonacci_period_mod_n{
    my($n) = @_;
    my $fibonaccis = fibonacci_below_n(N);
    my $k = 1;
    for my $f (@{$fibonaccis}){
        if($f % $n == 0){
            return $k * multiplicative_order($fibonaccis-&gt;[$k+1], $n);
        }
        $k++;
    }
    return -1;
}

MAIN:{
    print fibonacci_period_mod_n(3) . "\n";
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-2.pl
8
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to compute the Pisano period in a fairly direct way. First you must 
determine the smallest Fibonacci Number evenly divisible by the modulus. Record the index
of this term in the sequence, call it &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt;. Compute the multiplicative order &lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt; of the 
&lt;code&gt;k+1&lt;/code&gt;st term with the given modulus. The Pisano period is then &lt;code&gt;k * M&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above code implements that procedure fairly directly. One possible change would be
to not pre-compute Fibonacci terms as done here, but for this small problem it hardly 
matters. Take care if trying this out on very large terms, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-155/"&gt;Challenge 155&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/FortunatePrime.html"&gt;Fortunate Prime&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/MultiplicativeOrder.html"&gt;Multiplicative Order&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/PisanoPeriod.html"&gt;Pisano Period&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/perl/pwc155</id>
    <published>2022-03-13T19:10:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-13T19:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <category term="/perl"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Dancer2: Hello World with Visual Studio Code</title>
  <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Part of the Dancer2 video course available both to <a href="/pro">Pro</a> subscribers and attendees of the <a href="https://leanpub.com/c/dancer">Perl Dancer course</a> on Leanpub.
<p>
]]></summary>
  <updated>2022-03-13T17:30:01Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://perlmaven.com/dancer2-hello-world-with-vscode"/>  <id>https://perlmaven.com/dancer2-hello-world-with-vscode</id>
  <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Part of the Dancer2 video course available both to <a href="/pro">Pro</a> subscribers and attendees of the <a href="https://leanpub.com/c/dancer">Perl Dancer course</a> on Leanpub.
<p>
]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Gabor Szabo</name>
    </author>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>#554 - Exceptions in Perl?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/554.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Hi there</p>
<p>I borrowed the title from Curtis' recently shared <a href="https://gist.github.com/Ovid/5205534f7dcc52e4d931aaff301b39aa">gist</a>. I am sure every one of us have dealt with exceptions in Perl. Being a <a href="https://metacpan.org">CPAN</a> fan, I found plenty of choices readily available. I am a big fan of <a href="https://metacpan.org/dist/Try-Tiny">Try::Tiny</a> and it has always been my first choice to deal with exceptions in Perl. I suggest you must check out the gist for more insights and suggestions shared by Curtis.</p>
<p>I would also like to share another gem by Curtis, <a href="https://github.com/Ovid/Cor/wiki/Porting-from-Moose-or-Moo">Porting from Moose or Moo</a>. It is a big help for anyone to move to Corinna from Moose or Moo. Most of my personal work shared on <a href="https://metacpan.org/author/MANWAR">MetaCPAN</a> used Moo. The document by Curtis would be handy when porting to Corinna once it is part of core Perl. I am eagerly waiting for it to happen.</p>
<p>Finally, this is my <strong>99th edition</strong> of the weekly newsletter. In two weeks time, I would be presenting the <strong>100th edition</strong>. I joined the team of editors in <strong>May 2018</strong>, thanks to the chief editor, <strong>Gabor Szabo</strong>, for all the support and guidance.</p>
<p>Enjoy the rest of the newsletter and pray for the world peace.</p></div>
    </content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/554.html</id>
    <published>2022-03-07T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-07T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Padovan Prime Directive: Find the Missing Permutations</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/2022/03/06#pwc154" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The examples used here are from The Weekly Challenge problem statement and demonstrate 
the working solution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are given possible permutations of the string "PERL". Write a script to find any 
permutations missing from the list.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;

use Algorithm::Loops q/NestedLoops/;

sub factorial{
    my($n) = @_;
    return 1 if $n == 1;
    $n * factorial($n - 1);
}

sub missing_permutations{
    my($permutations, $s) = @_;
    my @missing;
    ##
    # remove any duplicates
    ##
    my %permutations;
    map {$permutations{$_}=undef} @{$permutations};    
    $permutations = [keys %permutations];
    ##
    # get the letters missing in each slot
    ##
    my @missing_letters;
    for my $i (0 .. length($s) - 1){
        my %slot_counts;
        my @ith_letters = map {my @a = split(//, $_); $a[$i]} @{$permutations};
        map{$slot_counts{$_}++} @ith_letters;
        $missing_letters[$i] = [grep {$slot_counts{$_} != factorial(length($s) - 1)} keys %slot_counts];
    }
    ##
    # determine which missing letters form missing permutations
    ##
    my $nested = NestedLoops(\@missing_letters);
    while (my @set = $nested-&gt;()){
        my $candidate = join("", @set);
        my @matched = grep {$candidate eq $_} @{$permutations};
        push @missing, $candidate if !@matched;
    }
    return @missing;
}


MAIN:{
    my @missing = missing_permutations(
        ["PELR", "PREL", "PERL", "PRLE", "PLER", "PLRE", "EPRL", "EPLR", "ERPL",
         "ERLP", "ELPR", "ELRP", "RPEL", "RPLE", "REPL", "RELP", "RLPE", "RLEP",
         "LPER", "LPRE", "LEPR", "LRPE", "LREP"], "PERL"
    );
    print join(", ", @missing) . "\n";
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-1.pl
LERP
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I tried to write as general a solution as possible. This code should handle any 
number of missing permutations, provided that there are no duplicate letters within the
starting word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approach is to first consider each position in the starting word as a "slot" and then
check which letters are missing from each slot. In the code above we assume that each 
letter from the starting word appears in each slot at least once. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we know the missing letters we form new permutations with them and see which ones are
missing from the initial list. To cut down on the tedious bookkeeping involved I used the
&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Algorithm::Loops"&gt;Algorithm::Loops&lt;/a&gt; module to generate the
candidate permutations from the known missing letters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An even more general solution would not only catch any number of missing permutations but 
also allow for duplicate letters in the starting word and an input containing permutations 
which so not have at least one occurrence of each letter per slot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write a script to compute the first 10 distinct Padovan Primes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;

use Math::Primality qw/is_prime/;

sub first_n_padovan_primes{
    my($n) = @_;
    my @padovan_primes;
    my @padovans = (1, 1, 1);
    {
        push @padovans, $padovans[@padovans - 2] + $padovans[@padovans - 3];
        push @padovan_primes, $padovans[@padovans - 1] if is_prime($padovans[@padovans - 1]);
        redo if @padovan_primes &lt;= $n;
    }
    return @padovan_primes[1..@padovan_primes - 1];
}

MAIN:{
    print join(", ", first_n_padovan_primes(10)) . "\n";
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-2.pl
2, 3, 5, 7, 37, 151, 3329, 23833, 13091204281, 3093215881333057
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before really looking at the sample solutions for this problem I decided that my approach 
would be generat e giant list of primes and then check against that list to determine if 
a new sequence element was prime or not. Nice idea, but it doesn't scale that well for 
this problem! Yes, it worked for a smaller number of Padovan Primes but to catch the first 
ten would require generating an enormous list of prime numbers. Better in this case to use
something like &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Math::Primality"&gt;Math::Primality&lt;/a&gt; to check each
candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-154/"&gt;Challenge 154&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/PadovanSequence.html"&gt;Padovan Sequence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/perl/pwc154</id>
    <published>2022-03-06T18:43:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-06T18:43:00-05:00</updated>
    <category term="/perl"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
