<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Perl</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://perl.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>There's More Than One Way To Aggregate It</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2021-12-13T12:50:43Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://perl.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://perl.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>#542 - Perl Advent Calendar</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/542.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Hi there</p>
<p>How you all doing? Are you making the most of the festive season?</p>
<p>In the <a href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/540.html">540th edition</a> of the weekly newsletter, I mentioned <strong>Advent Calendars</strong>. I noticed some activity in the GitHub repository for the <strong>Perl Advent Calendar</strong> and was hoping to see another exciting edition full of Perl projects. A friend of mine on <strong>Facebook</strong> mentioned that this year the <a href="http://perladvent.org/2021/index.html">Perl Advent Calendar</a> is looking a bit sparse. At the time of writing this editorial, I have only seen <a href="http://perladvent.org/2021/2021-12-01.html">one post</a> i.e. Day 1 of Year 2021. Being one of many contributors in the past, I am sad to see the current state of the project. I have absolutely no idea what happened this year. I know I have too many things already on my plate but I would like to help to get the <strong>Perl Advent Calendar</strong> back to its original glory.</p>
<p>Talking about <strong>Advent Calendars</strong>, I would like to mention <a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/advent-calendar-2021">The Weekly Challenge Advent Calendar</a> which has mix of <strong>Perl</strong> and <strong>Raku</strong> like in the past. We have been running this since the beginning i.e. <strong>2019</strong>. You will find some of the fun tasks from the past year being discussed by members of <strong>Team PWC</strong>. I have made a slight change to the look and feel this year. I hope you like it.</p>
<p>How about the <a href="https://24pullrequests.com">24 Pull Requests</a> event?</p>
<p>I have not seen it being discussed either on any of the social platforms e.g. <strong>Facebook</strong>, <strong>Twitter</strong> or <strong>LinkedIn</strong>. I haven't had chance to take part this year. I couldn't take part last year either; what a shame. I still have 10 days and I have booked a few days off work. So there is a possibility I might take part and even complete the challenge. Please wish me luck.</p>
<p>Last but not least, <strong>Curtis</strong>, leader of the <strong>Corinna</strong> project, announced that he had a great meeting with the Perl Steering Council and they are extremely receptive to Corinna going into the core. I can't wait for <strong>Corinna</strong> to be part of core Perl. <strong>Damian</strong> shared the details on one of issues discussed in the same meeting in a <a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/damian_conway/2021/12/a-not-so-simple-matter-of-privacy.html">blog post</a>. You definitely don't want to miss it.</p>
<p>Enjoy the newsletter.</p></div>
    </content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/542.html</id>
    <published>2021-12-13T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-13T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sleeping Divisors</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/2021/12/12#pwc142" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The examples used here are from The Weekly Challenge problem statement and demonstrate 
the working solution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are given positive integers, $m and $n. Write a script to find total count of 
divisors of $m having last digit $n.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;
sub factor{
    my($n) = @_;
    my @factors = (1);
    foreach  my $j (2 .. sqrt($n)){
        push @factors, $j if $n % $j == 0;
        push @factors, ($n / $j) if $n % $j == 0 &amp;&amp; $j ** 2 != $n;
    }
    return @factors;  
}

sub divisors_last_digit{
    my($m, $n) = @_;
    my @divisors;   
    my @factors = factor($m);
    {
        my $factor = pop @factors;
        push @divisors, $factor if $n == substr($factor, -1);    
        redo  if @factors;  
    }    
    return sort {$a &lt;=&gt; $b} @divisors;   
}

MAIN:{
    my($m, $n); 
    my @divisors;
    ($m, $n) = (24, 2); 
    @divisors = divisors_last_digit($m, $n);
    print "($m, $n): " . @divisors . " --&gt; " . join(", ", @divisors) . "\n";  
    ($m, $n) = (75, 5); 
    @divisors = divisors_last_digit($m, $n);
    print "($m, $n): " . @divisors . " --&gt; " . join(", ", @divisors) . "\n";  
    ($m, $n) = (30, 5); 
    @divisors = divisors_last_digit(30, 5);
    print "($m, $n): " . @divisors . " --&gt; " . join(", ", @divisors) . "\n";  
}

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-1.pl
(24, 2): 2 --&gt; 2, 12
(75, 5): 3 --&gt; 5, 15, 25
(30, 5): 2 --&gt; 5, 15
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Implement Sleep Sort.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;
use Thread::Pool;

sub create_workers{
    my @numbers = @_; 
    my $count = @numbers; 
    my $workers = new Thread::Pool({
        optimize =&gt; "cpu", 
        do =&gt; \&amp;sleeper, 
        workers =&gt; $count,
        maxjobs =&gt; $count, 
        minjobs =&gt; $count 
    });
    return $workers;
}

sub sleeper{
    my($n) = @_; 
    sleep($n);
    return $n;   
}

sub sleep_sort{
    my($numbers, $workers) = @_; 
    my @jobs;
    my @sorted;   
    for my $n (@{$numbers}){
        my $job_id = $workers-&gt;job($n);
        push @jobs, $job_id;   
    } 
    {
        my $job = pop @jobs;     
        my @result = $workers-&gt;result_any(\$job);
        if(!@result){    
            push @jobs, $job;  
        }
        else{
            push @sorted, $result[0]; 
        }
        redo if @jobs; 
    }
    $workers-&gt;shutdown; 
    return @sorted;   
}

MAIN:{
    my @numbers;
    my @sorted; 
    @numbers = map{int(rand($_) + 1)} (0 .. 9);  
    print join(", ", @numbers) . "\n"; 
    @sorted = sleep_sort(\@numbers, create_workers(@numbers));  
    print join(", ", @sorted) . "\n"; 
}  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-2.pl
1, 1, 1, 3, 2, 3, 4, 7, 8, 6
1, 1, 1, 2, 3, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8
$ perl perl/ch-2.pl
1, 1, 1, 2, 2, 5, 5, 2, 1, 9
1, 1, 1, 1, 2, 2, 2, 5, 5, 9
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope participants in The Weekly Challenge enjoyed this! After I saw Jort Sort in 
Challenge 139 I was reminded of other joke sorts and suggested this as a future challenge.
Happily the suggestion was accepted!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threading is easy in Perl, which uses an "Interpreter Threads" ("ithreads") model. 
Node.js programmers will find this model familiar as it is exactly what that language 
uses. Unfortunately Perl's documentation writers are not as familiar with concurrent and 
parallel programming topics and some of the official documentation needs updating. 
Unfortunately, this is a bizarrely 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Perl/perl5/issues/14691"&gt;contentious issue&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To ensure you are using a perl interpreter with proper ithreads support try this 
one-liner: &lt;code&gt;$ perl -Mthreads -e 0&lt;/code&gt;. If that runs without error you are good to go! If you
get an error you'll need to install a new perl. One convenient option is to use 
&lt;a href="https://perlbrew.pl/"&gt;Perlbrew&lt;/a&gt;. After installing &lt;code&gt;perlbrew&lt;/code&gt; you'll need to invoke it
like this &lt;code&gt;perlbrew install perl-5.34.0 -Dusethreads&lt;/code&gt;. Please see the Perlbrew 
documentation for additional (straightforward) details if you decide to undertake this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here rather than &lt;code&gt;use threads&lt;/code&gt; directly &lt;code&gt;Thread::Pool&lt;/code&gt; is used. This is a convenient
pattern for using Perl's ithreads. Since each ithread is really a new perl interpreter 
process this allows for some fine tuning of the number of ithreads created to help 
conserve memory usage. In this case the memory conservation is actually somewhat minimal
since Sleep Sort requires us to start a new ithread for each element of the array to be 
sorted. Amusingly, because of the process based threading model, we can quickly crash the 
program by attempting to sort an array whose size causes the system to exceed the number
of allowed processes. Remember, this is a joke sort, right!?!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically you'd create a pool of workers whose number matched the number of CPU cores
available. That way each core could be tasked by the OS for whatever CPU intensive code
you'd care to run without the ithreads competing too badly with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concurrent and parallel programming issues are somewhat advanced. Excellent documentation
exists that is both Perl specific and more general. Be sure to understand the difference 
between ithreads and so called "co-operative thread" models (as used in modules such as
Coro. The "advanced" nature of this topic is due to understanding the various trade-offs 
at play. Deep understanding usually comes from experience of implementing solutions this
way and study of the underlying Operating System concepts. Even the most modest modern
computer systems systems available have multiple cores at your disposal as a programmer
so this effort is certainly worthwhile! The bibliography of &lt;code&gt;perlthrtut&lt;/code&gt; is an excellent
starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-142/"&gt;Challenge 142&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://iq.opengenus.org/sleep-sort/"&gt;Sleep Sort&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/perlthrtut"&gt;perlthrtut&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Thread::Pool"&gt;Thread::Pool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nodesource.com/blog/worker-threads-nodejs/"&gt;Node.js Workers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/perl/pwc142</id>
    <published>2021-12-12T13:16:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-12-12T13:16:00-05:00</updated>
    <category term="/perl"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A (not so) simple matter of privacy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/damian_conway/2021/12/a-not-so-simple-matter-of-privacy.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2021:/users/damian_conway//875.10580</id>
    <published>2021-12-11T22:03:25Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-12T11:10:15Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Damian Conway</name>
        <uri>http://damian.conway.org</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/damian_conway/">
        <![CDATA[<p>You may have seen <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/perl/comments/rdcziv/corinna_discussion_with_the_perl_steering/">Ovid's recent post</a>
on his discussions with the Perl Steering Committee
about moving forward with implementing an initial subset
of the <a href="https://github.com/Ovid/Cor">Corinna proposal</a> in the Perl core.</p>

<p>One of the issues that came up during those discussions was the best way to provide private
methods in Corinna. The current Corinna proposal is that this would be done <em>(like almost
everything else in Corinna)</em> via an attribute:</p>

<p><code>    method do_internal <strong>:private</strong> () {...}</code></p>

<p>Thereafter, the <code>do_internal()</code> method can only be called from within
the current class, and is never overridden by derived-class methods when
it is called within its original class.</p>

<p>In other words, the <code>:private</code> method effectively prepends the following
code to the start of the method:</p>

<p><code>    croak "Can't call method 'do_internal'"</code><br/>
<code>        if caller ne &lowbar;&lowbar;CLASS&lowbar;&lowbar;;</code></p>

<p>...and, in addition, causes the compiler to treat any call to that particular method
from within the current class as a <a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/perlobj#Method-Names-with-a-Fully-Qualified-Name">fully qualified method call</a>.
That is, within any class <code>C</code> with a private <code>do_internal()</code> method, any call
to <code>$self-&gt;do_internal()</code> is treated as a call to <code>$self-&gt;<strong>C::do_internal</strong>()</code>.</p>

<p>All of which means that there is no way to call a private method from anywhere
except within the same class. Which, of course, is the whole point of <em>having</em> private methods
in the first place.</p>

<p>But the need to automagically convert any call to a private method into a fully qualified
method call is <em>(to put it mildly)</em> a complication for the compiler.
So the members of the <em><s>Perl Steering Committee</s></em> Cor design team suggested that rather than having private methods,
Perl should have lexical methods instead. Specifically, they suggested that instead of:</p>

<p><code>    method do&lowbar;internal <strong>:private</strong> () {...}</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>    method do_external () {</code><br/>
<code>        $self-&gt;<strong>do&lowbar;internal()</strong>;   # Call private method</code><br/>
<code>        ...</code><br/>
<code>    }</code></p>

<p>...Perl would provide anonymous methods, which you could place in lexical variables
and then call using the existing <a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/perlobj#Subroutine-References-as-Methods"><em>call-via-reference</em> method call syntax</a>:</p>

<p><code>    my $do&lowbar;internal = <strong>method () {...}</strong>;</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>    method do_external () {</code><br/>
<code>        $self-&gt;<strong>$do&lowbar;internal()</strong>;   # Call lexical method</code><br/>
<code>        ...</code><br/>
<code>    }</code></p>

<p>That neatly avoids of the challenge of rewriting private methods to check their caller,
or the much greater challenge of rewriting private method calls to be fully qualified.
Instead, it cleverly enforces the <em>“can be called only from the current class”</em> requirement
by making it impossible to refer to the method at all, except in the lexical scope of the
<code>$do_internal</code> variable.</p>

<p>You could even consider the slightly uglier <code>$self-&gt;$do_internal()</code> call syntax as a win:
because it means that private method calls are explicitly marked as such.</p>

<p>The only downsides are:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The <em>call-via-reference</em> syntax is more obscure and perhaps
a little more challenging for less-experienced Perl developers.
That might discourage them from using this approach,
even for methods that really should be private,
thereby penalizing a good OO practice.</p></li>
<li><p>Using anonymous methods to implement private methods is <strong><em>structural</em></strong> rather that
<strong><em>declarative</em></strong>. That is: we can’t just say <strong><em>what</em></strong> we want to have happen,
we have to say <strong><em>how</em></strong> to actually implement it. In practical terms, this
means that private method definitions are no longer explicitly marked
as being private, and hence are far less searchable.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>And that second issue is the real problem here. Because they’re structural, not declarative,
lexical methods specified like this are also much easier to <a href="https://media.pragprog.com/articles/jan_03_enbug.pdf">“enbug”</a>.
For example, if the developer mistakenly wrote something like this:</p>

<p><code>    method other () {</code><br/>
<code>        ...</code><br/>
<code>        $do_internal++;</code><br/>
<code>        ...</code><br/>
<code>    }</code></p>

<p>Then any call to the <code>$do_external()</code> method will be fine so long as the
<code>other()</code> method is never called. But after <code>other()</code> has been
called, the next call to <code>$do_external()</code> will throw a weird exception:</p>

<p><tt>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Can't locate object method "140362266577153" via class "C"</tt></p>

<p>Of course, we can get around that potential bug by making <code>$do_internal</code> immutable:</p>

<p><code>    <strong>use Const::Fast;</strong></code><br/>
<code>    <strong>const</strong> my $do_internal => method () {...};</code></p>

<p>but that’s now an extra module load, and even more infrastructure to get right.</p>

<p><em>(BTW, wouldn’t it be cool if the existing <code>:const</code> subroutine attribute
could also be applied to scalar variables, in which case we’d just need:</p>

<p><code>    my $do_internal :const = method () {...};</code></p>

<p>Maybe one day!)</em></p>

<p>Yet another issue with using anonymous methods as private methods is that
they make it easy to subvert the intended encapsulation:</p>

<p><code>    our $do_internal = method () {...};</code></p>

<p>That’s no longer a private method, because you can now call it from literally anywhere in your code:</p>

<p><code>    $obj-&gt;<strong>$C::do_internal</strong>();</code></p>

<p>And, even if it were still a <code>my</code> variable, there’s nothing to prevent a class
from explicitly exporting it:</p>

<p><code>    method circumvent&lowbar;privacy () { return $do&lowbar;internal }</code></p>

<p>As an OO purist, I find that possibility worrying. And as someone who has reviewed a vast
amount of real-world Perl OO code over the past few decades, I think that kind of expedient
kludge is...inevitable.</p>

<p>So what do we do?</p>

<p>The good folks of the <em><s>Perl Steering Committee</s></em> Cor team suggested an approach that does address
some of these issues. They proposed that the syntax for private methods be:</p>

<p><code>    method <strong>$do&lowbar;internal</strong> () {...}</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>    method do&lowbar;external () {</code><br/>
<code>        $self-&gt;<strong>$do&lowbar;internal()</strong>;   # Call private method</code><br/>
<code>        ...</code><br/>
<code>    }</code></p>

<p>That is: when you want to declare a private method, you put a <code>$</code> at the start of its name.
This form of the <code>method</code> keyword would then create a <em>(presumably immutable!)</em> lexical
<code>$do_internal</code> variable, initialized with a reference to an anonymous method.
You could then use the reference in that variable to call the private method.</p>

<p>While it doesn’t solve the problem of evil developers explicitly exporting that variable, it
does make the syntax declarative again, and it could solve the issue of accidentally changing
the variable <em>(assuming the variable were indeed to be created as immutable)</em>.</p>

<p>The only problem is that now we have the <code>method</code> keyword not just declaring methods,<br/>
but also declaring variables.</p>

<p>Which, from the perspective of a language designer, is...less than ideal.<br/>
And, from the perspective of someone who actually still teaches Perl,<br/>
is <strong><em>much</em></strong> less than ideal.</p>

<p>So, how do we solve that?</p>

<p>Well, Raku solves it by marking private methods not with a <code>$</code>, but with a <code>!</code><br/>
and then calling them with the <code>!</code> as well (rather than Raku’s usual <code>.</code> method call operator):</p>

<p><code>    # In Raku...</code><br/>
<code>    method <strong>!do&lowbar;internal</strong> () {...}  # Private method</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>    method do&lowbar;external () {</code><br/>
<code>        self<strong>!do&lowbar;internal</strong>();       # Private method call</code><br/>
<code>        ...</code><br/>
<code>    }</code></p>

<p>That’s a neat solution, but it probably wouldn’t work for Perl.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, the ideal of prefix-marking private methods and private method calls in some way
<em>might</em> work. For example, we could consider formalizing the <em>“private methods start with an
underscore”</em> convention inside the new <code>class</code> blocks:</p>

<p><code>    method <strong>&lowbar;do&lowbar;internal</strong> () {...}</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>    method do&lowbar;external () {</code><br/>
<code>        $self-&gt;<strong>&lowbar;do&lowbar;internal</strong>();</code><br/>
<code>        ...</code><br/>
<code>    }</code></p>

<p>In other words, we could specify that any method definition that starts with an
underscore <strong><em>doesn’t</em></strong> get added to the method symbol table. Instead, it implicitly creates
an immutable and invisible lexical scalar within the class. Then, within any <code>class</code> block,
any call to a method whose name starts with an underscore actually calls the method through the
associated invisible lexical scalar instead.</p>

<p>Or, to put it more simply: it’s precisely the <em><s>Steering Committee</s></em> Cor team’s proposal, but: <code>s/\$/_/g</code><br/>
And with the added advantage that the lexical is not otherwise accessible within its scope,<br/>
and therefore not accidentally modifiable, or maliciously exportable.</p>

<p>That’s by far the safest alternative I can think of, but I concede that it might still be too magical.</p>

<p>In which case we’d instead need to address just the immediate problem: that we’re contemplating
using the <code>method</code> declarator to declare something that isn’t actually a method. Specifically,
we’re using <code>method</code> to declare variables.</p>

<p>And the easiest solution to that problem is simply to define another declarator:</p>

<p><code>    <strong>private</strong> $do&lowbar;internal () {...}   # Declare private method</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>    method do_external () {</code><br/>
<code>        $self-&gt;<strong>$do&lowbar;internal()</strong>;      # Call private method</code><br/>
<code>        ...</code><br/>
<code>    }</code></p>

<p>Now <code>method</code> once again only declares named methods, and we can easily explain
that <code>private</code> declares a lexically scoped variable whose immutable value
is a reference to the anonymous method.</p>

<p>We get very clear declarative labelling of private methods
and equally clear labelling of calls to those private methods.</p>

<p>We <strong><em>don’t</em></strong> solve the <em>“naughty folk can export that variable to circumvent privacy”</em>
problem, but I suppose we could always just spin that as a feature, rather than a bug. <a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=%2FS">/s</a></p>

<p>For the moment, however, unless the <em><s>Steering Committee</s></em> Cor team is happy with either
the <em>“underscore enforces private”</em> approach or the addition of a <code>private</code> keyword,
I expect what we’ll actually have to do is to remove private methods entirely
from the first stage of the implementation, and simply keep on pondering
how to get them exactly right.</p>

<p>In the meantime, don’t let <em>anyone</em> ever tell you that language (re-)design is easy. <tt>:-)</tt></p>
]]>
        

    </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weekly Challenge 142</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/simongreennet/weekly-challenge-142-1gb3" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h2>
  <a href="#before-i-begin">
  </a>
  Before I begin...
</h2>

<p>As Mohammad mention in <a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/1000-days/">his blog</a>, December 18th will mark 1,000 days since The Weekly Challenge was born. I'd like to thank him for all the tireless work he puts into the challenge to make it a success.</p>

<p>I'd also like to shout out to Colin Crain for his weekly reviews of the Perl submission, and Pete Sergeant and the Perl Careers team for donating the monthly giveaways.</p>

<p>And finally thank you to every member of Team PWC. As much as I enjoy doing the challenge myself, I get even more out of it by reading other blog posts to see how other people tackle each task.</p>

<h2>
  <a href="#task-1-divisor-last-digit">
  </a>
  TASK #1 › Divisor Last Digit
</h2>

<h3>
  <a href="#task">
  </a>
  Task
</h3>

<p>You are given positive integers, <code>$m</code> and <code>$n</code>.</p>

<p>Write a script to find total count of divisors of <code>$m</code> having last digit <code>$n</code>.</p>

<h3>
  <a href="#my-solution">
  </a>
  My solution
</h3>

<p>This is a pretty straight forward task. It's a mash up of the two tasks last week, the first dealt with divisors, and the second taking an input of <code>$m</code> and <code>$n</code>.</p>

<p>I do have an observation about the task itself. The second value has to be a positive integer, but the solutions only match the 'last digit'. That means any value above nine isn't valid. As the number zero is not a positive integer, it also does not meet the criteria. I was definitely in two minds about including the option of 0, but the task clearly states a 'positive integer', so I stuck with that.</p>

<p>As for the task itself, I have a function <code>_get_divisors</code>. Given a number, it will return a list of all divisors. Like last weeks task, I only made modest optimizations to perform this quickly.</p>

<p>I filter this list by checking that the last digit of each divisor ( <code>× % 10</code> ) is the second value, and display the number of elements in the list.</p>

<p>The Perl code is a transliteration of the Python code.</p>

<h3>
  <a href="#examples">
  </a>
  Examples
</h3>



<div class="highlight js-code-highlight">
<pre class="highlight plaintext"><code>$ ./ch-1.py 24 2
2

$ ./ch-1.py 30 5
2
</code></pre>

</div>



<h2>
  <a href="#task-2-sleep-sort">
  </a>
  TASK #2 › Sleep Sort
</h2>

<h3>
  <a href="#task">
  </a>
  Task
</h3>

<p>Another joke sort similar to JortSort suggested by champion Adam Russell.</p>

<p>You are given a list of numbers. Write a script to implement <a href="https://iq.opengenus.org/sleep-sort">Sleep Sort</a></p>

<h3>
  <a href="#my-solution">
  </a>
  My solution
</h3>

<p>I found this task interesting because I've never really used threads in either Python or Perl. Once I read up on it, it was a matter of creating a thread for each number. After creating all the threads, we join them so our script won't exit before all the threads are completed. Each thread will sleep for the required number of seconds, and then display the number.</p>

<p>Like with the first task, the Perl code is a transliteration of the Python code. The only important difference is that I use <a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Time::HiRes#sleep">Time::HiRes</a>'s version of sleep to allow sleeping for parts of a second.</p>

<h3>
  <a href="#examples">
  </a>
  Examples
</h3>



<div class="highlight js-code-highlight">
<pre class="highlight plaintext"><code>$ ./ch-2.py 3 0.1 2 2.5 1
0.1
1
2
2.5
3

$ ./ch-2.pl 3 0.1 2 2.5 1
0.1
1
2
2.5
3
</code></pre>

</div>



</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Simon Green</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/simongreennet/weekly-challenge-142-1gb3</id>
    <published>2021-12-12T03:41:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-12T03:41:20Z</updated>
    <category term="python"/>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="theweeklychallenge"/>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-6969056211502125629</id>
    <published>2021-12-11T23:42:00.001+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-12-11T23:42:36.055+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(ccclxxi) 8 great CPAN modules released last week</title>
    <content type="html">Updates for &lt;i&gt;great CPAN modules&lt;/i&gt; released last week. A module is considered &lt;i&gt;great&lt;/i&gt; if its favorites count is greater or equal than 12.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/GUGOD/App-perlbrew-0.94" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;App::perlbrew&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Manage perl installations in your $HOME &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.94&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-04&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 167&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.94 was 7 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/DWHEELER/App-Sqitch-v1.2.1" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;App::Sqitch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Sensible database change management &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;v1.2.1&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-05&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 38&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: v1.2.0 was 15 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/JHTHORSEN/JSON-Validator-5.04" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;JSON::Validator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Validate data against a JSON schema &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;5.04&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-09&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 29&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 5.03 was 19 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/PREACTION/Minion-Backend-mysql-0.32" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;Minion::Backend::mysql&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - MySQL backend &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.32&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-11&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 12&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.30 was 11 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/DCANTRELL/Number-Phone-3.8002" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;Number::Phone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - base class for Number::Phone::* modules &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;3.8002&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-06&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 15&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 3.8001 was 2 months, 15 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/SSIMMS/PDF-API2-2.043" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;PDF::API2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Create, modify, and examine PDF files &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;2.043&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-08&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 27&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 2.042 was 2 months, 22 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/KIMOTO/SPVM-0.9017" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;SPVM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Static Perl Virtual Machine. Fast Calculation, Fast Array Operation, and Easy C/C++ Binding. &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.9017&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-10&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 21&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.9015 was 2 months, 16 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/BDFOY/Unicode-Tussle-1.115" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;Unicode::Tussle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Tom's Unicode Scripts So Life is Easier &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.115&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-11&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 13&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.111 was 5 years, 6 months, 4 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/6969056211502125629/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/ccclxxi-8-great-cpan-modules-released.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/6969056211502125629"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/6969056211502125629"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/ccclxxi-8-great-cpan-modules-released.html" title="(ccclxxi) 8 great CPAN modules released last week"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-4851525430142946524</id>
    <published>2021-12-11T23:34:00.005+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-12-11T23:39:10.825+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(dxiii) stackoverflow perl report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;These are the ten most rated questions at &lt;a href="http://www.stackoverflow.com"&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; last week.&lt;br /&gt;Between brackets: [&lt;b&gt;question score&lt;/b&gt; / answers count]&lt;br /&gt;Build date: 2021-12-11 22:30:55 GMT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70293610" target="_blank"&gt;How to convert between the unicode forms: string, name, number&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;4&lt;/b&gt;/3]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70297671" target="_blank"&gt;Perl: How is to be interpreted a negation of an array and scalar?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70307461" target="_blank"&gt;cpan says App::cpanminus is up to date but cpanm doesn't come up in /usr/bin&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70257809" target="_blank"&gt;Perl's rpm version differs from "perl -v"&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;- [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70285870" target="_blank"&gt;Is there a way to remote to a different machine, and run multiple commands there in series (using perl)?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70296344" target="_blank"&gt;Perl issue when encoding mysql data from UTF-8 to UCS-2 for SMPP&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70302112" target="_blank"&gt;Wrapper generator SWIG (C++/Perl): How to access "blessed" objects in a 1d vector&amp;lt;double&amp;gt;in Perl?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70314803" target="_blank"&gt;Perl: Can't use string ("XXX") as a HASH ref while "strict refs" in use&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70247252" target="_blank"&gt;Perl: match regex from the file&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70262927" target="_blank"&gt;Perl Regex return named groups in capture Group one&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/4851525430142946524/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/dxiii-stackoverflow-perl-report.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/4851525430142946524"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/4851525430142946524"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/dxiii-stackoverflow-perl-report.html" title="(dxiii) stackoverflow perl report"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My Favorite Warnings: shadow</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/12/my-favorite-warnings-shadow.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2021:/users/tom_wyant//506.10572</id>
    <published>2021-12-09T21:21:25Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-09T21:23:21Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tom Wyant</name>
        
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/">
        <![CDATA[<p><cite>Who knows what evil lurks in the hearts of men? <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shadow">The Shadow</a> knows!</cite></p>

<p>OK, Perl does not literally have a warning about a 1930's pulp fiction and radio serial character. But Perl 5.28 introduced <a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/perldiag#s--variable--s-masks-earlier-declaration-in-same--s"><code>shadow</code></a> as a new warning category for cases where a variable is redeclared in the same scope. Previously, such warnings were under <code>misc</code>.</p>

<p>To tickle this it is sufficient to</p>

<pre>
$ perl -Mstrict -Mwarnings -Mdiagnostics -e 'my $x; my $x;'
</pre>

<p>If your Perl is at least 5.28.0, you get the diagnostic</p>

<pre>
"my" variable $x masks earlier declaration in same scope at -e line 1 (#1)
    (W shadow) A "my", "our" or "state" variable has been redeclared in the
    current scope or statement, effectively eliminating all access to the
    previous instance.  This is almost always a typographical error.  Note
    that the earlier variable will still exist until the end of the scope
    or until all closure references to it are destroyed.
</pre>

<p>Earlier Perls (back to 5.6 which is when <code>warnings</code> was introduced) give a similar warning, but the category is <code>misc</code>.</p>

<p>It is hard to come up with a reason why you would want to disable this warning. An extremely contrived example (do not try this at home!) would be something like</p>

<pre>
sub make_closures {
    my ( $x ) = @_;
    my $c1 = sub { $x * $_[0] };
    my $x = $x * 2;
    return ( $c1, sub { $x * $_[0] } );
}
</pre>

<p>But it would be far simpler and clearer just to call the second variable something else. If you absolutely, positively have to disable this under a range of versions of Perl, the changing category for this warning means you have to jump through some hoops. Something like this should do the trick:</p>

<pre>
my $x; # or whatever
no if "$]" &gt;= 5.028, qw{ warnings shadow };
no if "$]" &lt; 5.028, qw{ warnings misc };
my $x;
</pre>

<p>Note that this warning category only covers earlier declarations in the same scope. Using the same-named variable in nested scopes does not generate this diagnostic:</p>

<pre>
$ perl -Mstrict -Mwarnings -Mdiagnostics -e 'my $x; { my $x; }'
</pre>

<p>is silent.</p>

<p>This warning category also covers <code>our</code> and <code>state</code> variables, and lexical subroutines.</p>

<p><br />
<p><cite>The weed of crime bears bitter fruit! Crime does not pay...The Shadow knows!</cite></p></p>

<p>Previous entries in this series:</p>
<ol>
    <li><a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/10/my-favorite-warnings-a-belated-introduction.html">A Belated Introduction</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/09/my-favorite-warnings-once.html"><code>once</code></a></li>
    <li><a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/09/my-favorite-warnings-redundant-and-missing.html"><code>redundant</code> and <code>missing</code></a></li>
    <li><a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/09/my-favorite-warnings-exiting.html"><code>exiting</code></a></li>
    <li><a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/10/my-favorite-warnings-uninitialized.html"><code>uninitialized</code></a></li>
    <li><a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/10/my-favorite-warnings-redefine-sooner.html"><code>redefine</code></li>
    <li><a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/11/my-favorite-warnings---ex-warnings.html">Ex-Warnings</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/11/my-favorite-warnings-deprecated.html"><code>deprecated</code></a></li>
    <li><a href="https://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/11/my-favorite-warnings-experimental.html"><code>experimental</code></a></li>
</ol>
]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Closures</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/12/closures.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2021:/users/tom_wyant//506.10550</id>
    <published>2021-12-02T03:41:03Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-09T18:32:43Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tom Wyant</name>
        
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/">
        <![CDATA[<p><cite>A casual remark about closures which I made in <a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/tom_wyant/2021/10/my-favorite-warnings-redefine-sooner.html">My Favorite Warnings: <code>redefine</code></a> touched off a long off-topic exchange with Aristotle that I thought ought to be promoted to a top-level blog entry. The big thing I learned was that <strong>any Perl subroutine can be a closure.</strong> The rest of this blog will try to make clear why I now believe this. The words are my own, as are any errors or misconceptions.</cite></p>

<p>The second sentence of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Closure_(computer_programming)">Wikipedia&apos;s definition of a closure</a> says "Operationally, a closure is a record storing a function together with an environment." This makes it sound a lot like an object, and therefore of little additional interest in an O-O environment.</p>

<p>But I came to closures pragmatically through Perl, and to me they were a magic way to make data available somewhere else. All I had to do was get a code reference where it needed to be, and any external lexical variables got the values <i>at the time the reference was taken</i>. So much I understood up to the fatal blog post, and it sufficed for my simple needs.</p>

<p>A fairly typical Perl example of closures in action is:</p>

<pre>
my $add_one = make_adder( 1 );
my $add_two = make_adder( 2 );
say $add_one-&gt;( 5 );  # 6
say $add_two-&gt;( 8 );  # 10

<p>sub make_adder {<br />
    my ( $addend ) = @_;<br />
    return sub { $addend + $_[0] };<br />
}<br />
</pre></p>

<p>A deeper understanding of this magic requires a look at how it works. In this case, the man behind the curtain is the lexical variable <code>$addend</code>.</p>

<p>The usual argument for using lexical variables is that they are only accessable in a given scope -- specifically from the point they come into existence with <code>my</code> to the end of the enclosing scope. Compared to global variables this is a big win in itself. But closures make use of another property of lexical variables: that each entry into the scope results in a new instance of the variable. The returned code reference incorporates not only the code itself but the current instance of any relevant lexicals, in this case <code>$addend</code>. In fact if you add to the above code example</p>

<pre>
say '$add_one is ', $add_one;
say '$add_two is ', $add_two;
</pre>

<p>you will see that though both variables nominally refer to the same subroutine, different values are printed.</p>

<p>To differentiate the behaviour of closures from a simple object, consider:</p>

<pre>
my ( $add_two, $mul_two, $chg_two ) = make_closures( 2 );
my ( $add_four, $mul_four, $chg_four ) = make_closures( 4 );

<p>say $add_two-&gt;( 3 );  # 5<br />
say $mul_two-&gt;( 3 );  # 6<br />
say $add_four-&gt;( 3 ); # 7<br />
say $mul_four-&gt;( 3 ); # 12</p>

<p>$chg_two-&gt;( 5 );      # What will happen now?</p>

<p>say $add_two-&gt;( 3 );  # 8 !!!<br />
say $mul_two-&gt;( 3 );  # 15 !!!<br />
say $add_four-&gt;( 3 ); # Still 7<br />
say $mul_four-&gt;( 3 ); # Still 12</p>

<p>sub make_closures {<br />
    my ( $operand ) = @_;<br />
    return(<br />
        sub { $operand + $_[0] },<br />
	sub { $operand * $_[0] },<br />
	sub { $operand = $_[0] },<br />
    );<br />
}<br />
</pre></p>

<p>The point of this example is that all three closures share not only the value of <code>$operand</code> but the actual instance. If the value of the instance is changed by one closure, the other closures over that instance of the variable see the new value; but closures over other instances of that same variable do not. This was new to me, but not really startling.</p>

<p>The big surprise to me was the realization that <i>any Perl subroutine can be a closure.</i> A normal named subroutine simply closes over the first instance of the variable -- the one that was current when it was compiled.</p>

<p>To see this, add to the end of <code>sub make_closures</code>, just before the right curly bracket,</p>

<pre>
    no warnings 'closure';
    sub add_first { $operand + $_[0] }
</pre>

<p>Subroutine <code>add_first()</code> will only see the first instance of <code>$operand</code>, which is the point of this example. But we need to silence a warning since nested named subroutines making use of the outer subroutine's arguments are so far from normal Perl that they may well represent an error on the part of the programmer. (Translation of the previous sentence: <i>Don't try this at home.</i>)</p>

<p>If we then insert calls to <code>add_first( 3 )</code> both before and after the call to <code>$chg_two-&gt;( 5 );</code> we see that <code>add_first()</code> returns the same value as <code>$add_two-&gt;()</code>, which shows that it accesses the same instance of <code>$operand</code> as <code>$add_two</code> and friends.</p>

<p>After all the above, it should come as no surprise that in the following, <code>sub increment{}</code> and <code>sub decremnt{}</code> close over <code>$number</code>.</p>

<pre>
{
    my $number = 0;
    sub increment {
        return $number++;
    }
    sub decrement {
        return --$number;
    }
}
</pre>

<p>No warning is generated because there is only ever one instance of <code>$number</code>. Of course, if there were only one subroutine above, it could also be written with a <code>state</code> variable. But the whole question of <code>my</code>, <code>our</code>, <code>state</code>, and <code>use vars</code> is a subject for another time.

<p>A demonstration of all the points discussed in this blog post is available on GitHub as <a href="https://gist.github.com/trwyant/d73e823d5ceb267101f1969569351395"><code>closures.t</code></a>.</p>
]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Do you want to partner with the Perl Marketing Committee to organize Hackathons in 2022?</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/hackothon-events-planning-2022"/>
  <id>tag:news.perlfoundation.org,2021-12-09:/post/hackothon-events-planning-2022</id>
  <published>2021-12-09T07:04:11</published>
  <updated>2021-12-09T07:04:11</updated>
  <summary>
  <![CDATA[
     In 2022, the Perl Marketing Committee are looking to help organize two hackathon events based on data collected in the survey run by Andrew Solomon. The initial focus areas are Editor/IDE integration, and CPAN Recommendations. The vision of the committee is to help make these events happen by partnering with projects within the Perl community. The goal is to make these events fun, rewarding, and successful, by being as accessible 
   ]]>
  </summary>
  <author>
    <name>Nic Evans</name>
  </author>
  <category term="Hackathons" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category"/>
  <category term="Marketing" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category"/>  <content type="html" xml:lang="en-us" xml:base="http://news.perlfoundation.org/">
   <![CDATA[
     
     <p>In 2022, the Perl Marketing Committee are looking to help organize two (or more!) hackathon events based on data collected in <a href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/newcomer-survey-results-actions">the survey run by Andrew Solomon.</a> </p>

<p>The initial focus areas are Editor/IDE integration, and CPAN Recommendations.</p>

<p>The vision of the committee is to help make these events happen by partnering with projects within the Perl community.</p>

<p>The goal is to make these events fun, rewarding, and successful, by being as accessible as possible. We also want to increase first time/one off contributions.</p>

<p>The committee hopes to improve accessibility by running these events as a hybrid of in-person and virtual attendance, with a primary location for people to attend in-person, virtual attendance from any location, and perhaps semi-formal/adhoc satellite locations. Further, we are eager to see how language barriers, visual impairment, hearing impairment, etc. can be brought down with video chat software (many with live transcription), text chat with modern translation, etc.</p>

<p>By working with projects before the event, a range of tasks will be available to help people of differing experience levels make their first contribution to the project.</p>

<p>The committee will reach out to various projects in the near future to get the ball rolling.</p>

<p>Comments and feedback are welcome below, especially people keen to be involved with organizing.</p>

    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Advent of Code Day 6, 7 and 8</title>
    <link href="http://domm.plix.at/perl/2021_aoc_day_06_to_08.html"/>
    <id>http://domm.plix.at/perl/2021_aoc_day_06_to_08.html</id>
    <updated>2021-12-08T22:42:56+00:00</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <summary type="html">Day 6 - Lanternfish

Did the first part via an Array, because I was expecting some GoL stuff in Part 2. There wasn't and the Array-based solution would take forever for part 2. So after a bit of ...</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/7"&gt;Day 6&lt;/a&gt; - Lanternfish&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did the first part via an Array, because I was expecting some GoL stuff in Part 2. There wasn't and the Array-based solution would take forever for part 2. So after a bit of thinking (and (for once) not looking at reddit for ideas) I realized that the position of each fish is irrelevant, and we just need to count the fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Counting fish is faster than fish-herding them in an array&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So part 2 is converted to a hash (where the keys are the generation of the fish, and the value the number of fishes at that generation), and a very simple loop to move the fish around. I had a small problem while figuring out when to add fish vs just set them, but the &lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/6811e15ec44cb4f4702d00ca9254a6df044ef90f/2021/06_2.pl"&gt;finished code is quite clear to read&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Cleanup&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I later like to come back to the code and clean it up a bit more (and maybe make it a bit smarter). While doing so I realized that I don't need a hash, I can use the fish generation as the index of an array.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;my @fish = map { 0 } ( 0 .. 8 );
for ( split( ',', &amp;lt;&amp;gt; ) ) {
    $fish[ $_ ]++;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read in the list of fish and store them in an array indexed by the generation. The first line inits the array with 0s to prevent undefined warnings.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;for my $day ( 1 .. 256 ) {
    my $born = 0;
    for my $gen ( 0 .. 8 ) {
        if ( $gen  0 ) {
            $born = $fish[$gen];
        }
        else {
            $fish[ $gen - 1 ] = $fish[$gen];
        }
    }
    $fish[6] += $fish[8] = $born;
    say "$day: ".sum(@fish) if ( $day  80 || $day == 256 );
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for each of the days we go through all the generations, and move them one generation down (&lt;code&gt;$fish[ $gen - 1 ] = $fish[$gen]&lt;/code&gt;). But the fish of generation 0 move to generation 6, and spawn the same number (&lt;code&gt;$born&lt;/code&gt;) in generation 8. To calculate the sum of the fish i use &lt;code&gt;List::Util&lt;/code&gt;'s &lt;code&gt;sum&lt;/code&gt;, but only for day 80 (part 1) and day 256 (part 2). My stupid array-based solution takes nearly a second for the first part, and probably forever for the second part; but the smarter solution takes only a few milliseconds for both parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/06_1.pl"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/06_2.pl"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/7"&gt;Day 7&lt;/a&gt; - The Treachery of Whales&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first part I had a mathy gut feeling that the solution has to be related with the &lt;code&gt;median&lt;/code&gt; of the values, so I hacked up a solution (using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPAN &lt;/span&gt;module &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Statistics::Basic"&gt;Statistics::Basic&lt;/a&gt; for the statistics stuff), which worked for the test data. Tried the proper input and got a star!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I assumed that part 2 will need &lt;code&gt;mean&lt;/code&gt;. Tried it on the test-data, didn't work because the mean was a float, which I truncated to int. So I tried rounding it up, now it worked with test, but not with live data. Instead of thinking a tiny bit more, I thought that a &lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/commit/e687a0a93e97f4bc22c425b71162787bff03fe01"&gt;brute force approach&lt;/a&gt; will also work and just calculated the fuel for all possible positions, which worked fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While brushing teeth (it's morning here..) I realized that I should also have tried the rounded down mean, so I did that, and got the proper result (much faster..). Of course I now knew that the result was in fact correct, but I don't have enough mathy gut feelings to prove that. Then I also used Gauss' sum formula for the fuel consumption. When I was coding the fuel sum I knew there was a smarter solution, but again the computer was fast enough for me to not use my brain (not sure I like this trend..)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's the cleaned up solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;use Statistics::Basic qw(:all);

my @crabs = split( ',', &amp;lt;&amp;gt; );
my $mean  = mean(@crabs);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read in the data and calculate the &lt;code&gt;mean&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;my $res=0;
for my $cand ( int($mean), sprintf( '%.0f', $mean ) ) {
    my $fuel;
    for my $c (@crabs) {
        my $diff = abs( $c - $cand );
        $fuel += $diff * ( $diff + 1 ) / 2;
    }
    $res = !$res ? $fuel : $fuel &amp;lt; $res ? $fuel : $res;
}
say $res;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the rounded down and rounded up mean, and for each go through all the crabs. Get the distance it has to travel, and use Gauss to calculate the fuel consumption. Then use the barley readable line &lt;code&gt;$res = !$res ? $fuel : $fuel &amp;lt; $res ? $fuel : $res;&lt;/code&gt; to figure out which of the two candidates uses less fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite task this year so far :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/07_1.pl"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/07_2.pl"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/8"&gt;Day 8&lt;/a&gt; - Seven Segment Search&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part was ridiculously easily especially considering the absurd long and complex explanation of the task. Just go through the second list of words and count those with the correct length:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;my $hit;
for (&amp;lt;&amp;gt;) {
    chomp;
    my ( $first, $second ) = split / \| /;
    for my $read ( split / /, $second ) {
        my $l = length($read);
        $hit++ if ( $l  2 || $l  3 || $l  4 || $l  7 );
    }
}
say $hit;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;And now to something complex&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that a few numbers are based on the length of the input (we did learn something in part 1!). To figure out the rest, I grabbed some of the best dev tools, pen &amp;amp; paper, and draw the missing numbers, and which lines are needed to get them. I soon realized that, from the numbers using 5 lines, only the 3 overlaps completely with the 1. This means that I need not figure out the exact position of each line, just which ones overlap. After a bit more drawing and thinking I found ways to identify the other numbers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        my $l    = length($read);
        my $cand = [ split( //, $read ) ];
        if ( my $num = $direct{$l} ) {
            $res[$num] = $cand;
        }
        elsif ( $l  5 ) {
            if ( List::Compare-&gt;new( $cand, $res[1] )-&gt;get_intersection  2 ) {
                $res[3] = $cand;
            }
            elsif ( List::Compare-&amp;gt;new( $cand, $res[4] )-&amp;gt;get_intersection  3 ) {
                $res[5] = $cand;
            }
            else {
                $res[2] = $cand;
            }
        }
        elsif ( $l  6 ) {
            if ( List::Compare-&amp;gt;new( $cand, $res[1] )-&amp;gt;get_intersection  1 ) {
                $res[6] = $cand;
            }
            elsif ( List::Compare-&gt;new( $cand, $res[4] )-&gt;get_intersection  4 ) {
                $res[9] = $cand;
            }
            else {
                $res[0] = $cand;
            }
        }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was to lazy to come up with my own way to find the intersection of two arrays (see &lt;a href="https://abigail.github.io/HTML/AdventOfCode/2021/day-08.html"&gt;Abigale's post&lt;/a&gt; for a nice one), so I used &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/List::Compare"&gt;List::Compare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest was simple: Map the letter combinations to their respective value:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;   my %decode;
    for ( my $i = 0; $i &amp;lt; @res; $i++ ) {
        $decode{ join( '', sort $res[$i]-&amp;gt;@* ) } = $i;
    }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally go through the second set of readings, and convert them to a 4-digit number, and sum them all up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;   my $output;
    for my $read ( split / /, $second ) {
        my $lookup = join( '', sort split( //, $read ) );
        $output .= $decode{$lookup};
    }
    $sum += $output;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a very nice task!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/08_1.pl"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/08_2.pl"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
    <category term="git"/>
    <category term="AdventOfCode"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>JavaScript Supported Web Scraping using Perl and Selenium</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/yuki_kimoto/2021/12/javascript-supported-web-scraping-using-perl-and-selenium.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2021:/users/yuki_kimoto//2020.10568</id>
    <published>2021-12-08T06:52:37Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-08T07:04:51Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Yuki Kimoto</name>
        
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/yuki_kimoto/">
        <![CDATA[<p><img src="https://perlclub.net/images/corporate/perl_club_company_logo.png"></p>

<p><a href="https://perlclub.net/en">Perl Club</a> starts to translate Japanese Perl Tutorial to English. Yuki Kimoto is one of the Perl Messengers.</p>

<p>Perl Club decides to write all articles English at first.</p>

<p>This is a first English-first article. </p>

<p>If you want to scrape web contents, this article explains how to scrape web contents using Perl and Selenium.</p>

<blockquote>
<a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20211119124656.html">JavaScript Supported Web Scraping using Perl and Selenium</a>

<p><br></p>

<p>I explain JavaScript supported web scraping using Perl and Selenium::Remote::Driver. Selenium::Remote::Driver is a Perl module for Selenium. Selenium provides the APIs for JavaScript supported web scraping.</p>

<blockquote>

<p><br />
</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Perl Weekly Challenge 142: Divisor Last Digit and Sleep Sort</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/laurent_r/2021/12/perl-weekly-challenge-142-divisor-last-digit-and-sleep-sort.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogs.perl.org,2021:/users/laurent_r//3226.10567</id>
    <published>2021-12-08T04:27:56Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-08T04:29:14Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>laurent_r</name>
        <uri>https://laurent-rosenfeld.developpez.com/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://blogs.perl.org/users/laurent_r/">
        <![CDATA[<p>These are some answers to the Week 142 of the <a href="https://perlweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-142/">Perl Weekly Challenge</a> organized by <a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/mohammad_s_anwar/">Mohammad S. Anwar</a>.</p>

<p><em>Spoiler Alert:</em> This weekly challenge deadline is due in a few days from now (on December 12, 2021 at 24:00). This blog post offers some solutions to this challenge, please don’t read on if you intend to complete the challenge on your own.</p>

<h2>Task 1: Divisor Last Digit</h2>

<p><em>You are given positive integers, <code>$m</code> and <code>$n</code>.</em></p>

<p><em>Write a script to find total count of divisors of <code>$m</code> having last digit <code>$n</code>.</em></p>

<p><em>Example 1:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: $m = 24, $n = 2
Output: 2

The divisors of 24 are 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8 and 12.
There are only 2 divisors having last digit 2 are 2 and 12.
</code></pre>

<p><em>Example 2:</em></p>

<pre><code>Input: $m = 30, $n = 5
Output: 2

The divisors of 30 are 1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 10 and 15.
There are only 2 divisors having last digit 5 are 5 and 15.
</code></pre>

<h3>Divisor Last Digit in Raku</h3>

<p>We first generate all divisors of the input integer (including 1 and the input number itself, as these may end-up with the right digit), using a <code>grep</code> testing the divisibility of each number less than or equal to the input integer, and then use another <code>grep</code> to keep all divisors ending with the same digit as the other input integer.</p>

<pre><code>use v6;

sub count_divisors (UInt $m, UInt $n) {
    my @divisors = grep {$m %% $_}, 1..$m;
    my $last-digit = substr $n, *-1;
    my @eligible-divisors = grep { $last-digit == substr $_, *-1 }, @divisors;
    return @eligible-divisors.elems;
}

for (24, 34), (24, 12), (30, 45) {
  say "$_ -&gt; ", count_divisors $_[0], $_[1];
}
</code></pre>

<p>This program displays the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ raku ./div_last_digit.raku
24 34 -&gt; 2
24 12 -&gt; 2
30 45 -&gt; 2
</code></pre>

<h3>Divisor Last Digit in Perl</h3>

<p>This is essentially a Perl port of the Raku program just above:</p>

<pre><code>use strict;
use warnings;
use feature "say";

sub count_divisors {
    my ($m, $n) = @_;
    my @divisors = grep {$m % $_ == 0} 1..$m;
    my $last_digit = substr $n, -1, 1;
    my @eligible_divisors = grep { $last_digit == substr $_, -1, 1 } @divisors;
    return scalar @eligible_divisors;
}
for ([24, 34], [24, 12], [30, 45]) {
  say "@$_ -&gt; ", count_divisors $_-&gt;[0], $_-&gt;[1];
}
</code></pre>

<p>This program displays the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ perl ./div_last_digit.pl
24 34 -&gt; 2
24 12 -&gt; 2
30 45 -&gt; 2
</code></pre>

<h2>Task 2: Sleep Sort</h2>

<p><em>Another joke sort similar to JortSort suggested by champion Adam Russell.</em></p>

<p><em>You are given a list of numbers.</em></p>

<p><em>Write a script to implement Sleep Sort. For more information, please checkout this <a href="https://iq.opengenus.org/sleep-sort/">post</a>.</em></p>

<p>The basic idea of the sleep sort is that you launch a thread (or a process) for each item in the array to be sorted.  Each thread then waits (or &#8220;sleeps&#8221;) for an amount of time proportional to the value of the element for which it was created and finally prints this value. If things go right, the array item with the smallest value is printed first, then the next higher value, and so on until lastly the item with largest value, so that you eventually get the array items in ascending sorted order. </p>

<h3>Sleep Sort in Raku</h3>

<p>For each value in the input array, we <a href="https://docs.raku.org/routine/start">start</a> a promise. In the code for each promise, the thread is made to <a href="https://docs.raku.org/routine/sleep">sleep</a> for an amount of time proportional to the value (here, half the value) and then prints the value:</p>

<pre><code>use v6;

await &lt;6 8 1 12 2 14 5 2 1 0&gt;.map: { start {sleep $_/2; .say} };
</code></pre>

<p>This scripts prints out the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ raku ./sleep-sort.raku
0
1
1
2
2
5
6
8
12
14
</code></pre>

<p>This nice <a href="https://andrewshitov.com/2019/09/09/sleep-sort-in-perl-6/">post by Andrew Shitov</a> provides a somewhat similar solution also using promises, together with quite a bit of further explanations.</p>

<h3>Sleep Sort in Perl</h3>

<p>The Perl solution is similar, but spawns processes using <code>fork</code>. The solution looks simple, but since I had not used <code>fork</code> for ages, it took me quite a while to get it to work properly.</p>

<pre><code>use strict;
use warnings;
use feature "say";

while ($_ = shift and @ARGV &gt;= 1) {
    last unless fork;
}
sleep $_;
say;
wait;
</code></pre>

<p>This script displays the following output:</p>

<pre><code>$ perl sleep-sort.pl 5 7 3 4 1 2 9
1
2
3
4
5
7
9
</code></pre>

<h2>Wrapping up</h2>

<p>The next week Perl Weekly Challenge will start soon. If you want to participate in this challenge, please check https://perlweeklychallenge.org/ and make sure you answer the challenge before 23:59 BST (British summer time) on December 19, 2021. And, please, also spread the word about the Perl Weekly Challenge if you can.</p>
]]>
        

    </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>JavaScript Supported Web Scraping using Perl and Selenium with Google ChromeDriver</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/yukikimoto/javascript-supported-web-scraping-using-perl-and-selenium-with-google-chromedriver-31n" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://perlclub.net/en"&gt;Perl Club&lt;/a&gt; starts to translate Japanese Perl Tutorial to English. Yuki Kimoto is one of the Perl Messengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl Club decides to write all articles English at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a first English-first article. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to scrape web contents, this article explains how to scrape web contents using Perl and Selenium with GoogleChrome Driver.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.perlzemi.com/blog/20211119124656.html"&gt;JavaScript Supported Web Scraping using Perl and Selenium&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I explain JavaScript supported web scraping using Perl and Selenium::Remote::Driver. Selenium::Remote::Driver is a Perl module for Selenium. Selenium provides the APIs for JavaScript supported web scraping.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</content>
    <author>
      <name>Yuki Kimoto</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/yukikimoto/javascript-supported-web-scraping-using-perl-and-selenium-with-google-chromedriver-31n</id>
    <published>2021-12-08T02:17:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-08T02:17:15Z</updated>
    <category term="selenium"/>
    <category term="javascript"/>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="google"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sweeter Perl exception classes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/mjgardner/sweeter-perl-exception-classes-23hl" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://phoenixtrap.com/2021/11/23/video-a-year-of-being-wrong-on-the-internet/"&gt;mentioned&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href="https://thibaultduponchelle.github.io/the-ephemeral-miniconf/"&gt;Ephemeral Miniconf&lt;/a&gt; last month that as soon as I write about one Perl module (or five), someone inevitably brings up another (or seven) I’ve missed. And of course, it happened again &lt;a href="https://phoenixtrap.com/2021/11/30/vicious-test-mockery-of-a-perl-modulino/"&gt;last week&lt;/a&gt;: no sooner had I written in passing that I was using &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Exception::Class"&gt;Exception::Class&lt;/a&gt; than the denizens of the &lt;a href="https://web.libera.chat/#perl"&gt;Libera Chat IRC #perl channel&lt;/a&gt; insisted I should use &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Throwable"&gt;Throwable&lt;/a&gt; instead for defining my exceptions. (I’ve already blogged about various ways of &lt;a href="https://phoenixtrap.com/2021/02/22/exceptional-perl-failure-is-an-option/"&gt;catching exceptions&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why Throwable? Aside from Exception::Class’s author &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Exception::Class#DESCRIPTION"&gt;recommending it&lt;/a&gt; over his own work due to a &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/release/DROLSKY/Exception-Class-1.45/source/Changes#L57"&gt;“nicer, more modern interface,”&lt;/a&gt; Throwable is a &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Moo::Role"&gt;Moo role&lt;/a&gt;, so it’s composable into classes along with other &lt;a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/perlootut#Roles"&gt;roles&lt;/a&gt; instead of mucking about with multiple inheritance. This means that if your exceptions need to do something reusable in your application like &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Task::Kensho::Logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;, you can also consume a role that does that and not have so much duplicate code. (No, I’m not going to pick a favorite logging module; I’ll probably get that wrong too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, since Throwable is a role instead of a class, I would have to define several additional &lt;a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/functions/package"&gt;&lt;code&gt;package&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;s in my tiny &lt;a href="https://perlmaven.com/modulino-both-script-and-module"&gt;modulino&lt;/a&gt; script from last week, one for each exception class I want. The beauty of Exception::Class is its simple declarative nature: just &lt;a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/functions/use"&gt;&lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; it and &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Exception::Class#DECLARING-EXCEPTION-CLASSES"&gt;pass a list&lt;/a&gt; of desired class names along with options for attributes and whatnot. What’s needed for simple use cases like mine is a declarative syntax for defining several exception classes without the noise of multiple packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Throwable::SugarFactory"&gt;Throwable::SugarFactory&lt;/a&gt;, a module that enables you to do just that by adding an &lt;code&gt;exception&lt;/code&gt; function for declaring exception classes. (There’s also the similarly-named &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Throwable::Factory"&gt;Throwable::Factory&lt;/a&gt;; see the above discussion about never being able to cover everybody’s favorites.) The &lt;code&gt;exception&lt;/code&gt; function &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Throwable::SugarFactory#DECLARATION"&gt;takes three arguments&lt;/a&gt;: the name of the desired exception class as a string, a description, and an optional list of instructions Moo uses to build the class. It might look something like this:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Local::My::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Exceptions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Throwable::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;SugarFactory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nv"&gt;exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;GenericError&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;something bad happened&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;';&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;DetailedError&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;something specific happened&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;has&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;message&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;ro&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Throwable::SugarFactory takes care of creating constructor functions in Perl-style &lt;code&gt;snake_case&lt;/code&gt; as well as functions for detecting what kind of exception is being caught, so you can use your new exception library like this:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/env perl&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;experimental&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sx"&gt;qw(isa)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Feature::Compat::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;JSON::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;MaybeXS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Local::My::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Exceptions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nv"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;generic_error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;warn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;whoops!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;';&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nv"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;detailed_error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;message&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;you got me&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;encode_json&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;to_hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;isa&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;DetailedError&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;defined&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;does&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;('&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Throwable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;');&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The above also demonstrates a couple of other Throwable::SugarFactory features. First, you get a &lt;code&gt;to_hash&lt;/code&gt; method that returns a hash reference of all exception data, suitable for serializing to JSON. Second, you &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Throwable::SugarFactory#Throwable"&gt;get all of Throwable’s methods&lt;/a&gt;, including &lt;code&gt;throw&lt;/code&gt; for re-throwing exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does this leave last week’s &lt;a href="https://foaas.com/"&gt;FOAAS.com&lt;/a&gt; modulino client demonstration of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mock_object"&gt;object mocking&lt;/a&gt; tests? With a little bit of rewriting to define and then use our sweeter exception library, it looks like this. You can &lt;a href="https://phoenixtrap.com/2021/11/30/vicious-test-mockery-of-a-perl-modulino/"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; for a description of the rest of its workings.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/env perl&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nb"&gt;package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Local::CallFOAAS::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Exceptions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Throwable::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;SugarFactory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;BEGIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;NoMethodError&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;no matching WebService::FOAAS method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;has&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;ro&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;ServiceError&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;error from WebService::FOAAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;has&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;message&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;ro&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nb"&gt;package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Local::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;CallFOAAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# this is a modulino&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Test2::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;V0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;             &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# enables strict, warnings, utf8&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# declare all the new stuff we're using&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;feature&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sx"&gt;qw(say state)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;experimental&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sx"&gt;qw(isa postderef signatures)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Feature::Compat::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Syntax::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Construct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sx"&gt;qw(non-destructive-substitution)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;WebService::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;FOAAS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Package::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Stash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;BEGIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Local::CallFOAAS::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Exceptions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$foaas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Package::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Stash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;('&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;WebService::FOAAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;');&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$run_as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="o"&gt;!!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ENV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;CPANTEST&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class="p"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;defined&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;scalar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;caller&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;                          &lt;span class="nb"&gt;undef&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;__PACKAGE__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$run_as&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;@ARGV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;defined&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$run_as&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;( $class, @args ) {&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;say&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;call_method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;@args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;No method &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;',&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;isa&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;NoMethodError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Service error: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;',&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;isa&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;ServiceError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Utilities&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;methods&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;($)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;@methods&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;sort&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sr"&gt;s/^foaas_(.+)/$1/r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="nb"&gt;grep&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sr"&gt;/^foaas_/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$foaas&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;list_all_symbols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;('&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;CODE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;');&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;@methods&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;call_method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;( $class, $method = '', @args ) {&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;%methods&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;$_&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;methods&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;no_method_error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="k"&gt;unless&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$methods&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$foaas&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;get_symbol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;("&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;")&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;@args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;service_error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;message&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Testing&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;( $class, @ ) {&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Package::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Stash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;@tests&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;sort&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;grep&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sr"&gt;/^_test_/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;list_all_symbols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;('&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;CODE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;');&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$test&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;@tests&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;subtest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$test&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="nv"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$test&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="nv"&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;diag&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;done_testing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;_test_can&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;($class) {&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;@subs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sx"&gt;qw(run call_method methods test)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;can_ok&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;@subs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;can do: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;@subs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;_test_methods&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;($class) {&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$mock&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;mock&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;WebService::FOAAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;track&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;methods&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$mock&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;override&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;ok&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;lives&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;call_method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; lives&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;ok&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;scalar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$mock&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;sub_tracking&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; called&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;_test_service_failure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;($class) {&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$mock&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;mock&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;WebService::FOAAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;';&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;methods&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$mock&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;override&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;sub &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;die&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;mocked&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="k"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="nv"&gt;dies&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;call_method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;isa_ok&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;ServiceError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; throws ServiceError on failure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;like&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sx"&gt;qr/^mocked/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;correct error in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;$method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Updated, thanks to &lt;a href="http://www.grinnz.com/"&gt;Dan Book&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/karenetheridge"&gt;Karen Etheridge&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/author/BOBK"&gt;Bob Kleemann&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt; The only goofy bit above is the need to put the exception calls in a &lt;code&gt;BEGIN&lt;/code&gt; block and then explic­it­ly call &lt;code&gt;BEGIN { Local::CallFOAAS::Exceptions-&amp;gt;import() }&lt;/code&gt;. Since the two pack­ages are in the same file, I can’t do a &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; state­ment since the implied &lt;a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/functions/require"&gt;&lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would look for a cor­re­spond­ing file or entry in &lt;a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/variables/%25INC"&gt;&lt;code&gt;%INC&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. (You can get around this by mess­ing with &lt;code&gt;%INC&lt;/code&gt; direct­ly or through a mod­ule like &lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/me::inlined"&gt;me::inlined&lt;/a&gt; that does that mess­ing for you, but for a single-​purpose mod­uli­no like this it’s fine.)&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://phoenixtrap.com/tip"&gt;Do you like what you see? Leave a tip!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <author>
      <name>Mark Gardner</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/mjgardner/sweeter-perl-exception-classes-23hl</id>
    <published>2021-12-07T15:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-07T15:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="oop"/>
    <category term="exceptions"/>
    <category term="moo"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>#541 - Hanukkah is over - Advent started</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/541.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Hi there</p>
<p>Hanukkah, the 8-day celebration of the Jews returning to Jerusalem and the rededication of the Temple on the Temple-mount is now over. We ate way too much and the UN passed only one resolution trying to eliminate the historical ties of Jews to this hill. Very good timing.</p>
<p>Now onto Advent!</p>
<p>How often do you remember to thank Mark Gardner for his extraordinary posts about Perl? I think I have only thanked him once. Maybe I should set up a cron job to send him a thank-you note every month. Or maybe I should <a href="https://phoenixtrap.com/tip/">leave him a tip</a>. Finally he set up a system where we can give him a one-time tip or, IMHO better yet, a recurring tip. It is so nice to see month-by-month that people still value your work even if they are too busy or too embarrassed to say it themselves.</p>
<p>Enjoy your week!</p></div>
    </content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/541.html</id>
    <published>2021-12-06T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-06T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Developing A Game Engine with Perl: Part 8 - Vim</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/ansigameengine/developing-a-game-engine-with-perl-part-8-vim-2gj5" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dev.to/ansigameengine/developing-a-game-engine-with-perl-part-2-mouse-input-43nj"&gt;As Always...&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;I DO NOT KNOW WHAT I AM DOING.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to start reading from the beginning. Check out the &lt;a href="https://dev.to/ansigameengine/developing-a-game-engine-with-perl-3b8"&gt;first article in this series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's step back from &lt;a href="https://dev.to/ansigameengine/developing-a-game-engine-with-perl-part-6-a-colourful-telnet-server-4i7g"&gt;typing code&lt;/a&gt; for a moment and talk about how that code is typed. There are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source-code_editor#Notable_examples"&gt;many options&lt;/a&gt; for a developer to code with, and we all have a preference. It's not so much a matter of right and wrong, as it is of comfort and enjoyment. For me, I code in &lt;a href="https://www.vim.org/download.php"&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--DXxsZ3CF--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/r64ntezh2wlam11ohdhc.jpeg" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--DXxsZ3CF--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/r64ntezh2wlam11ohdhc.jpeg" alt="" width="225" height="225"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  &lt;a href="#and-coding-in-vim-is-fun"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  ...and Coding in Vim is fun
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was introduced to Vim back in college. Our school used &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_AIX"&gt;AIX&lt;/a&gt; for their server OS and we were taught to use Vim. This was also my first introduction to a Unix environment. Coming from a home Dos/Windows environment and entering the Unix world came with challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mamchenkov.net/wordpress/2004/05/10/vim-for-perl-developers/"&gt;Using Vim&lt;/a&gt; twisted my brain and took a bit to get use to. But today, after using it for many years, it often feels &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0KRxhNrtVIY"&gt;very rhythmic&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iurhjlBum0o"&gt;fun&lt;/a&gt; to code. Also, not gonna lie, it kinda makes me feel that sense of "coolness" I got when watching &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Rn2cf_wJ4f4"&gt;Hackers&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--LS6FsB3F--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_66%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/7wan5j8kutdpoihzkhsq.gif" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--LS6FsB3F--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_66%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/7wan5j8kutdpoihzkhsq.gif" alt="Image description" width="480" height="360"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p96KIwW5RIc"&gt;Hahaha...&lt;/a&gt; That movie does &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; hold up well! Teenager me was so impressionable.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$me-&amp;gt;hides_face_in_shame();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We can verify my shame level using this code:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;use strict;
use warnings;
use Shameful::movies;

my $movie  = shift;
my $me     = new Shameful::movies();
my $shame  = $me-&amp;gt;watched($movie);
my $return = "Great Movie!";

if ($shame) {
    $return = $me-&amp;gt;hides_face_in_shame($movie);
}

print $return;
exit;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Running that code prints out the following.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;localhost:~/Fake_But_Should_Be_Real_Scripts/ # 
perl i_loved_watching.pl Hackers

Hack the planet!... More like Hide your face bro!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;
  &lt;a href="#ansi-in-vim"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  ANSI in Vim
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with ANSI codes directly in Vim I see a lot of &lt;code&gt;^[&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--kU2bjP2K--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/vx03498arazf6pauu39z.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--kU2bjP2K--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/vx03498arazf6pauu39z.png" alt="Image description" width="474" height="265"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Now this &lt;code&gt;^[&lt;/code&gt; isn't the same as &lt;code&gt;shift+6 and [&lt;/code&gt;. No, this represents the escape character and is highlighted blue in my Vim. If it was &lt;code&gt;shift+6 and [&lt;/code&gt; it would be coloured the same as regular text. Something very useful to know, you can type the escape character in Vim by pressing &lt;code&gt;ctrl+v&lt;/code&gt; and then the &lt;code&gt;escape&lt;/code&gt; key. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
  &lt;a href="#i-split-vim-up-to-open-multiple-files"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  I split Vim up to open multiple files
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the &lt;code&gt;:split&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;:vsplit&lt;/code&gt; command in Vim often to load in other files. Using &lt;code&gt;split&lt;/code&gt; will stack files above/below each other (split horizontally) and &lt;code&gt;vsplit&lt;/code&gt; does side by side (vertically). Sometimes I need to combine &lt;code&gt;split&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;vsplit&lt;/code&gt; to have 3 files at once. Switching between each file in (v)split can be done with &lt;code&gt;ctrl+w+w&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--ufTfubZN--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/89gr4cikr966i90xijah.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--ufTfubZN--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/89gr4cikr966i90xijah.png" alt="Image description" width="880" height="884"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
  &lt;a href="#so-colourful"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  So Colourful
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vim supports colour schemes. It's something I don't change often, so I always forget and have to look it up. Since I just did it recently after &lt;a href="https://dev.to/ansigameengine/developing-a-game-engine-with-perl-part-3-hardware-failure-server-upgrade-on1"&gt;upgrading the dev/test server&lt;/a&gt;, I'll share here with you all. You can change it with the :colorscheme command. The one I'm using is :colorscheme peachpuff. I also have syntax highlighting turned on with the :syntax on. I made it permanent by adding the commands to ~/.vimrc I code in &lt;a href="https://dev.to/ansigameengine/developing-a-game-engine-with-perl-part-4-uefi-vs-opensuse-installer-5e1c"&gt;OpenSuSE Linux&lt;/a&gt;, Vim config files may vary with your OS. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
  &lt;a href="#dont-try-this-at-work"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Don't try this at work
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running a bulk search and replace can cause unexpected results if you're not careful. I know I'm thankful for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Undo#History"&gt;whoever invented undo&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--WU8WiBEF--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/y96str6utiqwochk8183.png" class="article-body-image-wrapper"&gt;&lt;img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/practicaldev/image/fetch/s--WU8WiBEF--/c_limit%2Cf_auto%2Cfl_progressive%2Cq_auto%2Cw_880/https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/y96str6utiqwochk8183.png" alt="Image description" width="488" height="408"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
There are &lt;a href="https://linux.die.net/man/1/sed"&gt;many ways&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://linux.die.net/man/1/awk"&gt;search and replace&lt;/a&gt; the contents of a file in Linux and &lt;a href="https://perldoc.perl.org/perlrequick"&gt;Perl&lt;/a&gt;. However, when I'm in Vim, I often find it quickest to use the :%s command. Typically when I need to apply a search and replace to a whole file I use a command like this:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;:%s/\^[//g
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The format is &lt;code&gt;:%s/search_pattern/replace_with/g&lt;/code&gt; The search pattern I used in the above example is to find the escape character &lt;code&gt;^[&lt;/code&gt; I mentioned earlier and replace every occurrence with nothing &lt;code&gt;//g&lt;/code&gt;. I have to precede &lt;code&gt;^[&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;\&lt;/code&gt; so the &lt;a href="http://vimdoc.sourceforge.net/htmldoc/pattern.html"&gt;regular expression search pattern&lt;/a&gt; knows it's a literal escape character. I type &lt;code&gt;^[&lt;/code&gt; using ctrl+v and pressing escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  &lt;a href="#how-about-you"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  How about you?
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you code in Vim? What sort of tricks and tips have you learned? What colorscheme do you prefer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestions or comments please share constructively. Also please visit our social media pages for lots of fun videos and pictures showing the game engine in action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/ANSIGameEngine/"&gt;ANSI Game Engine on Instagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/ANSIGameEngine"&gt;ANSI Game Engine on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dev.to/ansigameengine/developing-a-game-engine-with-perl-part-7-fork-3acm"&gt;Prev &amp;lt;&amp;lt; Part 7 - Fork&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Next &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Coming Soon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <author>
      <name>Shawn Holland</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/ansigameengine/developing-a-game-engine-with-perl-part-8-vim-2gj5</id>
    <published>2021-12-06T07:41:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-06T07:41:20Z</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <category term="gamedev"/>
    <category term="devjournal"/>
    <category term="vim"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Like, It’s Just the First Ten Numbers Man!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/2021/12/05#pwc141" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The examples used here are from The Weekly Challenge problem statement and demonstrate 
the working solution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write a script to find lowest 10 positive integers having exactly 8 divisors&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;
sub factor{
    my($n) = @_;
    my @factors = (1, $n);
    foreach my $j (2..sqrt($n)){
        push @factors, $j if $n % $j == 0;
        push @factors, ($n / $j) if $n % $j == 0 &amp;&amp; $j ** 2 != $n;
    }    
    return @factors;  
}

sub first_ten_with_eight{
    my $i = 0;
    my @first_ten;  
    do{
        my @factors = factor($i);
        push @first_ten, $i if @factors == 8;   
        $i++; 
    }while(@first_ten != 10); 
    return @first_ten;
}

MAIN:{
    print join(", ", first_ten_with_eight()) . "\n";   
}  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-1.pl
24, 30, 40, 42, 54, 56, 66, 70, 78, 88
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have re-used that &lt;code&gt;factor()&lt;/code&gt; function quite a bit for these challenges, especially 
recently. My blog writing has been fairly terse recently and as much as I'd like to
be a bit more verbose I really am not sure if there all that much more to say about this
code that hasn't been said before!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are given positive integers, $m and $n. Write a script to find total count of 
integers created using the digits of $m which is also divisible by $n.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;
##
# You are given positive integers, $m and $n.
# Write a script to find total count of integers 
# created using the digits of $m which is also 
# divisible by $n.
##
use Data::PowerSet q/powerset/;

sub like_numbers{
    my($m, $n) = @_; 
    my @divisible; 
    for my $subset (@{powerset(split(//, $m))}){
        my $i = join("", @$subset);
        push @divisible, $i if $i &amp;&amp; $i != $m &amp;&amp; $i % $n == 0;
    }  
    return @divisible;
}

MAIN:{
    print like_numbers(1234, 2) . "\n";
    print like_numbers(768, 4) . "\n";
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-2.pl
9
3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've been making more use of &lt;code&gt;Data::PowerSet&lt;/code&gt; recently that I would have expected! If 
anyone is interested in seeing an implementation of the Power Set calculations see my
C++ solution links below. While not Perl the code is quite readable and should be 
adaptable easy to other languages. There is also a Rosetta Code entry for Power Set
but, frankly, many of the submissions there, especially the C++ and Perl ones are overly
convoluted in my opinion. Or at least much more so than the way I implemented it, which
I would think would be the more common method but I guess not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-141/"&gt;Challenge 141&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/PowerSet.html"&gt;Power Set Defined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/pod/Data::PowerSet"&gt;Data::PowerSet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rosettacode.org/wiki/Power_set"&gt;Rosetta Code Entry: Power Set&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://adamcrussell.livejournal.com/30630.html"&gt;C++ Solutions: Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://adamcrussell.livejournal.com/30842.html"&gt;C++ Solutions: Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/perl/pwc141</id>
    <published>2021-12-05T16:47:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-12-05T16:47:00-05:00</updated>
    <category term="/perl"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Advent of Code Day 1 to 5</title>
    <link href="http://domm.plix.at/perl/2021_aoc_day_01_to_05.html"/>
    <id>http://domm.plix.at/perl/2021_aoc_day_01_to_05.html</id>
    <updated>2021-12-05T16:45:36+00:00</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <summary type="html">As you have probably noted by the measurable reduction of programmer productivity worldwide, Advent of Code is running again. Here's a short recap of my experiences from day 1 to day 5.

I usually ...</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you have probably noted by the measurable reduction of programmer productivity worldwide, &lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; is running again. Here's a short recap of my experiences from day 1 to day 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually approach the problems straight-forward (or brute-force), mostly because I'm not that kind of smart to know all the nice shortcuts and algorithms (which I later usually read up on the very recommended "Solution Megathreads" on &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/"&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;. You can find me solutions &lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/tree/main/2021"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/1"&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt; - Sonar Sweep&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting of easy, just adding / comparing some values. I still learned something during the second task: When comparing a sliding window of data (at least in this simple case), you only need to compare the first and the last value, because the middle values are affecting both window-values the same way and thus can be ignored:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;12
24    24
53    53
      13&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can sum up 12+24+53 and compare that with the sum of 24+53+13, but you can just as well ignore 24+53 and just compare 12 and 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/01_1.pl"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/01_2.pl"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/2"&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt; - Dive!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still simple, a little bit of parsing and the rest was again just adding up numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/02_1.pl"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/02_2.pl"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/3"&gt;Day3&lt;/a&gt; - Binary Diagnostic&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some troubles remembering how to convert a binary sting (&lt;code&gt;1001101&lt;/code&gt;) to an int. I first used the rather ugly &lt;code&gt;my $bits='110101'; my $int = eval '0b'.$bits&lt;/code&gt;, and only "remembered" about &lt;code&gt;oct()&lt;/code&gt; after reading it in some other solutions. But I used unicode var names &lt;code&gt;$γ, $ε&lt;/code&gt; :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/03_1.pl"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/03_2.pl"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/4"&gt;Day 4&lt;/a&gt; - Giant Squid aka Bingo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I again forgot something I already learned in a previous Advent: If the input contains blocks separated by blank lines, it's much easier to just split the input on two newlines instead of remembering state and starting new blocks if there is an empty line...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I convert the horizontal rows and vertical cols into lines, so each bingo card has 10 lines. Each line is a Hash where key and value are the number (i.e. 42 =&amp;gt; 42) because I thought that in part 2 we might need to do something with the checked values (with turned out to not be the case, ah, well..)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a number is drawn, go through all the boards and all the rows, mark the drawn number with a X, and check if a line has 5 Xs (&lt;code&gt;my @checked = grep {/X/} values $line-&amp;gt;%*;&lt;/code&gt;). If it has, we have a winner, so calc the value and report it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory part 2 only needed to remove the exit, but as I had to remove bingo cards that have already one I had to convert my loop to use an iterator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/04_1.pl"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/04_2.pl"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/4"&gt;Day 5&lt;/a&gt; - Hydrothermal Venture&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a solution for part 1 quite quickly, but it didn't work for the proper data. So I let the code rest for a bit, went for a run, cooked lunch, and later checked a few of the posts on reddit. And indeed I found the needed tip: I was using a plain &lt;code&gt;sort&lt;/code&gt;, which (in Perl) sorts alphanumerically, and not by int value. This was quickly fixed by the spaceship operator: &lt;code&gt;sort { $a &amp;lt;=&amp;gt; $b }&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the diagonals in part 2 I wasted a lot of time on just mucking with the coordinates, without success. I knew what I had to do, but was too lazy to properly implement it. So late in the afternoon I took pen &amp;amp; paper, drawed some diagrams, and renamed my vars from &lt;code&gt;$x, $y&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;$row, $col&lt;/code&gt;, because I constantly messed up which was which. Also figuring out which direction was which took me an embarrassingly long time...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/05_1.pl"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code/blob/main/2021/05_2.pl"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Next week..&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to keep playing (and posting here and on reddit), but let's see what the combination of more complex tasks, work and family will allow :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <category term="git"/>
    <category term="AdventOfCode"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Raku CI Bot Grant Report October and November 2021</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/2021-10-raku-ci-bot-grant-update"/>
  <id>tag:news.perlfoundation.org,2021-12-05:/post/2021-10-raku-ci-bot-grant-update</id>
  <published>2021-12-05T14:50:48</published>
  <updated>2021-12-05T14:50:48</updated>
  <summary>
  <![CDATA[
     Patrick Böker submitted his report for the Raku CI Bot grant, for the months of October and November: In October and November most of my time was spent on finding and fixing bugs. Several problems I encountered are bugs in third party systems. Some of those I tackled, some remain as bug reports. Reported and fixed bugs: Red: Boolean checking DateTime columns fails when using Pg #530 Red: Checking multiple 
   ]]>
  </summary>
  <author>
    <name>Moritz Lenz</name>
  </author>
  <category term="Grants" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category"/>
  <category term="Raku Development" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category"/>  <content type="html" xml:lang="en-us" xml:base="http://news.perlfoundation.org/">
   <![CDATA[
     
     <p>Patrick Böker submitted his report for the Raku CI Bot grant, for the months of October and November:</p>

<hr />

<p>In October and November most of my time was spent on finding and fixing bugs.</p>

<p>Several problems I encountered are bugs in third party systems. Some of those I tackled, some remain as bug reports.</p>

<p>Reported and fixed bugs:</p>

<ul>
<li>Red: Boolean checking DateTime columns fails when using Pg <a href="https://github.com/FCO/Red/issues/530">#530</a> (Fix: FCO)</li>
<li>Red: Checking multiple existance checks results in empty WHEN clause [#531]
(https://github.com/FCO/Red/issues/531) (Fix: FCO)</li>
<li>Red: Type constraints in models are ignored on assignment [#513](https://
github.com/FCO/Red/issues/513) (Fix: FCO)</li>
<li>Red: Forbid .^create on non-type-objects <a href="https://github.com/FCO/Red/issues/488">#488</a> (Fix: FCO)</li>
<li>Red: Enums are not supported <a href="https://github.com/FCO/Red/issues/487">#487</a> (Fix: FCO)</li>
<li>Red: MVM_str_hash_lvalue_fetch_nocheck called concurrently on the same hash in Red::Model <a href="https://github.com/FCO/Red/issues/529">#529</a> (Fix: me)</li>
<li>Red: Remove duplicate operator <a href="https://github.com/FCO/Red/pull/535">#535</a> (Fix: me)</li>
<li>Cro::HTTP: Do not send the ENO_OF_STREAM flag twice [#160](https://
github.com/croservices/cro-http/pull/160) (Fix: me)</li>
</ul>

<p>Still unresolved bugs:</p>

<ul>
<li>MoarVM: NativeCall error <a href="https://github.com/MoarVM/MoarVM/issues/1614">#1614</a> (Severity: Medium)</li>
<li>Rakudo: Type check failed in binding to parameter for a named param that has not been passed <a href="https://github.com/rakudo/rakudo/issues/4647">#4647</a> (Severiy: Low, PR: Kaiepi)</li>
<li>Red: Unknown columns in query in concurrent setting <a href="https://github.com/FCO/Red/issues/537">#537</a> (Severity: High)</li>
<li>Red: Enum on Pg: invalid input syntax for type integer: \"a\" <a href="https://github.com/FCO/Red/issues/527">#527</a> (Severity: High)</li>
<li>Red: SELECTing enums generates broken WHERE in most cases <a href="https://github.com/FCO/Red/issues/495">#495</a> (Severity: Low, workaround available)</li>
<li>Red: LTA error with missing use Red:api&lt;2&gt; [#490](https://github.com/FCO/
Red/issues/490) (Severity: Low, only a feature request)</li>
<li>Cro::HTTP: Implement support for sslkeylogfile [#162](https://github.com/
croservices/cro-http/pull/162) (Severity: Low, feature request, PR: me (also 
[1](https://github.com/jnthn/p6-io-  +socket-async-ssl/pull/64))</li>
<li>Cro::HTTP: Implement remote window handling [#161](https://github.com/
croservices/cro-http/pull/161) (Severity: High, PR: me)</li>
<li>Test::Mock: List calls when with matching failed [#18](https://github.com/
jnthn/test-mock/pull/18) (Severity: Low, feature request, PR: me)</li>
</ul>

<p>The above list might lead to the impression that Red is bug ridden / unusable. 
It is important to understand, that Red is officially still alpha software, so 
bugs are expected. I also can't emphasize enough how quickly the Red
developers, especially FCO the lead dev, responded and tackled the problems I reported.</p>

<p>I do hope that instead of evading bugs in third party software by utilizing 
workarounds or switching the library, but instead golfing, reporting and fixing bugs, the quality of our software ecosystem will improve and future users will be able to enjoy a more reliable ecosystem.</p>

<p>In the CI bot I did the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Added an integration test to test the entire lifecycle of a PR</li>
<li>Implement App Authorization in the GitHub API lib</li>
<li>Implement a minimal GraphQL API in the GitHub API lib</li>
<li>Implement a configuration system to allow easy setup of a development environment</li>
<li>Write a first draft of a guide on how to set up a development environment</li>
<li>Rename RakuCIBot to RakudoCIBot, as the functionality is tailored to the 
Rakudo stack and won't be of any use to other Raku implementations. The repository has moved respectively to https://github.com/Raku/RakudoCIBot. It might make sense to move it into the <code>rakudo</code> org, but that's a separate step.</li>
<li>Introduce a logging framework and add some logging</li>
</ul>

<p>As it stands now, when using the SQLite database driver and ignoring some 
instability caused by some of the still unresolved bugs listed above, RCB now successfully polls GitHub for new PRs, starts a test run on the OBS 
backend, reads out the test results and persists them. Reporting back to 
GitHub is not yet working reliably.</p>

    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-2438191565013524930</id>
    <published>2021-12-04T17:28:00.001+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-12-04T17:28:16.407+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(ccclxx) 12 great CPAN modules released last week</title>
    <content type="html">Updates for &lt;i&gt;great CPAN modules&lt;/i&gt; released last week. A module is considered &lt;i&gt;great&lt;/i&gt; if its favorites count is greater or equal than 12.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/PLICEASE/Alien-Build-2.46' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Alien::Build&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Build external dependencies for use in CPAN &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;2.46&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-11-30&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 19&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 2.45 was 1 month, 2 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/OLIVER/App-Netdisco-2.052000' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;App::Netdisco&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - An open source web-based network management tool. &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;2.052000&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-11-30&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 13&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 2.051005 was 5 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/MIK/Crypt-JWT-0.034' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Crypt::JWT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - JSON Web Token &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.034&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-11-28&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 18&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.033 was 6 months, 27 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/OALDERS/libwww-perl-6.59' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;LWP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - The World-Wide Web library for Perl &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;6.59&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-02&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 153&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 6.58 was 1 month, 8 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/MARIOROY/MCE-1.876' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;MCE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Many-Core Engine for Perl providing parallel processing capabilities &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.876&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-02&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 89&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.875 was 16 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/MARIOROY/MCE-Shared-1.875' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;MCE::Shared&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - MCE extension for sharing data supporting threads and processes &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.875&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-03&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 14&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.873 was 1 year, 4 months, 2 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/PREACTION/Minion-Backend-mysql-0.30' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Minion::Backend::mysql&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - MySQL backend &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.30&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-11-30&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 12&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.29 was 5 months, 23 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/DBOOK/Mojo-SQLite-3.008' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Mojo::SQLite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - A tiny Mojolicious wrapper for SQLite &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;3.008&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-11-28&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 24&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 3.007 was 3 months, 26 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/TEODESIAN/Selenium-Remote-Driver-1.46' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Selenium::Remote::Driver&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Perl Client for Selenium Remote Driver &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.46&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-04&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 44&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.45 was 1 month, 14 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/DANBERR/Sys-Virt-v7.10.0' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Sys::Virt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - libvirt Perl API &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;v7.10.0&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-01&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 15&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: v7.9.0 was 29 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/EXODIST/Test2-Suite-0.000144' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Test2::Suite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Distribution with a rich set of tools built upon the Test2 framework. &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;0.000144&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-03&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 31&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 0.000142 was 18 days before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://metacpan.org/release/PREACTION/Yancy-1.085' target='_blank'&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;'&gt;Yancy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - The Best Web Framework Deserves the Best CMS &lt;ul&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Version: &lt;strong&gt;1.085&lt;/strong&gt; on 2021-12-04&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Votes: 42&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;li&gt;Previous version: 1.084 was 1 month, 1 day before&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/2438191565013524930/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/ccclxx-12-great-cpan-modules-released.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/2438191565013524930"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/2438191565013524930"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/ccclxx-12-great-cpan-modules-released.html" title="(ccclxx) 12 great CPAN modules released last week"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-7225888110025479431</id>
    <published>2021-12-04T17:26:00.002+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-12-04T17:26:21.895+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(cdxciii) metacpan weekly report - Mojolicious</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the weekly favourites list of CPAN distributions. Votes count: 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Week's winner: &lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Mojolicious" target="_blank"&gt;Mojolicious (+2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build date: 2021/12/04 16:26:06 GMT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clicked for &lt;u&gt;first time&lt;/u&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/JSON::Schema::Modern::Document::OpenAPI" target="_blank"&gt;JSON::Schema::Modern::Document::OpenAPI&lt;/a&gt; - One OpenAPI v3.1 document&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Increasing&lt;/u&gt; its reputation:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/aliased" target="_blank"&gt;aliased&lt;/a&gt; (+1=32)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/App::Cmd" target="_blank"&gt;App::Cmd&lt;/a&gt; (+1=43)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/App::Iptables2Dot" target="_blank"&gt;App::Iptables2Dot&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/App::shcompgen" target="_blank"&gt;App::shcompgen&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Data::Faker" target="_blank"&gt;Data::Faker&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Date" target="_blank"&gt;Date&lt;/a&gt; (+1=5)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/DBI" target="_blank"&gt;DBI&lt;/a&gt; (+1=251)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Enbugger" target="_blank"&gt;Enbugger&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Getopt::Long::Complete" target="_blank"&gt;Getopt::Long::Complete&lt;/a&gt; (+1=12)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/IO::Prompter" target="_blank"&gt;IO::Prompter&lt;/a&gt; (+1=23)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/libwww::perl" target="_blank"&gt;libwww::perl&lt;/a&gt; (+1=153)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/MCE" target="_blank"&gt;MCE&lt;/a&gt; (+1=89)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Mojo::IOLoop::ReadWriteProcess" target="_blank"&gt;Mojo::IOLoop::ReadWriteProcess&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Mojo::IRC" target="_blank"&gt;Mojo::IRC&lt;/a&gt; (+1=13)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Mojolicious" target="_blank"&gt;Mojolicious&lt;/a&gt; (+2=465)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/MojoX::HTTP::Async" target="_blank"&gt;MojoX::HTTP::Async&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Net::SSL::ExpireDate" target="_blank"&gt;Net::SSL::ExpireDate&lt;/a&gt; (+1=7)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Parallel::ForkManager" target="_blank"&gt;Parallel::ForkManager&lt;/a&gt; (+1=90)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Perl::Critic::CognitiveComplexity" target="_blank"&gt;Perl::Critic::CognitiveComplexity&lt;/a&gt; (+1=2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Sys::SigAction" target="_blank"&gt;Sys::SigAction&lt;/a&gt; (+1=11)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Term::ANSIColor" target="_blank"&gt;Term::ANSIColor&lt;/a&gt; (+1=54)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Test::Perl::Critic" target="_blank"&gt;Test::Perl::Critic&lt;/a&gt; (+1=14)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Test::XPath" target="_blank"&gt;Test::XPath&lt;/a&gt; (+1=3)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Text::Unidecode" target="_blank"&gt;Text::Unidecode&lt;/a&gt; (+1=32)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/7225888110025479431/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/cdxciii-metacpan-weekly-report.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/7225888110025479431"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/7225888110025479431"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/cdxciii-metacpan-weekly-report.html" title="(cdxciii) metacpan weekly report - Mojolicious"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0">
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5910101498857524639.post-607926694231674912</id>
    <published>2021-12-04T17:25:00.000+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-12-04T17:25:10.796+01:00</updated>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="cpan"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="perl"/>
    <title type="text">(dxii) stackoverflow perl report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;These are the ten most rated questions at &lt;a href="http://www.stackoverflow.com"&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; last week.&lt;br/&gt;Between brackets: [&lt;b&gt;question score&lt;/b&gt; / answers count]&lt;br/&gt;Build date: 2021-12-04 16:19:09 GMT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr/&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70167857" target="_blank"&gt;Why would you ever need (?(R)...|...) if condition in a regex?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;5&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70158802" target="_blank"&gt;MultiDimensional array Input to Single array in Perl&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70139704" target="_blank"&gt;Perl code executed alongside C program writes incorrect byte length to memory in Windows&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70207227" target="_blank"&gt;Perl way to allocate some memory inglobal array&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/1]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70179933" target="_blank"&gt;Perl Dynaloader gives Usage error while calling function with parameters&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/0]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70181597" target="_blank"&gt;In Mojolicious can I forward to another action?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;/0]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70190875" target="_blank"&gt;How do I search and replace a string after an arbitrary amount of white space in bash?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/4]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70193994" target="_blank"&gt;How to avoid line insert to the file if the line is already present in the file?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/4]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70138714" target="_blank"&gt;Perl match and extract phone number with (312) 555-1212 format&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/70160375" target="_blank"&gt;Perl: What is the preferred way of evaluating expressions besides eval?&lt;/a&gt; - [&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;/2]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
    <link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/feeds/607926694231674912/comments/default" title="Enviar comentarios"/>
    <link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/dxii-stackoverflow-perl-report.html#comment-form" title="0 comentarios"/>
    <link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/607926694231674912"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/5910101498857524639/posts/default/607926694231674912"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com/2021/12/dxii-stackoverflow-perl-report.html" title="(dxii) stackoverflow perl report"/>
    <author>
      <name>Unknown</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/>
    </author>
    <thr:total>0</thr:total>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>100 Languages Speedrun: Episode 15: Awk</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://dev.to/taw/100-languages-speedrun-episode-15-awk-1d55" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Awk is basically a proto-Perl. As Perl was one of the most influential language of all times (JavaScript, Ruby, and PHP are all Perl's direct descendants), Awk is indirectly quite historically important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There hasn't been any good reason to use Awk for decades now. As I keep saying over and over, if you write anything nontrivial, just use a real programming language like Ruby, Python, or Perl. But it's still interesting for historical reason, so let's check what coding was like back in the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#hello-world"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Hello, World!
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awk scripts are a series of &lt;code&gt;pattern { command }&lt;/code&gt;, where pattern is most often a regular expression. If script contains any such pattern, it will be executed on each line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's one way to say Hello, World! in Awk:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/./&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;Hello, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;





&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ seq 1 5 | ./hello.awk
Hello, 1!
Hello, 2!
Hello, 3!
Hello, 4!
Hello, 5!
$ ./hello.awk
World
Hello, World!
Bob Ross
Hello, Bob!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So any line that contains non-whitespace characters will result in a hello. String concatenation is done by just putting a few strings next to each other. &lt;code&gt;"Hello, " $1 "!"&lt;/code&gt; is what would be &lt;code&gt;"Hello, " + $1 + "!"&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;"Hello, " . $1 . "!"&lt;/code&gt; or such in a more reasonable language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each line is &lt;code&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt;, and it's also automatically split into words, so &lt;code&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt; means first word of currently processed lines, &lt;code&gt;$2&lt;/code&gt; means second word, etc. Those special variables are used for regular expression's first, second etc. match in Perl, Ruby, and some other languages, and I think that's where they came from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#sum-numbers-from-stdin"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Sum numbers from STDIN
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some other patterns like &lt;code&gt;BEGIN&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;END&lt;/code&gt; to do before and after processing lines. Here's a simple Awk program for adding all numbers, one per line:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;BEGIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/[0-9]+/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;END&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Which works like this:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ seq 10 20 | ./sum.awk
165
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Awk has pre-Perl regular expressions, so things like &lt;code&gt;\d&lt;/code&gt; don't work. That's another reason why it's better to use something more modern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awk's &lt;code&gt;BEGIN { }&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;END { }&lt;/code&gt; blocks are still present in Perl, Ruby, and some other languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#fizzbuzz-with-regexp"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  FizzBuzz with regexp
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to do the FizzBuzz is to reuse our regular expressions from episode 7. At first you might think command block would just do &lt;code&gt;{ print "FizzBuzz" }&lt;/code&gt; or such, but then all the other blocks would match too (divisible by 15 is also divisible by 3 and 5 etc.). An easy way is to modify &lt;code&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt; variable (current line). We print it at the end.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/^(([0369]*[147]([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*([258][0369]*[258]|[147])|[0369]*[258])(([147][0369]*[147]|[258])([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*([258][0369]*[258]|[147])|([147][0369]*[258]|[0369]?))*(([147][0369]*[147]|[258])([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*[258][0369]*|[147][0369]*)|([0369]*[147]([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*[258][0369]*|[0369]*))0$/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;FizzBuzz&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/^(([0369]*[147]([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*([258][0369]*[258]|[147])|[0369]*[258])(([147][0369]*[147]|[258])([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*([258][0369]*[258]|[147])|([147][0369]*[258]|[0369]?))*(([147][0369]*[147]|[258])([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*([258][0369]*[147]|[0369]?)|([147][0369]*[147]|[258]))|([0369]*[147]([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*([258][0369]*[147]|[0369]?)|[0369]*[147]))5$/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;FizzBuzz&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/^.*[05]$/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;Buzz&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/^(([0369]*[147]([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*([258][0369]*[258]|[147])|[0369]*[258])(([147][0369]*[147]|[258])([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*([258][0369]*[258]|[147])|([147][0369]*[258]|[0369]?))*(([147][0369]*[147]|[258])([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*[258][0369]*|[147][0369]*)|([0369]*[147]([258][0369]*[147]|[0369])*[258][0369]*|[0369]*))$/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;Fizz&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/./&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;To use it:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ seq 1 20 | ./fizzbuzz.awk
1
2
Fizz
4
Buzz
Fizz
7
8
Fizz
Buzz
11
Fizz
13
14
FizzBuzz
16
17
Fizz
19
Buzz
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#fizzbuzz"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  FizzBuzz
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A less ridiculous version would be this:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;FizzBuzz&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;next&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;Buzz&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;next&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;Fizz&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;";&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;next&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Any expression can be used as pattern. &lt;code&gt;next&lt;/code&gt; prevents all other pattern checks for the current lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#file-output"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  File output
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awk makes it really easy to print to files. This script sort out the input to &lt;code&gt;odd.txt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;even.txt&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/[13579]$/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;odd.txt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/[02468]$/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;even.txt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Like in shell &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; means overwrite the file, and &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; means append. But while it might look like it will keep reopening and overwriting so you only see last line, each file will be opened just once:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt; % seq 20 30 | ./file_output.awk
$ cat odd.txt
21
23
25
27
29
$ cat even.txt
20
22
24
26
28
30
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;And &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; without arguments is the same as &lt;code&gt;print $0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#pipe-output"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Pipe output
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even nicer, we can do similar redirection with pipes:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/[13579]$/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;tac&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Which matches all the lines with odd numbers and send them to &lt;code&gt;tac&lt;/code&gt; program to print them in backward order.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ seq 10 30 | ./reverse_odds.awk
29
27
25
23
21
19
17
15
13
11
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#fibbonacci"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Fibbonacci
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awk has normal function definitions. There's no distinction between number and string variables. If we put a command block without a pattern, it will match every line.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nv"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;fib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;fib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;fib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;fib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Which does:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ seq 1 20 | ./fib.awk
1
1
2
3
5
8
13
21
34
55
89
144
233
377
610
987
1597
2584
4181
6765
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#rolling-dice"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Rolling Dice
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awk has some trouble with command line arguments - it normally treats them as files to open. This code only works because we don't actually have any per-line patterns.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;BEGIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;ARGV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;];&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;rand&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;ARGV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We can use it to roll 5 100-sided dice:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ./dice.awk 100 5
84
39
78
79
91
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#tally"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Tally
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awk has associative arrays (nowadays usually called hashes or dictionaries).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight perl"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#!/usr/bin/awk -f&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;tally&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;END&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;tally&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;tally&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Awk has no way to print regular arrays or associative arrays. If you try to &lt;code&gt;print tally&lt;/code&gt; it will give you an error. It's another feature of modern programming languages that has roots in times of Awk, but is now done in much better ways.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight js-code-highlight"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ./dice.awk 6 100 | ./tally.awk
2 17
3 18
4 17
5 22
0 13
1 13
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#should-you-use-awk"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Should you use Awk?
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special purpose languages have their place, but what Awk is doing - processing text files - is no longer "special purpose". Pretty much every modern language excels at processing text files and matching regular expressions, and handles everything Awk does a lot better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awk made a lot of sense back when its originated, as C was godawful at text processing, and Unix shell was godawful at writing any kind of structured programs, so Awk was addressing an obvious need. In modern times where every programmer is familiar with a language like Ruby, Python, Perl, or pretty much anything else that can process text, there's no place for Awk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language also definitely shows its age. Its regular expression engine is bad. It doesn't have &lt;code&gt;console.log&lt;/code&gt; equivalent. It can't handle common text formats like CSV or JSON. It doesn't have sufficient Unicode capabilities. And so on. It does quite decently on conciseness, but only if you do exactly the kind of programs it likes - common requirements like parsing command line arguments will not work too well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awk is mainly of historical relevance, but it's not completely dead yet. If you work with a lot of Unix shell scripts, short Awk programs will be occasionally used there. I don't approve of this at all (seriously, just use real programming language like Ruby, Python, or Perl), but it might be useful to learn basics of Awk so you can read such shell code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
  &lt;a href="#code"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  Code
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/taw/100-languages-speedrun"&gt;All code examples for the series will be in this repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/taw/100-languages-speedrun/tree/master/episode-15-awk"&gt;Code for the Awk episode is available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <author>
      <name>Tomasz Wegrzanowski</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://dev.to/taw/100-languages-speedrun-episode-15-awk-1d55</id>
    <published>2021-12-04T14:49:33Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-04T14:49:33Z</updated>
    <category term="unix"/>
    <category term="awk"/>
    <category term="perl"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Grant report: Optimizations building upon the new Raku dispatch mechanism</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/jonathan-raku-2021-11"/>
  <id>tag:news.perlfoundation.org,2021-12-04:/post/jonathan-raku-2021-11</id>
  <published>2021-12-04T05:27:10</published>
  <updated>2021-12-04T05:27:10</updated>
  <summary>
  <![CDATA[
     Jonathan writes: My latest grant proposal was recently approved. I had the possibility to dedicate quality time to Raku work at the start of November, but knew I would be tied up with some other work in the latter part of the month. Thus I optimistically forged ahead with some grant work while I could, crossing my fingers for approval. This report covers what got done. The main completed task 
   ]]>
  </summary>
  <author>
    <name>Matthias Bloch</name>
  </author>
  <category term="Raku Development" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category"/>  <content type="html" xml:lang="en-us" xml:base="http://news.perlfoundation.org/">
   <![CDATA[
     
     <p>Jonathan writes:
<hr>
My latest <a href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/grant_proposal_raku_dispatch_optimizations">grant proposal</a> 
was <a href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/grants_nov_2021_votes">recently approved</a>. 
I had the possibility to dedicate quality time to Raku work at the start of November, but knew I would be tied up with some other
work in the latter part of the month. Thus I optimistically forged ahead with some grant work while I could,
crossing my fingers for approval. This report covers what got done.</p>

<p>The main completed task was to reorganize and streamline return and stack unwind handling. My work on the
new dispatch mechanism introduced a new callstack layout. This created an opportunity to simplify the way
we handle stack unwinding - that is, removing frames either because we are returning or because of an
exception. Since this happens for every single non-inlined block or routine that we call, savings here
have an impact on all but the most micro of micro-benchmarks. For example, a recursive Fibonacci benchmark
(written recursively to frustrate inlining) showed a 5% improvement from this work. The work also elimiated
some <code>malloc</code> calls in favor of callstack allocation in a number of situations, and resulted in overall
simpler and smaller code in MoarVM. Faster and simpler is certainly welcome.</p>

<p>I also did some optimization on frame invocation, primarily by splitting the specialized and unspecialized
callframe setup paths, which allowed for eliminating a number of branches that the C compiler was not able
to. This new factoring also revealed an opportunity to fold two <code>memset</code> calls into one, which was also a
welcome saving. This was worth a further 3% off the recursive Fibonacci benchmark. (To give a picture of how
Raku compares with Perl in this benchmark, Raku runs it in around two thirds of the time, despite the fact
that it has to cope with the potential upgrade of <code>Int</code> to a big integer.)</p>

<p>A central goal for the grant as a whole is to make progress on escape analysis. When I worked on this previously,
a particular challenge was the reliance on attribute container to vivify (get allocated) upon first touch. This
was not so much an optimization as a means to determine if an attribute had been initialized, for the purpose of
running defaults. Unfortunately, however, it greatly complicates the escape analysis of object graphs at creation
time, and makes all attribute access a little more costly. (One could also get occasionally surprised by the fact
that reading an attribute during a constructor would count as initializing it too.) Thus, I started working on a
new appraoch, based upon container descriptors, which are also the mechanism used in array and hash element
auto-vivification. The work in progress is currently a pull request, which needs further work to analyze why
it causes regressions in a small number of modules; this new approach does, however, already passes the
specification test suite.</p>

<p>I also did some design work for a faster and simpler way to handle <code>LEAVE</code> blocks. Today they carry quite some
performance overhead, we are unable to ever inline them, and needing to support them imposes a small, but non-zero,
cost on the exit of every callframe, regardless of if they have a <code>LEAVE</code> block. The new design I have worked on
should fix all of these issuses, and I hope to implement it during December. Even if <code>LEAVE</code> is rarely directly
used, it plays an important part in ensuring locks are reliabily released, and so is used implicitly in many
programs.</p>

<p>Finally, I also tracked down and fixed a bug in the intersection of dispatch resumption and inlining. </p>

<p><code>
Time spent on the grant: 30 hours 52 minutes
Time remaining on the grant: 169 hours 8 minuates
</code></p>

    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Merging multiple git repos with their commit history</title>
    <link href="http://domm.plix.at/perl/2021_12_git_merge_repos_with_history.html"/>
    <id>http://domm.plix.at/perl/2021_12_git_merge_repos_with_history.html</id>
    <updated>2021-12-01T12:14:41+00:00</updated>
    <category term="perl"/>
    <summary type="html">Advent of Code has started again and I'm again publishing my solutions to github (and probably also here). In the last two years I created on git repo for each year, but this year I changed my mind ...</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://adventofcode.com/2021"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; has started again and I'm again publishing my solutions to github (and probably also here). In the last two years I created on git repo for each year, but this year I changed my mind and want to have on repo containing a dir for each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I could just copy all the files into the &lt;a href="https://github.com/domm/advent_of_code"&gt;new repo&lt;/a&gt;, but that would lose the commit history. Which is unacceptable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The status quo ante&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
├── advent2019
│   ├── 01_1.pl
│   └── 01_2.pl
└── advent2020
    ├── 01_1.pl
    └── 01_2.pl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;What I want&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
└─── advent_of_code
    ├── 2019
    │   ├── 01_1.pl
    │   └── 01_2.pl
    └── 2020
        ├── 01_1.pl
        └── 01_2.pl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that git allows you to rewrite history and have once munged a repo using &lt;code&gt;git filter-branch&lt;/code&gt; (to completely delete some files and commits). I of course forgot the details, but after a little bit of searching and trial and error I got it working!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;First, prepare the old repo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prevent merge conflicts later, I first move the code in the old repo from the root dir into a new dir, eg &lt;code&gt;2019&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
└─── advent2019
    ├── 01_1.pl
    └── 01_2.pl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
└─── advent2019
    └─── 2019
        ├── 01_1.pl
        └── 01_2.pl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/fabiomaggio/ce7ecd7dffd27b32a45325204288efce"&gt;this gist&lt;/a&gt; very helpful, and adapted it to my needs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd advent2019
mkdir 2019
git filter-branch --tree-filter 'mkdir -p /tmp/ad; mv * /tmp/ad; mkdir 2019; mv /tmp/ad/* 2019/' --tag-name-filter cat --prune-empty -- --all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This uses &lt;code&gt;git filter-branch&lt;/code&gt; to move the old code to a temp dir (&lt;code&gt;mv * /tmp/ad&lt;/code&gt;) and then move it back to the new location (&lt;code&gt;mv /tmp/ad/* 2019/&lt;/code&gt;), using some git magic to keep the history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was at it, I also removed some of the AdventOfCode input files which I had commited (but which we should not commit):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git filter-branch -f --tree-filter 'rm -f 2019/*.data' HEAD&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Second, import the repo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I can merge the old repo into my new unified repo. This time this &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/6004865"&gt;StackOverflow comment&lt;/a&gt; pointed me in the right direction. The basic idea is to add the old repo as a new remote, fetch the commits, and then merge them using &lt;code&gt;--allow-unrelated-histories&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd advent_of_code
git remote add old19 ../advent2019/
git fetch old19
git merge --allow-unrelated-histories old19/master
git remote remove old19&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then push, and we're done and have a nice unified repo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/perl/advent_of_code$ tree
.
├── 2019
│   ├── 01_1.pl
│   ├── 01_2.pl
├── 2020
│   ├── 01_1.pl
│   ├── 01_2.pl
│   ├── 01_2_golf.pl
├── 2021
│   ├── 01_1.pl
│   ├── 01_1_golf.pl
│   └── 01_2.pl
└── README.md&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the history was preserved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/perl/advent_of_code$ git log 2019/24_1.pl
commit dbaf0bc1df645bda61ec5cf7e623d478a179947e
Author: Thomas Klausner &amp;lt;domm@plix.at&amp;gt;
Date:   Fri Dec 27 10:10:10 2019 +0100

    no need to keep a map around, the rating is unique per map&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Win!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next steps: Fix all links pointing to the old repos to point to the new location, and maybe archive / delete the github repos (and/or have them redirect to the new unified repo)&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <category term="git"/>
    <category term="AdventOfCode"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>List of new CPAN distributions – Nov 2021</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlancar.wordpress.com/2021/12/01/list-of-new-cpan-distributions-nov-2021/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><table>
<tr>
<th>dist</th>
<th>author</th>
<th>first_version</th>
<th>latest_version</th>
<th>abstract</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/API-Mathpix">API-Mathpix</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/ERIAM">ERIAM</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>Use the API of Mathpix</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Acme-CPANModulesBundle-Import-DAVECROSS">Acme-CPANModulesBundle-Import-DAVECROSS</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>Acme::CPANModules::* created from DAVECROSS's posts</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Acme-MarkdownTest">Acme-MarkdownTest</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/NEILB">NEILB</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>test module to see how markdown is handled</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Alien-Meson">Alien-Meson</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/ZMUGHAL">ZMUGHAL</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>Find or build meson build tool</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Alien-Ninja">Alien-Ninja</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/ZMUGHAL">ZMUGHAL</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>Find or build Ninja build tool</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Alien-SWIProlog">Alien-SWIProlog</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/ZMUGHAL">ZMUGHAL</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>Alien package for the SWI-Prolog Prolog interpreter</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Alien-libgpiod">Alien-libgpiod</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SACAVILIA">SACAVILIA</a></td>
<td>v0.1</td>
<td>v0.1</td>
<td>Find or build libgpiod (Linux GPIO character device library)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/AltaPay_Try">AltaPay_Try</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/MAFEMBRAC">MAFEMBRAC</a></td>
<td>v1.0.1</td>
<td>1.0.1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/App-CPANChangesUtils">App-CPANChangesUtils</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.074</td>
<td>0.074</td>
<td>Parse CPAN Changes file</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/App-Images-To-DjVu">App-Images-To-DjVu</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SKIM">SKIM</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>Base class and script for composing DjVu files from images.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/App-URIInfoUtils">App-URIInfoUtils</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>Utilities related to URI::Info</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/App-ansiexpand">App-ansiexpand</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/UTASHIRO">UTASHIRO</a></td>
<td>0.99</td>
<td>0.9901</td>
<td>ANSI sequence aware tab expand/unexpand command</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/App-geoCancerDiagnosticDatasetsRetriever">App-geoCancerDiagnosticDatasetsRetriever</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/AALAMEER">AALAMEER</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>GEO Cancer Diagnostic Datasets Retriever is a bioinformatics tool for cancer diagnostic dataset retrieval from the GEO website.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/App-renlikewd">App-renlikewd</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>REName a file so it becomes LIKE the current (Working) Directory's name</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/App-timeput">App-timeput</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/TULAMILI">TULAMILI</a></td>
<td>0.060</td>
<td>0.078</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/App-tjoin">App-tjoin</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/TULAMILI">TULAMILI</a></td>
<td>0.060</td>
<td>0.061</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Bencher-Scenario-BinarySearch">Bencher-Scenario-BinarySearch</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>Benchmark binary searching</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Bencher-Scenario-BinarySearch-File">Bencher-Scenario-BinarySearch-File</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>Benchmark binary searching sorted lines from a file</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Bencher-Scenarios-URI-Info">Bencher-Scenarios-URI-Info</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>Scenarios to benchmark URI::Info</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Commons-Link">Commons-Link</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SKIM">SKIM</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>TODO.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Cookie">Cookie</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/JDEGUEST">JDEGUEST</a></td>
<td>v0.1.1</td>
<td>v0.1.5</td>
<td>Cookie Object</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Cookies">Cookies</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/JDEGUEST">JDEGUEST</a></td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>Cookies API for Server &amp; Client</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/DBIx-DBFlow">DBIx-DBFlow</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/JLMARTIN">JLMARTIN</a></td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>Database development helpers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/DBIx-DBFlow-Runtime">DBIx-DBFlow-Runtime</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/JLMARTIN">JLMARTIN</a></td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>Runtime utilities for DBIx::DBFlow</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/DBIx-Spreadsheet">DBIx-Spreadsheet</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/CORION">CORION</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>Query a spreadsheet with SQL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Dancer2-Plugin-ControllerAutoload">Dancer2-Plugin-ControllerAutoload</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/GILS">GILS</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>Autoload controllers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Data-Sah-DefaultValue">Data-Sah-DefaultValue</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>Default-value rules for Data::Sah</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Data-TableData-Rank">Data-TableData-Rank</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>Add a rank column to a table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Device-Chip-Adapter-Gpiod">Device-Chip-Adapter-Gpiod</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SACAVILIA">SACAVILIA</a></td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>Device::Chip::Adapter implementation for Linux GPIO character devices</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Dyn">Dyn</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SANKO">SANKO</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>dyncall Backed FFI</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/File-Find-Rule-DjVu">File-Find-Rule-DjVu</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SKIM">SKIM</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>Common rules for searching DjVu files.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/File-Syslogger">File-Syslogger</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/VVELOX">VVELOX</a></td>
<td>v0.0.1</td>
<td>v0.0.2</td>
<td>Use POE to tail a file and read new lines into syslog.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/File-Temp-VarOptions">File-Temp-VarOptions</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>Like File::Temp, but allowing to set options with variables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Future-Workflow">Future-Workflow</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PEVANS">PEVANS</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>asynchronous workflow management using futures</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/GitHubDDL">GitHubDDL</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/MACOPY">MACOPY</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>GitDDL compatibility database migration utility when  hosted on GitHub</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Hash-Util-Exists-Tiny">Hash-Util-Exists-Tiny</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/AAHAZRED">AAHAZRED</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>Some hash helper functions related to perl's exists function.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/HealthCheck-Diagnostic-RemoteHealth">HealthCheck-Diagnostic-RemoteHealth</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/GSG">GSG</a></td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>Get results from an HTTP HealthCheck</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/IURL-XS">IURL-XS</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/BRDUCH">BRDUCH</a></td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>parsing URLs with zero-copy and no mallocs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Iterator-Breathe">Iterator-Breathe</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/GENE">GENE</a></td>
<td>0.0100</td>
<td>0.0201</td>
<td>Iterate a counter up and back</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/JSON-Schema-Modern-Document-OpenAPI">JSON-Schema-Modern-Document-OpenAPI</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/ETHER">ETHER</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.005</td>
<td>One JSON Schema document</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Math-Ryu">Math-Ryu</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SISYPHUS">SISYPHUS</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>perl interface to the ryu C library.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Module-Features-Set">Module-Features-Set</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>Features of modules that generate text tables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/MojoX-HTTP-Async">MojoX-HTTP-Async</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/CDN">CDN</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.08</td>
<td>simple package to execute multiple parallel requests to the same host</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Mojolicious-Plugin-YamlRoutes">Mojolicious-Plugin-YamlRoutes</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/HDELGADO">HDELGADO</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>Generates routes from a yaml file</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Net-RFC3161-Timestamp">Net-RFC3161-Timestamp</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/AKHUETTEL">AKHUETTEL</a></td>
<td>0.010</td>
<td>0.020</td>
<td>Utility functions to request RFC3161 timestamps</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/PERLSDK">PERLSDK</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/MAFEMBRAC">MAFEMBRAC</a></td>
<td>v1.0.1</td>
<td>v1.0.1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/PensioAPI">PensioAPI</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/MAFEMBRAC">MAFEMBRAC</a></td>
<td>1.0.1</td>
<td>1.0.1</td>
<td>Integrate AltaPay gateway with Perl projects.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Pensio">Pensio</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/MAFEMBRAC">MAFEMBRAC</a></td>
<td>1.0.1</td>
<td>1.0.1</td>
<td>Integrate AltaPay gateway with Perl projects.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/RT-Extension-ReplyWithMail">RT-Extension-ReplyWithMail</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/AVERKIOS">AVERKIOS</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>RT-Extension-ReplyWithMail Extension</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/RoleBundle-TinyCommons-Iterator">RoleBundle-TinyCommons-Iterator</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.004</td>
<td>0.004</td>
<td>Iterator roles</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/RoleBundle-TinyCommons-Tree">RoleBundle-TinyCommons-Tree</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.129</td>
<td>0.129</td>
<td>Roles related to object tree</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/SelectPdf">SelectPdf</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SELECTPDF">SELECTPDF</a></td>
<td>v1.2.0</td>
<td>v1.4.0</td>
<td>Get the result of an asynchronous call.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Task-Kramerius">Task-Kramerius</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SKIM">SKIM</a></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>Install modules for Kramerius system.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Test-Expander">Test-Expander</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/JSF">JSF</a></td>
<td>v1.0.0</td>
<td>v1.0.5</td>
<td>Expansion of test functionalities that appear to be frequently used while testing.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Test-Mock-Object">Test-Mock-Object</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/OVID">OVID</a></td>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>Dead-simple mocking</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/Tree-RB-XS">Tree-RB-XS</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/NERDVANA">NERDVANA</a></td>
<td>0.00_01</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>Red/Black Tree object withthe compatible API to Tree::RB</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/URI-Info">URI-Info</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>Extract various information from a URI (URL)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/URI-Router">URI-Router</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SYBER">SYBER</a></td>
<td>v0.1.0</td>
<td>v0.1.3</td>
<td>highest performance powerful URI router (URI path to value lookup) for HTTP frameworks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/WWW-KeePassHttp">WWW-KeePassHttp</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PETERCJ">PETERCJ</a></td>
<td>0.010</td>
<td>0.020</td>
<td>Interface with KeePass PasswordSafe through the KeePassHttp plugin</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/WebService-WsScreenshot">WebService-WsScreenshot</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SYMKAT">SYMKAT</a></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>API client For ws-screenshot</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/WebService-YTSearch">WebService-YTSearch</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/GENE">GENE</a></td>
<td>0.0100</td>
<td>0.0302</td>
<td>Search YouTube</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/release/require-relative">require-relative</a></td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/BARNEY">BARNEY</a></td>
<td>1.0.0</td>
<td>1.0.0</td>
<td>like require for relative paths</td>
</tr>
</table>
<h3>Stats</h3>
<p>Number of new CPAN distributions this period: <b>62</b></p>
<p>Number of authors releasing new CPAN distributions this period: <b>36</b></p>
<p>Authors by number of new CPAN distributions this period: </p>
<table>
<tr>
<th>No</th>
<th>Author</th>
<th>Distributions</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PERLANCAR">PERLANCAR</a></td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/MAFEMBRAC">MAFEMBRAC</a></td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SKIM">SKIM</a></td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/ZMUGHAL">ZMUGHAL</a></td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/TULAMILI">TULAMILI</a></td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/GENE">GENE</a></td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/JLMARTIN">JLMARTIN</a></td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SACAVILIA">SACAVILIA</a></td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/JDEGUEST">JDEGUEST</a></td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/AVERKIOS">AVERKIOS</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SYMKAT">SYMKAT</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/GSG">GSG</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/CORION">CORION</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/GILS">GILS</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/ETHER">ETHER</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/MACOPY">MACOPY</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/AAHAZRED">AAHAZRED</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/NERDVANA">NERDVANA</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/ERIAM">ERIAM</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/HDELGADO">HDELGADO</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>21</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/BARNEY">BARNEY</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/VVELOX">VVELOX</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>23</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SYBER">SYBER</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/JSF">JSF</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PETERCJ">PETERCJ</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>26</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/OVID">OVID</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>27</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/UTASHIRO">UTASHIRO</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>28</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SANKO">SANKO</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>29</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/PEVANS">PEVANS</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SISYPHUS">SISYPHUS</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>31</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/SELECTPDF">SELECTPDF</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>32</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/BRDUCH">BRDUCH</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>33</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/CDN">CDN</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>34</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/AKHUETTEL">AKHUETTEL</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/NEILB">NEILB</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>36</td>
<td><a href="https://metacpan.org/author/AALAMEER">AALAMEER</a></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">dist author first_version latest_version abstract API-Mathpix ERIAM 0.01 0.01 Use the API of Mathpix Acme-CPANModulesBundle-Import-DAVECROSS PERLANCAR 0.001 0.001 Acme::CPANModules::* created from DAVECROSS's posts Acme-MarkdownTest NEILB 0.01 0.02 test module to see how markdown is handled Alien-Meson ZMUGHAL 0.01 0.01 Find or build meson build tool Alien-Ninja ZMUGHAL 0.01 0.02 Find or build Ninja build tool … <a href="https://perlancar.wordpress.com/2021/12/01/list-of-new-cpan-distributions-nov-2021/" class="more-link">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">List of new CPAN distributions – Nov 2021</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>perlancar</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://perlancar.wordpress.com/?p=1957</id>
    <published>2021-12-01T00:31:10Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-01T00:31:10Z</updated>
    <category term="cpan"/>
    <category term="perl"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>#540 - 24 Pull Requests</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/540.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Hi there</p>
<p>Did you participate in <strong>Hacktoberfest 2021</strong>?</p>
<p>If not then you have one more chance to participate in the global event <a href="https://24pullrequests.com">24 Pull Requests</a>. Participation is simple, you just have to submit one pull request each day between 1st Dec 2021 and 24th Dec 2021. It is one of my favourite events. I have participated in the event each year, without a break, since 2015. I was introduced to it by <a href="http://blogs.perl.org/users/neilb/2015/11/24-pull-requests.html">Neil Bowers</a>. Last year I was going through rough patch so, unfortunately, I had to skip it. My best performance was in the year 2018 when I contributed <strong>125 pull requests</strong> in the first 24 days of December. If I am not mistaken then the <strong>24 Pull Requests</strong> event is little more relaxed as compare to <strong>Hacktoberfest</strong>. You don't have to submit a pull request every day. Instead, you can submit in bulk one day and then take a break. However, make sure you have submitted at least 24 pull requests by the end of play on 24th December.</p>
<p>Happy Hacking !!!</p>
<p>Do you follow the much-discussed <strong>Perl</strong> project <strong>Corinna</strong>?</p>
<p>The project is run by <strong>Curtis</strong> and his dedicated team of experts. I came across a <a href="https://ovid.github.io/articles/why-is-perl-not-putting-moose-in-the-core.html">blog post</a> by <strong>Curtis</strong> talking about "<strong>Why is Perl not putting Moose in the core?</strong>" There is a bold statement in the post in response to the question "<strong>What’s an Object in Perl?</strong>" and it is "<strong>Perl knows nothing about OOP. It doesn’t know what objects are.</strong>"</p>
<p><strong>Curtis</strong> doesn't say things without a reason. Please read the full blog post for more informations. I am one of the biggest followers of <strong>Curtis</strong> and never miss his posts.</p>
<p>If you remember, I mentioned <strong>Advent Calendars</strong> in the editorial of the weekly newsletter edition <a href="https://www.perlweekly.com/archive/536.html">#536</a>. Ever since then, I have noticed lots of activities in the <strong>Perl</strong> and <strong>Raku</strong> communities about <strong>Advent Calendars</strong>. I am confident this year we are going to have another fun filled <strong>Advent Calendar</strong>.</p>
<p>Last but not least, <a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org">The Weekly Challenge</a> (also known as <strong>Perl Weekly Challenge</strong>) is going to complete <strong>1000 days</strong> on <strong>18th December 2021</strong>. To celebrate the day, the team is running a <strong>FREE T-shirt</strong> campaign. If you are interested in knowing about it then please check out the <a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/1000-days">blog post</a>.</p>
<p>Stay safe and avoid the new <strong>COVID-19</strong> variant <strong>Omicron</strong>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/540.html</id>
    <published>2021-11-29T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-29T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Dancer2: Install Perl, editor, Dancer2</title>
  <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Part of the Dancer2 video course available both to <a href="/pro">Pro</a> subscribers and attendees of the <a href="https://leanpub.com/c/dancer">Perl Dancer course</a> on Leanpub.
<p>
]]></summary>
  <updated>2021-11-29T09:30:01Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://perlmaven.com/dancer2-install"/>  <id>https://perlmaven.com/dancer2-install</id>
  <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Part of the Dancer2 video course available both to <a href="/pro">Pro</a> subscribers and attendees of the <a href="https://leanpub.com/c/dancer">Perl Dancer course</a> on Leanpub.
<p>
]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Gabor Szabo</name>
    </author>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Binary Addition Simulation / Nth from a Sorted Multiplication: Table The Weekly Challenge 140</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/2021/11/28#pwc140" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The examples used here are from The Weekly Challenge problem statement and demonstrate 
the working solution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are given two decimal-coded binary numbers, $a and $b. Write a script to simulate the
addition of the given binary numbers.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;
sub add_binary{
    my($x, $y) = @_;
    my $sum = ""; 
    my @a = reverse(split(//, $x));            
    my @b = reverse(split(//, $y));            
    if(@b &gt; @a){
        my @c = @b;
        @b = @a;
        @a = @c;   
    } 
    my $carry = 0; 
    for(my $d = 0; $d &lt;= @a - 1; $d++){ 
        my $d0 = $a[$d]; 
        my $d1 = $b[$d];
        if($d1){
            $sum = "0$sum", $carry = 0 if $d0 == 1 &amp;&amp; $d1 == 1 &amp;&amp; $carry == 1;  
            $sum = "1$sum", $carry = 0 if $d0 == 1 &amp;&amp; $d1 == 0 &amp;&amp; $carry == 0; 
            $sum = "0$sum", $carry = 1 if $d0 == 1 &amp;&amp; $d1 == 1 &amp;&amp; $carry == 0; 
            $sum = "0$sum", $carry = 1 if $d0 == 0 &amp;&amp; $d1 == 1 &amp;&amp; $carry == 1; 
            $sum = "0$sum", $carry = 0 if $d0 == 0 &amp;&amp; $d1 == 0 &amp;&amp; $carry == 0; 
            $sum = "1$sum", $carry = 0 if $d0 == 0 &amp;&amp; $d1 == 0 &amp;&amp; $carry == 1; 
            $sum = "0$sum", $carry = 1 if $d0 == 1 &amp;&amp; $d1 == 0 &amp;&amp; $carry == 1; 
            $sum = "1$sum", $carry = 0 if $d0 == 0 &amp;&amp; $d1 == 1 &amp;&amp; $carry == 0; 
        } 
        else{
            $sum = "0$sum", $carry = 1, next if $d0 == 1 &amp;&amp; $carry == 1;  
            $sum = "1$sum", $carry = 0, next if $d0 == 0 &amp;&amp; $carry == 1;  
            $sum = "0$sum", $carry = 0, next if $d0 == 0 &amp;&amp; $carry == 0;  
            $sum = "1$sum", $carry = 0, next if $d0 == 1 &amp;&amp; $carry == 0;  
        }  
    } 
    $sum = "$carry$sum" if $carry == 1;  
    return $sum; 
}

MAIN:{
    print add_binary(11, 1) . "\n"; 
    print add_binary(101, 1) . "\n"; 
    print add_binary(100, 11) . "\n"; 
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-1.pl
100
110
111
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an unusual fondness for Perl's right hand conditional. But that is pretty obvious 
from the way I wrote this, right? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are given 3 positive integers, $i, $j and $k. Write a script to print the $kth 
element in the sorted multiplication table of $i and $j.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;
sub nth_from_table{
    my($i, $j, $k) = @_;
    my @table;
    for my $x (1 .. $i){
        for my $y (1 .. $j){
            push @table, $x * $y; 
        }  
    }  
    return (sort {$a &lt;=&gt; $b} @table)[$k - 1];   
} 

MAIN:{
    print nth_from_table(2, 3, 4) . "\n";  
    print nth_from_table(3, 3, 6) . "\n";  
} 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-2.pl 
3
4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full Disclosure: At first I wanted to do this in some convoluted way for fun. After
experimenting with, like, nested &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;s for a few minutes I lost all interest in "fun" and
just went with a couple of &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loops!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-140/"&gt;Challenge 140&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/perl/pwc140</id>
    <published>2021-11-28T17:16:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-11-28T17:16:00-05:00</updated>
    <category term="/perl"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Maintaining Perl 5 Core (Tony Cook): October 2021</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/maintaining_perl5_tony_cook_oct_2021"/>
  <id>tag:news.perlfoundation.org,2021-11-28:/post/maintaining_perl5_tony_cook_oct_2021</id>
  <published>2021-11-28T17:01:27</published>
  <updated>2021-11-28T17:01:27</updated>
  <summary>
  <![CDATA[
     Approximately 25 tickets were reviewed, and 3 patches were applied.  0.83 #12957 review discussion review  sdbm source, comment  1.27 #18958 look over code  #18958 review code and comment  #18958 comment  1.59 #19020 research should the shell be trapping in this  case? haven’t found anything appropriate, also look at  dash source  #19020 more dash source, comment  2.74 #19121 research and comment 
   ]]>
  </summary>
  <author>
    <name>Jason A. Crome</name>
  </author>
  <category term="Grants" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category"/>  <content type="html" xml:lang="en-us" xml:base="http://news.perlfoundation.org/">
   <![CDATA[
     
     <p>Approximately 25 tickets were reviewed, and 3 patches were
applied.
```
[Hours]         [Activity]
  0.83          #12957 review discussion (mentioned in #19182), review
                sdbm source, comment
  1.27          #18958 look over code
                #18958 review code and comment
                #18958 comment
  1.59          #19020 research - should the shell be trapping in this
                case?  haven’t found anything appropriate, also look at
                dash source
                #19020 more dash source, comment
  2.74          #19121 research and comment
                #19121 re-work
                #19121 consider alternative for the delimiter, looking
                over code
                #19121 look at a :crlf issue - is it a problem elsewhere
                cpan #133233
  0.30          #19122 apply to blead, perldelta
  1.27          #19124 debugging
  0.30          #19166 review
  0.45          #19171 review and briefly comment
                #19171 review latest changes and apply to blead
  1.22          #19172 review and a couple of brief comments
  0.30          #19174 review discussion, testing, research and comment
  2.42          #19182 review, comments
                #19182 review changes, comment
                #19182 review, testing, brief comment
  0.43          #19184 review, consider if feature regen needs some re-
                work
                #19184 briefly review
  0.60          #19186 review, research and comment
  0.62          #19187 review and approve
  0.63          #19190 review, research, briefly comment
  0.91          #19191 review and apply, also supply patch upstream and
                update customizations
                #19191 comment
  0.43          #19194 review and approve
  2.18          #19197 review, research (who wrote that test? it was me)
                and comment
                #19197 review new commits
  9.56          #19198 debugging and comment
                #19198 debugging, work on a fix, simple testing, comment
                #19198 recheck, testing, try to find good place to add
                regression test, minor perl5db.t re-work
                #19198 minor cleanup and document DebugWrap in perl5db.t,
                write test, test the test with and without the fix,
                testing
                #19198 fix global destruction issue from fix, debug
                another threads only failure and work out a fix
                #19198 polish, documentation, more testing, update PR
  0.92          review coverity reported defects, create PR #19200
  1.42          :utf8 more on re-working fill/readdelim
  0.65          :utf8 more readdelim re-work
  1.58          :utf8 work on re-working fill
  0.17          github notifications</p>

<h1>  1.07          security list: research, testing, comment</h1>

<p>33.86 hours total
```</p>

    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>#539 - Farewell to David H. Adler</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/539.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Hi</p>
<p>Really sad news: that David H. Adler, known by many as DHA has passed away. I've included a number of links where people who can express themselves way better than I do say goodbye to him.</p>
<p>In other news the ephemeral miniconf took place this week. You can read about it below.</p>
<p>Lastly, The Weekly Challenge celebrates its first 1000 days. Congratulations to Mohammad Anwar, my co-editor of the Perl Weekly for keeping up with this project!</p>
<p>Enjoy your week!</p></div>
    </content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/539.html</id>
    <published>2021-11-22T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-22T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Jort Sort the First Five Long Primes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/2021/11/21#pwc139" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The examples used here are from The Weekly Challenge problem statement and demonstrate 
the working solution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are given a list of numbers. Write a script to implement JortSort. It should return 
true/false depending if the given list of numbers are already sorted.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;
use boolean;

sub jort_sort{
    for(my $i=0; $i &lt; @_ - 1; $i++){
        return false if $_[$i + 1] &lt; $_[$i];  
    }  
    return true;
}

MAIN:{
    print jort_sort(1, 2, 3, 4, 5) . "\n";
    print jort_sort(1, 3, 2, 4, 5) . "\n";
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-1.pl
1
0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently Jort Sort is a joke sort started by somebody in the JavaScript community. I 
didn't find it all that funny, but the code to implement it only took a quick minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write a script to generate the first 5 Long Primes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="perl"&gt;
use strict;
use warnings;
use boolean;
use LWP::UserAgent;
use constant PRIME_URL =&gt; "http://primes.utm.edu/lists/small/100000.txt";

sub get_primes{
    my @primes;  
    my $ua = new LWP::UserAgent(
        ssl_opts =&gt; {verify_hostname =&gt; 0}
    );
    my $response = $ua-&gt;get(PRIME_URL);
    my @lines = split(/\n/,$response-&gt;decoded_content);
    foreach my $line (@lines){
        my @p = split(/\s+/, $line);
        unless(@p &lt; 10){
            push @primes, @p[1..(@p - 1)]; 
        }  
    }
    return @primes; 
}

sub divide{
    my($n, $d) = @_; 
    my @remainders;
    my $q = (int($n / $d)) . ".";
    my $r = $n % $d; 
    push @remainders, $r; 
    my @a;
    for (0 .. $d){
        $q .= int($r*10 / $d);  
        $r = $r*10 % $d;
        @a = grep { $remainders[$_] == $r } (0 .. @remainders - 1);
        last if(@a); 
        push @remainders, $r; 
    }
    my $r_i = $a[0];
    my $i = index($q, ".");
    my $decimal_part = substr($q, $i+1); 
    return substr($q, 0, $i + 1) . substr($decimal_part, 0, $r_i) . "(" . substr($q, $i + $r_i + 1) . ")";  
}   

sub long_primes_five{
    my @long_primes;
    my @primes = get_primes();
    do{
        my $prime = shift @primes;    
        my $max_repetend = $prime - 1; 
        my $repeats = true if($prime != 2 &amp;&amp; $prime != 5); 
        if($repeats){
            my $x = divide(1, $prime, [], []); 
            $x =~ m/\((\d+)\)/;
            my $repetend = $1;
            push @long_primes, [$prime, $x] if length($repetend) == $prime - 1;   
        }
    }while(@long_primes &lt; 5);
    return @long_primes;
}

MAIN:{
    for my $p (long_primes_five()){
        print $p-&gt;[0] . "\t" . $p-&gt;[1] . "\n";
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sample Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="shell"&gt;
$ perl perl/ch-2.pl 
7       0.(142857)
17      0.(0588235294117647)
19      0.(052631578947368421)
23      0.(0434782608695652173913)
29      0.(0344827586206896551724137931)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second part of the challenge was much more fun! Maybe my favorite part was that it 
largely re-used code from &lt;a href="http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/2021/04/04#pwc106"&gt;challenge 106&lt;/a&gt;
and also &lt;a href="https://adamcrussell.livejournal.com/5175.html"&gt;Challenge 015&lt;/a&gt;. Here we grab a 
list of pre-computed primes and then check each one for the desired property. After we 
find five, as required, we're done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://jort.technology/"&gt;Jort Sort&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/FullReptendPrime.html"&gt;Long Prime&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org/blog/perl-weekly-challenge-139/"&gt;Challenge 139&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>http://www.rabbitfarm.com/cgi-bin/blosxom/perl/pwc139</id>
    <published>2021-11-21T16:34:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-11-21T16:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <category term="/perl"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Perl Tk: Keyboard and Mouse events</title>
  <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Showing how to create to bind keyboard an mouse events to functions in a Perl Tk based application.
<p>
]]></summary>
  <updated>2021-11-21T09:00:01Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://perlmaven.com/perl-tk-keyboard-and-mouse-events"/>  <id>https://perlmaven.com/perl-tk-keyboard-and-mouse-events</id>
  <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Showing how to create to bind keyboard an mouse events to functions in a Perl Tk based application.
<p>
]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Gabor Szabo</name>
    </author>
</entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Grants: November 2021 Votes</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/grants_nov_2021_votes"/>
  <id>tag:news.perlfoundation.org,2021-11-16:/post/grants_nov_2021_votes</id>
  <published>2021-11-16T20:00:44</published>
  <updated>2021-11-16T20:00:44</updated>
  <summary>
  <![CDATA[
     The Grants Committee has concluded voting on the November 2021 round. One grant request was submitted: Grant Proposal: Optimizations building upon the new Raku dispatch mechanism VOTING RESULTS: Approved. 4 YES votes 0 NO votes, 1 ABSTAIN We accept proposals throughout the year; our next round of review will begin in January. You can submit proposals at any time. If you want to help with funding and increase our budget, 
   ]]>
  </summary>
  <author>
    <name>Jason A. Crome</name>
  </author>
  <category term="Grants" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#category"/>  <content type="html" xml:lang="en-us" xml:base="http://news.perlfoundation.org/">
   <![CDATA[
     
       <img src="_ra-rel-mnt_/simplecas/fetch_content/7f97282811f6a9f862d7e659c79e5462cc195d94/grant-funding .png" style="max-width:100%;max-height:100%;padding:20px;" /><br>
     
     <p>The Grants Committee has concluded voting on the November 2021 round. One grant request was submitted:</p>

<h4><a href="https://news.perlfoundation.org/post/grant_proposal_raku_dispatch_optimizations">Grant Proposal: Optimizations building upon the new Raku dispatch mechanism</a> (USD 12,000)</h4>

<p>VOTING RESULTS: Approved. 4 YES votes (14 points), 0 NO votes, 1 ABSTAIN</p>

<p>We accept proposals throughout the year; our next round of review will begin in January. You can <a href="https://www.perlfoundation.org/how-to-write-a-proposal.html">submit proposals</a> at any time.</p>

<p>If you want to help with funding and increase our budget, please visit our <a href="https://www.perlfoundation.org/make-a-donation.html">donations page</a>. We sincerely appreciate all the donors which make the grant program possible. If you donate, please take advantage of your employers' matching donation program.</p>

<p>As always, thanks to our <a href="https://www.perlfoundation.org/our-donors.html">donors</a>, both large and small, who support this program to give back to the community.</p>

    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
  <entry>
    <title>#538 - Are you Perl blogger?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/538.html" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Hi there</p>
<p>Going back to the editorial of last week's <a href="https://perlweekly.com/archive/537.html">edition</a> of Perl Weekly, it is still there in my head raising many questions. It is a universal fact that Perl is no longer the favourite language among the youths in college these days. I remember when I was first introduced to Perl in 1999, it was the most popular language. Being a Perl fan, I feel it is my responsibility to bring Perl back to the discussion table. One way to do that is to talk about Perl-based projects and share them with the users of other languages. I have noticed that not as many people blog about Perl as they used to in the past. Talking about blogs, I would like to thank <a href="https://theweeklychallenge.org">The Weekly Challenge</a> team for spreading the power of Perl. For the record, in the last 138 weeks, the team have created and shared over 2000 blog posts. I used to blog regularly in the past but nowadays I hardly find time. Having said that, I still wrte a monthly report blog post where I talk about Perl and my other projects. I find making a live video is less time consuming than writing a blog post. I made some and then I stopped that as well, sorry. You can take a look my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/mohammadsajidanwar">YouTube Channel</a> if you fancy. I came across series of <a href="https://perlmaven.com/beginner-perl-maven-video-course">videos</a> by Gabor Szabo teaching Perl. It is great source for someone new to Perl and explore with live action.</p>
<p>I remember, Dave Cross, wrote a <a href="https://dev.to/davorg/don-t-be-a-perl-programmer-4h2d">blog post</a> talking about something that not many people would speak about. I personally agree with him fully and believe knowing more than one programming languages helps you as a programmer. I can tell from my own experience, I picked up Raku last year while participating the weekly challenge. Whatever little I know about Raku to date, I can tell it has helped me a lot. I use that knowledge to write better Perl programs. Recently, I started writing Python as well - just the basics for now. So the question is, does knowing Raku or Python make me any less of a Perl programmer? I am still a Perl programmer and all of my thought processes still follow Perl's rules. Perl is my first love and will remain so for the rest of my life. Even today, after more than 22 years, I find features that I never knew existed before, especially in the field of regex. I would like to give credit to Abigail for sharing the magic of regex in Perl as part of his weekly contributions.</p>
<p>While talking about blogs, how can I miss those who are doing great service on a regular basis? I would like to thank <a href="https://github.polettix.it/ETOOBUSY">Flavio Poletti</a> for blogging every day for months now. Also there is another name, <a href="https://phoenixtrap.com">Mark Gardner</a>, who writes a weekly blog post. Similarly we have weekly stats by <a href="https://niceperl.blogspot.com">Miguel Prz</a>.</p>
<p>Enjoy the rest of the newsletter.</p></div>
    </content>
    <id>https://perlweekly.com/archive/538.html</id>
    <published>2021-11-15T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-15T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="list of tags?"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
  <title>Perl Tk: The label, button, and entry widgets</title>
  <summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary>
  <updated>2021-11-15T08:00:01Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://perlmaven.com/perl-tk-menu"/>  <id>https://perlmaven.com/perl-tk-menu</id>
  <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Gabor Szabo</name>
    </author>
</entry>
</feed>
